<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Vehicle Inspection</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Certification of Safety Equipment Repair Orders.</heading>
    <text>Visual Inspection and Certification of Safety Equipment Repair Orders. In accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|23-105">Transportation Article, §23-105, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Automotive Safety Enforcement Division of the Department of  State Police has established the following procedures for visual inspection and certification of certain equipment and mechanism defects on certain types of State-registered motor vehicles or trailers by the State Police and police departments.</text>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="29|02|01|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Defects Which May Be Certified by Visual Inspection.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following guidelines have been established to provide the owner of any vehicle with a means of having certified by police departments, instead of an authorized inspection station, safety equipment repair orders which contain only the defects or combination of defects listed below:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>54—Windshield wipers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>55—Headlights, but not for aim;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>56—Taillights;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>57—Horn;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>60—Bumper(s)/rear protector frames;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>61—Glass;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>62—Load cover;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>64—Stoplights;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>65—Tag light(s);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>66—Dash lights;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>68—Rearview mirrors;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>69—Door latch/handle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>70—Fuel system, cap only;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>71—Turn signals;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>73—Hood/catch(es);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>76—Fender(s) flaps;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>78—Hazard warning lamps;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>79—Parking lamps;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>80—Side marker lamps;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>82—Emergency warning lamps;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>83—Back-up lamps;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>84—Reflectors;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>86—Low air warning device;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>87—Clearance lamps;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>88—Identification lamps.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commercial Vehicle Enforcement Division of the State Police will certify visual defects on commercial vehicles over 10,000 pounds GVW only during operational hours at scale houses.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Certification of Post-Manufacture Window Tinting.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as noted in <cite path="29|02|01|.02|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite>, the Department of State Police will no longer certify post-manufacture window tinting. The certification of post-manufacture window tinting shall only be done at authorized inspection stations for that class of vehicle by a registered inspection mechanic.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The inspection and certification of post-manufacture window tinting involving a medical exemption shall be referred to the Automotive Safety Enforcement Division of the Department of State Police.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>State Police Certification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Visual inspection and certification of the defects shall be conducted at all State Police installations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Due to limited parking and traffic conditions, Barrack M, JFK Highway, is excluded from these procedures.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Other Police Department Certification.</heading>
    <text>Visual inspection and certification of the defects will be conducted by all local police departments desiring to participate in the program.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Defects Other Than Those Listed.</heading>
    <text>If a repair order contains any of the defects listed above and any other defect, the vehicle owner or agent shall be advised that certification shall be performed by an authorized inspection station for that class of vehicle.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Inspection and Certification Procedures.</heading>
    <text>All the inspections and certifications shall be performed at the installation and as follows:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>State Police Certification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Certification shall be performed by adequately trained State Police personnel. If any ASED police personnel are at an installation, they will conduct, upon request, the inspections and certifications.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All certifications shall be conducted only during daylight hours. Certifications may not be conducted during inclement weather.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon determining that the equipment or mechanism has been repaired and is in compliance with established safety standards, the certification portion of the repair order will be completed as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The signature of the member certifying the repair orders will be entered in the space for the signature of the registered mechanic or police officer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The date of inspection will be the date of the actual certification and physical inspection;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The name of the inspection station will be Department of State Police;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The station number or agency code will be the location designator assigned to the installation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The address of the inspection station will be the installation name.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>After certification:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The No. 3 (inspection station/police department) copy will be retained by the installation and routinely forwarded to the Automotive Safety Enforcement Division;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The No. 4 (owner/agent) copy will be returned to the vehicle owner or agent for his records;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The No. 5 (State Police Compliance) copy will be returned to the vehicle owner or agent to be forwarded to the Automotive Safety Enforcement Division.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Local Police Department Certification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Certification should be performed by adequately trained personnel.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At the discretion of the Department, any internal reporting procedures may be followed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All certifications shall be conducted only during daylight hours. Certifications may not be conducted during inclement weather.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Upon determining whether the equipment or mechanism has been repaired and is in compliance with safety standards, the certification portion of the repair order will be completed as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The signature of the member certifying the repair orders will be entered in the space for the signature of the registered mechanic or police officer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The date of inspection will be the date of the actual certification and physical inspection;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The name of the inspection station will be the name of the police department;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The station number or agency code will be the location designator assigned to the department;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The address of the inspection station will be the address of the installation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>After certification:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The No. 3 (inspection station/police department) copy will be retained by the installation and routinely forwarded to the Automotive Safety Enforcement Division;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The No. 4 (owner/agent) copy will be returned to the vehicle owner or agent for his records;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The No. 5 (State Police Compliance) copy will be returned to the vehicle owner or agent to be forwarded to the Automotive Safety Enforcement Division.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Defect 54—Windshield Wipers (Not Applicable to Motorcycles or Trailers).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The windshield wipers shall be inspected for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Operation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Control;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Condition of blades and arms; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any missing part.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Do not certify if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The wipers are inoperative or cannot be controlled or operated by the driver;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>There is an arm broken or missing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>There is insufficient tension on the arm to hold the blade against windshield;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The blades are excessively worn or deteriorated and do not clean the windshield;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The wipers are incapable of cleaning the original arc on the windshield; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The arms fail to return to park position.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="29|02|01|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Defects.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Defects:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>55—Headlights;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>56—Taillights;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>64—Stoplights;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>65—Tag light(s);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>78—Hazard warning lamps;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>79—Parking lamps;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>80—Side marker lamps;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>82—Emergency warning lamp;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>83—Back-up lamps;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>87—Clearance lamps;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>88—Identification lamps.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Lamps shall be of an approved type and inspected for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Proper function;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Aiming—except headlights;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Mounting;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Cracked or broken lenses.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Do not certify if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Vehicle is not equipped with minimum lamps required by State law (see Regulation .22, Diagrams 1-6);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any bulb in a lamp required to be inspected fails to function properly;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>There are improperly connected circuits;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A lens is incorrectly installed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A lens is cracked, broken, or damaged to the point that any portion of the lens is missing or cracked to a degree that a light contrary to law is exhibited (white light to the rear);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A lens marked left or right is not properly installed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A lens is rotated, upside down or wrong side out;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Any lens does not correspond with the name stamped on the light body unless it is an approved type;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>A lens is obscured or shielded by a nontransparent material or headlamp equipped with after-market clear, tinted, or screen-type cover;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Any lamp is not securely attached to the vehicle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Any lamp is emitting a color contrary to the provisions of the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> (taillights shall be red, stoplights shall be red or amber, tag lights shall be white);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Any lamp or lens is turned so that its light is not properly directed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Any lamp, lens, or reflector is not of an approved type;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Back-up lamp operates when vehicle is in forward gear; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Back-up lamp not lit when in reverse gear.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The use of tape or paint is not an approved method of repair for a cracked, broken, or damaged lens referenced in <cite path="29|02|01|.08|C.|(5)">§C(5) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Defect 57—Horn (Not Applicable to Trailers).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The horn shall be inspected for mounting and sound and have a means of sounding which is readily accessible to the operator.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Do not certify if the horn:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is loose;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fails to function;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Produces a loud or harsh sound;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Is not equipped with an actuating device within arm's reach of the operator.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Defect 60—Bumpers, Rear Protector Frame (Not Applicable to Motorcycles).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Bumpers shall be inspected for broken or missing parts, abnormal protrusions, and sharp edges or conditions that could be hazardous to persons.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The bumpers shall be securely mounted to the vehicle and shall be capable of absorbing a reasonable degree of impact.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Bumpers shall be the original equipment or equivalent to it and extend to the extreme sides of the vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Bumper extensions or modifications to compensate for suspension changes are not acceptable on:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Class A passenger vehicles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Class M multipurpose vehicles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Mandatory front bumpers of class E 1/2 and 3/4 ton trucks; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Rear bumpers of class E 1/2 and 3/4 ton trucks, even though rear bumpers are not required on this type of truck.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Each truck with a gross vehicle weight registered over 10,000 pounds, except truck tractors and vehicles engaged in drive-away/tow-away operations, and every trailer or semitrailer with a gross weight of 3,000 pounds or more to be operated upon a highway shall be equipped with a permanent metal frame or bumper attached to the underside of the rear of the vehicle. The bumper or rear protector frame may not be any wider than the width of the vehicle. It may not be more than 30 inches above the highway when moving, and shall be constructed of heavy gauge steel. The maximum transverse distance from the widest part of the vehicle at the rear to the frame or bumper may not exceed 18 inches. The frame shall be constructed so as not to interfere with lights or other warning devices.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Any truck, trailer, or semitrailer so constructed and maintained that the body, chassis, or other parts of it afford the protection required by this regulation shall be considered to be in compliance with this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The provisions of this regulation may not apply to truck tractors, pole trailers, vehicles engaged in drive-away/tow-away operations, or to vehicles where the installation of the required frame would prevent operation of the vehicle in its designed use.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Do not certify if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The bumpers are broken or missing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>There are abnormal protrusions or conditions which could be hazardous to persons;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The bumpers are not mounted securely or capable of absorbing a reasonable degree of impact;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The bumpers are not the original equipment or equivalent, or do not extend the full width of the vehicle except that front bumpers on vehicles over 10,000 pounds gross vehicle weight registered, except school vehicles, need not extend to extreme sides of the vehicle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The bumpers are modified or extended to compensate for suspension changes or modifications (applicable to class A passenger, class M multipurpose, and class E 1/2 and 3/4 ton trucks);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The bumpers or the vehicle frame side rail are higher from the ground than 20 inches for class A passenger vehicles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The bumpers or the vehicle frame side rail are higher from the ground than 28 inches for class E 1/2 and 3/4 ton trucks and class M vehicles (if class E 1/2 or 3/4 ton trucks do not have a rear bumper then the bottom of the frame side rails may not be higher from the ground than 28 inches);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Trailers or semitrailers are not equipped with a rear protector frame as required;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The bumper, rear protector frame, or the vehicle frame side rail is higher from the ground than 30 inches for trucks and multipurpose passenger vehicles with a gross vehicle weight registered over 10,000 pounds and trailers and semitrailers with a gross weight of 3,000 pounds or more; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>On a truck used for spraying agriculture crops, the bumper, rear protector frame, or the vehicle frame side rail is higher from the ground than 32 inches.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="29|02|01|.11">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Defect 61—Glass (Not Applicable to Trailers).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Vehicle Glazing — Windshield, Side and Rear Windows.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All glazing material shall be checked for the manufacturer's trademark and the words "American Standard" or the letters "AS" followed by a number indicating the positions in the vehicle in which the material may be used. Reference American National Standard for Safety Glazing Materials for Glazing Motor Vehicles and Motor Vehicle Equipment Operating on Land Highways — Safety Standard, Standard ANSI/SAE Z26.1-1996, Approved by American National Standards Institute (August 11, 1997).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All glass used in the windshield shall be marked AS-1, in addition to the trademark or name of the manufacturer. AS-2 glass may be used in any other position on the vehicle other than the windshield. In some earlier models or foreign cars, the windshield marking does not contain the designation AS-1. However, if the windshield glass is approved by the U.S. D.O.T. for highway use, it shall be acceptable under these standards.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any questions regarding glazing shall be referred to the Automotive Safety Enforcement Division of the Department of State Police.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Acute area" means that windshield area 8 inches wide by 5 inches high located directly in front of the driver, centered vertically on the steering wheel of the vehicle and horizontally in the center of the critical area.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Cloudiness" means any degree of visible discoloration or separation, except tinting that does not affect clear vision.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Critical area" means the normal windshield wiper sweep, except the area obscured by the hood, fenders, or rearview mirror.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Discoloration" means a condition which impairs the transparency of the glazing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Noncritical area" means all windshield area outside the critical area.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Normal windshield wiper sweep" means the area of the windshield cleaned by the windshield wiper, excluding the return position on both passenger's and driver's sides.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Windshield — Driver's Side. Do not certify if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Cloudiness exceeds 1 inch from the top or side or 1 inch into the critical area from the bottom or, if the windshield is divided, exceeds 1/2 inch from the center divider;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The acute area contains any one crack, nick, pit, chip, star break, half moon, or bull's-eye fracture in excess of 1/4 inch in diameter or length, or any combination of individual cracks, nicks, pits, chips, star breaks, half moons, or bull's-eye fractures which cumulatively exceed 1/4 inch in diameter or length, or any permanent condition which significantly interferes with the driver's vision;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The critical area contains wiper blade scratches which are severe enough to distort vision, or any one crack, nick, pit, chip, star break, half moon, or bull's-eye fracture in excess of 1/2 inch in diameter or length, or any combination of individual cracks, nicks, pits, chips, star breaks, half moons, or bull's-eye fractures which cumulatively exceed 1/2 inch in diameter or length, or any permanent condition which significantly interferes with the driver's vision except in the permitted cloudy area; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The noncritical area contains any intersecting cracks or any one crack or combination of individual cracks extending inward more than 2 inches separately or cumulatively from the outer frame on flat or curved windshields or over 4 inches on wraparound windshields, or any one crack, nick, pit, chip, star break, half moon, or bull's-eye fracture in excess of 3/4 inch in diameter or length, or any combination of individual cracks, nicks, pits, chips, star breaks, half moons, or bull's-eye fractures which cumulatively exceed 3/4 inch in diameter or length, or any permanent condition which significantly interferes with the driver's vision except in the permitted cloudy area.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Windshield — Passenger's Side. Do not certify if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Cloudiness exceeds 2 inches from the top or side or extends more than 2 inches into the critical area from the bottom or, if the windshield is divided, exceeds 1/2 inch from the center divider;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The critical area contains wiper blade scratches which are severe enough to distort vision, or any one crack, nick, pit, chip, star break, half moon, or bull's-eye fracture in excess of 1/2 inch in diameter or length, or any combination of individual cracks, nicks, pits, chips, star breaks, half moons, or bull's-eye fractures which cumulatively exceed 1/2 inch in diameter or length, or any permanent condition  which significantly interferes with the driver's vision except in the permitted cloudy area;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The noncritical area contains any intersecting cracks or any one crack or combination of individual cracks extending inward more than 4 inches separately or cumulatively from the outer frame on flat or curved windshields or over 6 inches on wraparound windshields, or any one crack, nick, pit, chip, star break, half moon, or bull's-eye fracture in excess of 1-1/2 inches in diameter or length, or any combination of individual cracks, nicks, pits, chips, star breaks, half moons, or bull's-eye fractures which cumulatively exceed 1-1/2 inches in diameter or length, or any permanent condition which significantly interferes with the driver's vision except in the permitted cloudy area.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The windshield and all windows shall be inspected for cracks, sharp edges, obstructions, discoloration, modification, unauthorized material, proper glazing material, and conditions which interfere with vision. Do not certify if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>There are breaks, cracks, discolorations, modifications, or scratches in the windshield (see Regulation .22, diagram 7);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The window on the driver's side of the vehicle does not open and close as designed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any window shows sharp edges, is badly scratched, broken, discolored, modified, has been replaced with other than proper safety glazing material, or shows conditions which interfere with vision;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Posters, stickers, or other nontransparent materials on the windshield or other windows of the vehicle are in violation of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Except as provided in <cite path="29|02|01|.11|E.|(4)|(b)">§E(4)(b) of this regulation</cite>, a vehicle may not be equipped with any sign, poster, card, sticker, or other nontransparent material on the windshield, side wings, or side or rear windows of the vehicle.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>This does not apply to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Materials placed on the windshield or rear window, within a 7-inch square area in the lower corner, or on the side windows of the vehicle to the rear of the driver, if the materials are placed so as not to interfere with the driver's clear view of traffic;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Direction, destination, or termini signs on any passenger common carrier motor vehicle;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>An electronic toll collection device placed in the windshield of a vehicle in accordance with guidelines established by the Maryland Transportation Authority; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Security stickers authorized by a federal or State government agency that measure not more than 2 inches high and not more than 4 inches long, and are placed at the upper edge of the center of the windshield;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>All vehicles equipped with permitted signs, posters, cards, stickers or other nontransparent materials on windows to the rear of the driver must be equipped with an outside rearview mirror on each side; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The vehicle is designed to obstruct visibility and is not equipped with an outside rearview mirror on both sides.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Tinting.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as noted in <cite path="29|02|01|.11|F.|(2)">§F(2) of this regulation</cite>, the certification of post-manufacture window tinting shall only be performed at authorized inspection stations for that class of vehicle by a registered inspection mechanic.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The inspection and certification of post-manufacture window tinting involving a medical exemption shall be referred to the Automotive Safety Enforcement Division of the Department of State Police. Regulations governing the application of post-manufacture window tinting on vehicles and the requirements for a medical exemption are listed in §F(3)—(7) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Post-manufacture window tint is acceptable on the following vehicles in the listed locations:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Passenger cars, convertibles, and station wagons:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>All side and rear windows of these vehicles are regulated windows requiring at least 35 percent light transmittance after the application of post-manufacture window tint and the vehicle is equipped with an outside rearview mirror on each side.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Post-manufacture window tint may not be applied to the windshield below the AS1 line or below 5 inches from the top of the windshield, whichever is less.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Light trucks, vans, and multipurpose passenger vehicles except multipurpose passenger vehicles noted in <cite path="29|02|01|.11|F.|(4)">§F(4) of this regulation</cite>:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>All side windows of these vehicles to the immediate right and left of the driver are regulated windows requiring at least 35 percent light transmittance after the application of post-manufacture window tint.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Post-manufacture window tint may not be applied to the windshield below the AS1 line or below 5 inches from the top of the windshield, whichever is less.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Windows of these vehicles to the rear of the driver may be tinted with post-manufacture window tint to any degree of darkness.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>When equipped with permitted post-manufacture window tint on any side or rear window, the vehicle must be equipped with an outside rearview mirror on each side.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Post-manufacture window tint is prohibited on the following vehicles in the listed locations:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The application of post-manufacture window tint to the windshield or windows to the immediate right and left of the driver is prohibited on the following vehicles:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Trucks over 10,000 pounds GVWR, truck tractors, and buses;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Multipurpose passenger vehicles which have a seating capacity for 16 or more passengers including the driver, or were previously registered as a school vehicle or a passenger bus, and used to primarily transport passengers, or exceed 10,000 pounds GVWR and are used in the furtherance of a commercial enterprise; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Limousines.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Windows of these vehicles to the rear of the driver may be tinted with post-manufacture window tint to any degree of darkness provided the vehicle is equipped with an outside rearview mirror on each side.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The application of post-manufacture window tint is prohibited on all windows and the windshield of a school vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The following post-manufacture window tint is prohibited on any window or windshield of any vehicle:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A mirrored, one-way vision, or sparkling effect tint;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A red, yellow, or amber color tint; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Changes to a red, yellow, or amber color tint.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Medical Exemption. <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|22-406">Transportation Article, §22-406, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, provides an exemption for a person who must be protected from the sun for medical reasons from having a light transmittance of at least 35 percent on regulated windows equipped with post-manufacture window tint. The law requires the owner to have, in the vehicle at the time the vehicle is stopped by a police officer, a written certification that details the owner's medical need for tinted windows, from a physician licensed to practice medicine in the State. A vehicle owner whose vehicle is undergoing an inspection, or has been issued a safety equipment repair order for defect #61 "TINT", and indicates to the authorized inspection station their compliance with a medical exemption, shall be referred to the Automotive Safety Enforcement Division of the Department of State Police for examination of the vehicle owner's medical documentation and the vehicle's post-manufacture window tint. If the owner meets the requirements specified in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|22-406">Transportation Article, §22-406, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, for the medical exemption and the vehicle is compliant with all post-manufacture window tinting regulations in this chapter, excluding the light transmittance requirement of regulated windows equipped with post-manufacture window tint, the Division shall be authorized to certify the safety equipment repair order for defect #61 "TINT". A medical exemption is not applicable to vehicles listed in §F(4) and (5) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Defect 62—Load Cover.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Covers shall be inspected for presence, size, condition, and proper mounting.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Securement hardware shall be inspected for presence and condition.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Do not certify if the cover:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is missing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Does not fully cover the top of the vehicle bed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Contains a hole, rip, tear, or broken mesh which would permit any part of the load to blow, fall, or spill from the bed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Is not securely attached to the bed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Do not certify the load cover if the securement hardware is missing, broken, or damaged.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Defect 66—Dash Lights (Not Applicable to Trailers).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Dash lights shall be of an approved type and inspected for proper function and illumination of operational instruments.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Do not certify if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Any bulb in a lamp required to be inspected fails to function properly;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>There are improperly connected circuits;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The instrument panel is not lighted sufficiently to permit the operator to view the operational instruments of the vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Defect 68 — Rearview Mirror (Not Applicable to Trailers).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Mirrors shall be inspected for mounting and providing proper view to the rear.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Do not certify if the inside mirror:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is loosely mounted;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Does not provide a clear view of the highway at least 200 feet to the rear;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is cracked, broken, has sharp edges, or is clouded to the extent that rear vision is obscured;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Is very difficult to adjust or will not maintain a set adjustment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Do not certify if the outside mirror:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is loose enough that rear vision is impaired;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is obscured by the windshield pillar;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is cracked, pitted, or clouded to the extent that rear vision is obscured.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Do not certify a motorcycle if it is not equipped with two rearview mirrors, one on left and one on right handlebar, with a reflective area of at least 7 square inches each. Mirrors on 1978 or newer motorcycles with a plane surface shall have at least 12.5 square inches of reflective surface or, if convex, at least 10 square inches of reflective surface. The mirrors shall be securely mounted, regular in shape (circular, oval, rectangular, or square) and may not contain sharp edges, projections, or irregular indents capable of producing injury.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Defect 69—Door Latch and Door Handle (Not Applicable to Motorcycles or Trailers).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A door latch and door handle shall be inspected for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Operation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ability to work freely and cleared of obstruction; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Ability to hold the door tightly closed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Electric push button or ring and cable means of opening the door are acceptable provided they are readily accessible.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Do not certify if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The door handles are missing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The latches are inoperative;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The door has broken hinges;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The doors are wired or held closed by any means not equivalent to the original design.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Defect 70—Fuel System (Applicable to Fuel Tank Cap Only).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The fuel tank cap shall be inspected for proper fit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Do not certify if the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Fuel tank cap is not a proper fit; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fuel tank cap is missing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Defect 71—Turn Signals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Directional signals shall be of an approved type and inspected for functioning, mounting, color, and positioning. This includes motorcycles if equipped with signals. Motorcycles manufactured after January 1973 shall be equipped with turn signals.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Do not certify if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The lamp is not an approved type;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The lamp is not in an approved position (see Regulation .22, diagrams 1-6):</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The lamp is not functioning properly;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The lamp is not properly directed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The lamp is not clearly visible;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The lamp has a cracked or broken lens;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The operating system is not of an approved type;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The operating system is not functioning properly;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>A self-cancelling mechanism does not function properly;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>A 1962 or newer model is not equipped with approved turn signals.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Defect 73—Hood and Hood Catches (Not Applicable to Trailers and Motorcycles).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Hood and hood catches shall be inspected for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Coverage of engine compartment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Attachment to the vehicle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Height of air scoop;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Type of latch and keeper; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Operating condition of same.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Do not certify if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The hood does not cover at least the top of the engine compartment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The hood is attached by a means other than the original design or equivalent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The air scoop or bubble is higher than 1/3 the vertical height of the windshield (see Regulation .22, diagram 8);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The hood latch or keeper is not original equipment or equivalent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The hood is not equipped with a safety latch;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The latch or keeper is not in proper operating condition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The latch fails to hold the hood securely closed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An acceptable hood latch or keeper is a stud and safety pin type that requires pressure to be applied to remove the pin.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Defect 76—Fenders and Flaps.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Fenders shall be securely attached to the vehicle and inspected for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Tears;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sharp or jagged edges;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Sufficient coverage of the wheel and tire, both from the body outward and to the front and rear of tires and wheels.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Buses or commercial motor vehicles, including semitrailers and trailers, shall be equipped with suitable metal protectors or substantial flexible flaps behind the rear-most wheels of the vehicle or combination to prevent the projection of rocks, dirt, water, or other substances to the rear and to minimize side spray.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>This regulation may not apply to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Any farm tractor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any vehicle registered as a farm truck;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Uncoupled truck tractors;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Pole trailers; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Other vehicles where the construction is such that complete freedom around the wheel area is necessary to secure the designed use of the vehicle (see Regulation .22, diagrams 9-11).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Do not certify if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The fender has tears, sharp or jagged edges;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The fender is not securely fastened to the body;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The fender does not extend outward from the body to cover the top of the wheel and tire;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The rear of all fenders does not extend downward to the horizontal centerline of the wheel (extreme bottom edge of fender or rear quarter panel);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The front of all fenders does not extend forward to at least within a 45-degree angle of the horizontal centerline;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Fenders have been extended downward to compensate for suspension modifications;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A motorcycle rear fender is improperly mounted or missing (front fender is not required);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A commercial vehicle or trailer is not equipped with flaps as required.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Fenders may be extended outward to compensate for tire or wheel changes provided the extension:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provides required coverage of wheels and tires;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is constructed of substantial materials;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is securely attached to the fenders;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Has all edges rolled to eliminate sharp or jagged edges.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.20</num>
    <heading>Defect 84—Reflectors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Every motor vehicle, trailer, and semitrailer shall be equipped on the rear with two or more red reflectors in addition to, or as a part of, the tail lamps. However, motorcycles need only be equipped with one reflector. Buses and trucks, trailers, and semitrailers 80 inches or more in overall width shall also be equipped on each side with two reflectors: one amber at or near the front, and one red at or near the rear. Motor vehicles, trailers, semitrailers, and pole trailers 30 feet or more in overall length shall be equipped on each side with one amber reflector centrally located with respect to the length of the vehicle. Pole trailers shall be equipped with one amber reflector at or near the front of the load.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Do not certify if the reflector is missing, broken, or obscured from view.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.21</num>
    <heading>Defect 86—Low Air Warning Device.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation is applicable to all vehicles equipped with an air braking system.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The warning device, or devices, shall signal low air pressure in the braking system.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Do not certify if a warning device fails to function when air pressure falls below 60 psi.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.22</num>
    <heading>Diagrams.</heading>
    <text>See Diagram 1</text>
    <text>See Diagram 2</text>
    <text>See Diagram 3</text>
    <text>See Diagram 4</text>
    <text>See Diagram 5</text>
    <text>See Diagram 6</text>
    <text>See Diagram 7</text>
    <text>See Diagram 8</text>
    <text>See Diagram 9</text>
    <text>See Diagram 10</text>
    <text>See Diagram 11</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">
      <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|23-105">Transportation Article, §23-105, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>
    </annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-05-14">Effective date: May 14, 1975 (2:10 Md. R. 759)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-10-03">Regulation .02A amended effective October 3, 1988 (15:20 Md. R. 2334)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-10-03">Regulation .03B amended effective October 3, 1988 (15:20 Md. R. 2334)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-10-03">Regulation .05 amended effective October 3, 1988 (15:20 Md. R. 2334)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-10-03">Regulation .06 amended effective October 3, 1988 (15:20 Md. R. 2334)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-10-03">Regulation .08A and B amended effective October 3, 1988 (15:20 Md. R. 2334)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-10-03">Regulation .10E, F, G, and H amended effective October 3, 1988 (15:20 Md. R. 2334)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-10-03">Regulation .11A and E amended effective October 3, 1988 (15:20 Md. R. 2334)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-10-03">Regulation .18 amended effective October 3, 1988 (15:20 Md. R. 2334)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-10-03">Regulation .19 adopted effective October 3, 1988 (15:20 Md. R. 2334)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" discontinuity="true" effective="1993-10-25">Chapter revised effective October 25, 1993 (20:21 MD. R. 1655)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" discontinuity="true">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|12.06.01">COMAR 12.06.01</cite> to <cite path="|29.02.01">29.02.01</cite>, July 1994</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2012-02-01">Regulation .01 amended effective February 1, 2012 (39:1 Md. R. 21)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-08-28">Regulation .02C adopted effective August 28, 1995 (22:17 Md. R. 1322)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2012-02-01">Regulation .02C amended effective September 30, 2002 (29:19 Md. R. 1526); February 1, 2012 (39:1 Md. R. 21)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-08-28">Regulation .06 amended effective August 28, 1995 (22:17 Md. R. 1322)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-08-28">Regulation .10H amended effective August 28, 1995 (22:17 Md. R. 1322)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2012-02-01">Regulation .11 amended effective February 1, 2012 (39:1 Md. R. 21)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-08-28">Regulation .11C, F amended effective August 28, 1995 (22:17 Md. R. 1322)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2012-02-01">Regulation .14D amended effective February 1, 2012 (39:1 Md. R. 21)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
