<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General Inspection</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|14|01|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In <cite path="|11.14">COMAR 11.14</cite>.01-11.14.06 and <cite path="|11.14.09">11.14.09</cite>, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the State Motor Vehicle Administration of the Maryland Department of Transportation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Authorized dealer" means a Maryland dealer licensed as a truck inspection station.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Authorized inspection station" means a facility which has been licensed to perform inspections on, issue certificates to, or certify safety equipment repair orders for a specific class of vehicle. The following classes of stations are authorized to inspect the types of vehicles listed and any other type of vehicle authorized by the Division:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A—passenger vehicles, limousines, low speed vehicles, recreational motor homes, trucks 10,000 pounds and under GVWR, trailers not equipped with air brakes, up to 20 feet in length, and multipurpose passenger vehicles, except 3-wheeled multipurpose vehicles;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>B—any trailer, including those equipped with air brakes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>C—trucks, truck tractors, buses, recreational motor homes, converted buses, and limousines over 10,000 pounds GVWR;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>D—combination of Classes B and C;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>F—fleet (must own, operate, or control at least 15 vehicles);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>M—motorcycles and 3-wheeled multipurpose vehicles, and trailers 20 feet or less in length, if the trailers are not equipped with air brakes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>R—recreational motor homes and converted buses;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>T—any trailer up to 10,000 pounds GVWR not equipped with air brakes; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>G—combination of Classes R and T.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Bed" means the load-carrying part temporarily or permanently attached to a vehicle and separated from the passenger compartment and fully enclosed on both sides by sideboards or side panels, on the front by a board or panel or by the cab of the vehicle and, on the rear, by a tailgate, board, or panel.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Controller" means an individual who has submitted a Division application, passed a written examination administered by the Division, and been approved by the Division to control the dispensing of inspection certificates to registered inspection mechanics at an authorized inspection station.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Conviction" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-110">Transportation Article, §11-110, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Covert vehicle" means a vehicle used by the Division to monitor compliance with <cite path="|11.14">COMAR 11.14</cite>.01-11.14.06 and <cite path="|11.14.09">11.14.09</cite>, by authorized inspection station personnel.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Covert Vehicle Inspection.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Covert vehicle inspection" means the submission of a covert vehicle to an authorized inspection station for inspection.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Covert vehicle inspection may include the presentation of a fictitious safety equipment repair order written for the purpose of covert investigation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Dealer" means a dealer who is licensed in this State under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Title 15 of the Transportation Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Division" means the Automotive Safety Enforcement Division of the Department of State Police.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Enclosures" means the front, rear, and sides of a vehicle bed as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|24-106">Transportation Article, §24-106</cite>.1(d)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Facility" means a dealer, vehicle repair garage, repair shop, or gasoline service station.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Fictitious safety equipment repair order" means a safety equipment repair order that is an authentic document, prepared by Division personnel, containing information that may be fabricated for the purpose of submission for inspection and compliance with COMAR.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"GVWR" means the gross vehicle weight rating as determined by the manufacturer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"Inspection certificate" means a written certification by an inspection station that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Certifies that, as of its date, a specified vehicle meets or exceeds the standards for equipment established in these regulations; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is signed and dated on behalf of the inspection station by the registered individual who personally inspected the vehicle.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"Licensee" means the owner of a private business, all partners of a partnership and, in cases of corporations, the corporate officer or person with written power of attorney or any other representative of the corporation as defined under Regulation .02A(3) of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>"Limousine" means a vehicle that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has been modified or stretched for transportation of passengers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is driven as part of a service provided by a person that advertises itself as a provider of limousine services or registers with the Public Service Commission as a provider of limousine services; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is equipped with amenities not normally provided in passenger cars, including a custom interior, television, video cassette recorder, musical sound system, telephone, ice storage area, additional interior lighting, and driver-passenger communication such as an intercom or power-operated driver partition.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>"Load cover" means a device made of canvas or other type material and used to enclose the open top of a vehicle bed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>"Loose material" means loose material as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|24-106">Transportation Article, §24-106</cite>.1(a), Annotated Code of Maryland, and <cite path="11.15.20.01">COMAR 11.15.20.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>"Low speed vehicle" means a four-wheeled electric vehicle that has a maximum speed capability that exceeds 20 miles per hour but is less than 25 miles per hour.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>"Modular home trailer" means a trailer manufactured solely for the purpose of transporting modular homes or portions of modular homes. These vehicles may be inspected if they are overwidth or overlength, provided a permit has been issued by the State Highway Administration permitting movement on the highway.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>"Motorcycle" means a motor vehicle that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has motive power;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has a seat or saddle for the use of the rider;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is designed to travel:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>On not more than three wheels in contact with the ground; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>At speeds exceeding 35 miles per hour; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Is of a type required to comply with all motor vehicle safety standards applicable to motorcycles under federal law.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>"Multipurpose passenger vehicle" means a motor vehicle that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is designed primarily for carrying persons which is constructed on a truck chassis or with special features for occasional off-road operations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has 3 wheels; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is of unique design that does not clearly meet the requirements of any other class as determined by the Division, except 4-wheel drive passenger vehicles (sedans, convertibles, and station wagons).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>"Police officer" means a uniformed police officer or a civilian employee of the Department of State Police as defined in Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-147">11-147</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|23-101">23-101</cite>(g), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>"Post manufacture window tint inspection report" means a form that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has been approved by the Division;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has been completed by a registered inspection mechanic of an authorized inspection station approved to inspect post manufacture vehicle window tint; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Includes owner and vehicle information and light transmittance readings of regulated windows equipped with post manufacture window tint.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>"Post manufacture window tint medical exemption form" means a form issued by the Division for the purpose of providing notification and documentation to an authorized inspection station performing an inspection of a vehicle that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is owned by a person who must be protected from the sun for medical reasons and has been determined by the Division that the owner has met the medical exemption requirements established in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|22-406">Transportation Article, §22-406, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Excluding the light transmittance requirement, is compliant with all other post manufacture window tinting regulations under this subtitle.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>"Rebuilding" means the restoring of a salvage vehicle as set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-506">Transportation Article, §13-506, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or a vehicle which is inoperable because of the need for major or extensive repairs to the body, frame, suspension, engine, or drive train.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>"Registered inspection mechanic" means an individual who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has passed the appropriate written test;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has demonstrated proficiency with inspection and test equipment; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is not under any type of administrative sanctions.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(29)</num>
        <text>"SAE" means the Society of Automotive Engineers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30)</num>
        <text>"Safety equipment repair order (SERO)" means a written directive ordering repair of defective equipment on a specified vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(31)</num>
        <text>Second-Stage Manufacturer.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Second-stage manufacturer" means a licensed second-stage manufacturer as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|15-201">Transportation Article, §15-201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Second-stage manufacturer" includes a person who works on an incomplete vehicle so that it becomes a complete vehicle in accordance with <cite path="|11.15.27">COMAR 11.15.27</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|15-201">Transportation Article, §15-201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(32)</num>
        <text>"Securement hardware" means any device or equipment used to attach or secure a cover on a vehicle bed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(33)</num>
        <text>"Specially constructed vehicle" means a vehicle which was not originally constructed under a distinctive name, make, model, or type by a generally recognized manufacturer of vehicles and has not been materially altered from its original construction, including kit cars and replicas of previously manufactured vehicles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(34)</num>
        <text>"State police" means the Maryland State Police.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(35)</num>
        <text>"Supervisor" means an individual who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has submitted a Division application, passed a written examination administered by the Division, and been approved by the Division to act on behalf of a licensee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is responsible for and supervises the daily operation of the inspection program at the licensee's facility.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(36)</num>
        <text>Vehicle.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Vehicle" means, except as otherwise provided in this regulation, any vehicle registered or to be registered in this State as:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Class A (passenger) vehicle;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Class E (truck) vehicle;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Class F (tractor) vehicle;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Class G (trailer) vehicle;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Class J (vanpool) vehicle;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Class M (multipurpose) vehicle;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Class B (for hire) vehicle;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Class D (motorcycle) vehicle;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Class Q (limousine) vehicle;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>For the purpose of load covers required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|24-106">Transportation Article, §24-106</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, any vehicle as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-176">Transportation Article, §11-176, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xi)</num>
            <text>For the purpose of safety equipment repair orders only, any motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer, except as provided in <cite path="11|14|01|.01|B.|(36)|(b)">§B(36)(b) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Vehicle" does not include any Class L (historic) vehicle, Class N (street rod) vehicle, or trailer which is a mobile home as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-134">Transportation Article, §11-134, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(37)</num>
        <text>"Vehicle inspection handbook" means copies of regulations governing motor vehicle inspection which have been compiled in a handbook obtained from the Office of the Secretary of State, Division of State Documents, for the State of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Licensing Requirements for Facilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An application for an authorized inspection station license or renewal shall be submitted on a complete and legible form and signed in ink by the licensee, and accompanied by the fee set forth in <cite path="|11.11.05">COMAR 11.11.05</cite>, as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Private business—shall be signed by the owner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Partnership—shall be signed by all partners;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Corporation—shall be signed by a corporate officer or person with written power of attorney which shall either accompany the application or be on file with the Division.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Applications will not be accepted from any applicant who has been in business at that location for less than 6 months except:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Previously licensed facilities which have changed location;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Additional locations of existing or established businesses which have one or more branches licensed as authorized inspection stations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A dealer licensed by the Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>When adequate documentation of previous business operational experience is presented, the Division Commander may waive the 6-month waiting period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|14|01|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Personnel Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Hours of Operation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Inspection stations shall have regular daytime business hours Monday through Friday from at least 8 a.m. to 4 p.m.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Inspection stations may adjust their regular business days in the best interests of the State and the public on written approval from the Division.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Inspection Mechanic Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each licensee open to the public shall have available for duty during regular daytime business hours at least one full-time registered inspection mechanic at each authorized inspection station who shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Have successfully submitted an application for registered inspection mechanic which is complete, legible, bearing the applicant's signature in ink, and accompanied by the fee set forth in <cite path="|11.11.05">COMAR 11.11.05</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be at least 18 years old; or at least 17 years old and possess a certificate of satisfactory completion of an automotive mechanic's course from an accredited Maryland high school or its equivalent;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Have a minimum of 12 months' general motor vehicle repair experience;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Be thoroughly familiar with the contents of the Vehicle Inspection Handbook;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Possess a valid driver's license issued in the applicant's name for the class of vehicle to be driven in the course of inspection;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Receive a grade of at least 80 on the administrative part of the examination given by the Division and each part of the examination applying to the class of vehicle on which the applicant will be performing inspections;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Be reexamined if inactive for more than 6 months and be subject to periodic reexamination as required by the Division;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Be capable of performing and passing a demonstrated ability exam as required and prescribed by the Division;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Be capable of road testing the motor vehicle as part of the inspection procedure;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Be responsible for and capable of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Performing partial and complete inspections;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Completing all inspection certificates and safety equipment repair orders; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Maintaining records pertaining to all complete or partial inspections that the mechanic performs; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Refrain from the use, or being under the influence, of alcoholic beverages or controlled dangerous substances (CDS) during work hours.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Under <cite path="11|14|01|.03|B.|(1)|(f)">§B(1)(f) of this regulation</cite>, an approved inspection mechanic need only take those parts of the examination for the additional vehicle class or classes for which the inspection mechanic is seeking to be approved with a grade of at least 80 for each additional part or parts. Three consecutive failures of the written examination shall require at least a 6-month waiting period before any subsequent written examination may be taken.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Under <cite path="11|14|01|.03|B.|(1)|(h)">§B(1)(h) of this regulation</cite>, in cases when a written examination is required, or upon transfer from one authorized inspection station to another, the Division may require a registered inspection mechanic to pass the demonstrated ability exam. Three consecutive failures of any demonstrated ability exam shall require at least a 6-month waiting period before any subsequent exam. Demonstrated ability exams will be administered by the trooper or civilian employee of the Division assigned supervision of the station where the individual is employed only on routine station visit days and reexamination after failure will be conducted upon the next routine station visit, unless exigent circumstances exist.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Registered inspection mechanics may only be registered at one authorized inspection station on a full-time basis.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Controller Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant/licensee shall designate a controller to control inspection certificates within the facility who shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be approved by the Division to function in that capacity after successfully submitting a Division application and passing a written Supervisor/Controller Examination administered by the Division;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be authorized to receive inspection certificates from the Division;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Be responsible for issuing in strict numerical sequence all inspection certificates to registered inspection mechanics upon satisfactory completion of inspection;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Assure that all certificates contain the date the vehicle is fully certified and are issued before the vehicle leaves the facility premises;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Maintain strict security of all unused inspection certificates in a locked desk, cabinet, or safe, and assure that only designated personnel have access to the unused inspection certificates; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Have all records of inspections available at the facility during normal working hours that may be removed by Division personnel as needed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Supervisor Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant/licensee shall designate supervisory personnel who shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be approved by the Division to function in that capacity after successfully submitting a Division application and passing a written Supervisor/Controller Examination administered by the Division; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be responsible for and supervise the daily operation of the inspection program at the licensee's facility.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Administrative Penalties.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The registration under Regulation .03 of this chapter may be refused, revoked, or suspended if the registered inspection mechanic, controller, supervisor, or inspection station licensee, has committed any of the following offenses:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Misrepresentation or falsification of facts;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Failure to comply with any requirements of these regulations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Performing inspection or certifying a vehicle for which the mechanic is not registered to inspect, except for defects indicated on a SERO which can be visually certified;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Issuing an inspection certificate for a vehicle without having inspected its equipment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Issuing a repair order certification for any specified equipment without having inspected that equipment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Issuing an inspection certificate for a vehicle for which the equipment does not meet or exceed the standards established;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Issuing a repair order certification for any specified equipment if that equipment does not meet or exceed the standards established under this subtitle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Conviction for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A felony;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Assault;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Battery;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Theft;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A crime involving fraud; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>A controlled dangerous substance (CDS) violation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Making, issuing, or knowingly using any fictitious inspection certificate, repair order certification, or other document approved or issued by the Division;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Attaching, causing to be attached, or permitting to be attached to any vehicle an inspection certificate knowing it to be fictitious or issued without the equipment having been inspected for compliance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 23, Subtitle 1, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Issuing, causing to be issued, or permitting to be issued a repair order certification knowing it to be fictitious or issued without the equipment having been inspected for compliance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 23, Subtitle 1, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Materially altering or changing any equipment on a vehicle for which an inspection certificate or a repair order certification has been issued;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>A suspension or revocation of a driver's license within the past 3 years;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Using or being under the influence of alcoholic beverages or a controlled dangerous substance (CDS) during work hours; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Performing vehicle inspections in an area other than an approved designated inspection area.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A registered inspection mechanic shall discontinue inspections and notify the Division of any of the following circumstances and may not resume inspections until authorized to do so by the Division:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Revocation, suspension, cancellation, or loss of driver's license;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Change of employment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Conviction of a crime;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Condition or circumstance which may affect the mechanic's ability to conduct inspections or sign inspection certificates or safety equipment repair orders; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Request to cancel the registration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An authorized Maryland manufacturer, Maryland second-stage manufacturer, or dealer issuing a certification of repair for a dump service registration vehicle lift axle air/weight ratio defect without inspecting the equipment may have the privilege to certify safety equipment repair orders issued under <cite path="11.15.27.08|C.">COMAR 11.15.27.08C</cite> revoked.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A Maryland diesel emissions retester, as prescribed in <cite path="11.21.02.08">COMAR 11.21.02.08</cite>, that issues a certification of a repair to meet a diesel emission opacity standard without conducting an emissions test in accordance with <cite path="|11.21.02">COMAR 11.21.02</cite> may have the privilege to certify safety equipment repair orders issued under <cite path="|11.21.02">COMAR 11.21.02</cite> revoked.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Facility Requirements.</heading>
    <text>A facility may be licensed as an authorized inspection station with a classification of A, B, C, F, M, R, T or any combination of them. The building and location shall conform to established requirements. If a combination license is applied for, the larger inspection and work area prevails and shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Be open and readily accessible to the general public except those facilities with an F classification.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Comply with all applicable laws, ordinances, and regulations for the jurisdiction in which it is located.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Be appropriate for the business to be conducted as described below, including an entrance to the inspection area of sufficient height to accommodate the maximum legal height of vehicles to be inspected:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Authorized inspection station A—contain at least two work areas, one of which shall be at least 12 feet wide and 25 feet long.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Authorized inspection station B—contain an area at least 12 feet wide and at least 60 feet long. This area may be outside.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Authorized inspection station C—contain an area at least 15 feet wide and 45 feet long.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Authorized inspection station D—shall meet all requirements for Classes B and C.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Authorized inspection station F—contain an inspection area meeting the requirements established for the class or classes of vehicles owned or controlled by this facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Authorized inspection station M—contain an area at least 10 feet wide and 15 feet long.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Authorized inspection station R—contain an area at least 12 feet wide and 40 feet long.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Authorized inspection station T—this area shall be at least 12 feet wide and at least 60 feet long. This area may be outside.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Authorized inspection station G—shall meet all requirements of Classes R and T.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Allow minor repairs to be performed in the inspection area of any authorized inspection station open to the public, provided the area can be readily cleared for an inspection.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Require that the inspection area be within one building at the place of business of the licensee.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Inspection Area Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An inside inspection area shall have a smooth, level hard-surfaced concrete or cement floor which:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall have no more than a 1 percent slope from front to rear, rear to front, or side to side;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May not have a four-way slope;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Shall be free of work benches, displays, machinery, stairways, shelves, car washing equipment or any other obstructions which would create a hazard; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>May not be equipped with a drive-on lift.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Authorized inspection stations with two or more inspection areas may designate one area as a headlight testing/alignment area, provided this area meets the size requirements of the type of vehicle to be inspected and the requirements of §§A and C(2) of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Class A, C, or R authorized inspection stations shall be designed and equipped with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Two convex mirrors, a minimum of 12 inches in diameter each, one mounted facing forward from the left rear corner and one facing rearward on the right front corner of the inspection bay; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A track-mounted approved-type headlight tester.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Class A authorized inspection stations shall be equipped with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A frame contact lift capable of raising vehicles, except for limousines and recreational motor homes, at least 5 feet off the floor; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Jack stands able to hold limousines and recreational motor homes when raised and placed on them.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Diagram of Bay Layout.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|14|01|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Inspection Test Equipment and Tools.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applicants and licensees shall have the following test equipment and tools approved by the Division, except as specified in this regulation:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>One headlight tester (not required for Class B, M, or T), any track-mounted make or model:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Capable of accurately testing and aiming headlamp beam patterns and high intensity zones;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Equipped with an accurate beam candlepower output display; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Including necessary calibration equipment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>One drum micrometer calibration gauge compatible with the brake drum measuring tool;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>One disc micrometer calibration gauge compatible with the brake disc measuring tool;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>One ball joint checker, any make or model equipped with a dial indicator and capable of accurately measuring ball joint or king pin movement in increments of 0.001 of an inch (not required for Class B or T);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Two jack stands, any make or model, capable of supporting the types of vehicles subject to inspection;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>One roller/floor jack, any make or model capable of lifting types of vehicles subject to inspection;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A drum brake micrometer, any make or model capable of accurately measuring for the appropriate type of vehicle the inside diameter of brake drums in at least 0.005 of an inch increments;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A disc brake micrometer, any make or model with a pointed anvil, capable of accurately measuring for the appropriate type of vehicle the thickness of discs or rotors in increments of at least 0.001 of an inch;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>One brake shoe lining thickness gauge, any make or model capable of accurately measuring, for the types of vehicles subject to inspection, in fractions of an inch the remaining usable bonded brake lining or the thickness of brake lining remaining above rivet heads;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>One brake disc pad thickness gauge, any make or model capable of accurately measuring for the types of vehicles subject to inspection, in fractions of an inch the remaining usable bonded brake disc pad lining or the thickness of brake disc pad lining remaining above rivet heads;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>One ammeter, any make or model having a range of 0-40 amperes DC current (not required for Classes C or R);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>One screwdriver, any type, capable of spreading tire cuts and breaks to determine severity of damage;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>One tire tread depth gauge, any make or model capable of accurately measuring tire tread depth in 1/32 of an inch;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>One minimum 25-foot steel tape of any type with clearly legible S.A.E. figures and markings;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Two convex mirrors, a minimum of 12 inches in diameter each, any type providing a wide angle view of the front and rear of the inspection bay (not required for Classes B, M, or T);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Miscellaneous hand tools necessary to perform mechanical disassembly of vehicle components to conduct inspections;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>One typewritten or commercially printed S.A.E.-to-metric and metric-to-S.A.E. conversion chart enclosed in clear plastic;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>One tire pressure gauge, any make or model, capable of measuring air pressure in pounds per square inch (PSI) for type of vehicle being inspected;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>One 4-foot carpenter's level, any make or model, capable of determining horizontal and vertical levelness (required only if using the Hoppy Vision 100 or the Symtech Corporation "HBA 5" headlight tester); and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>One window tint meter (not required for Class B or T), any make or model:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Manufactured as a two-piece device, portable and compact, with digital readout to the nearest percent;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Suitable for testing standard automotive glazing on roll down and fixed windows;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Designed to be operated by one person;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Equipped with an alignment aid feature to assist in obtaining and maintaining accuracy throughout the period of measurement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Equipped with an activation switch or button, off switch or button, or self deactivation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Equipped with the manufacturer's reference sample/calibration standards that are labeled with the manufacturer's name, serial number (if equipped), and percentage of light transmittance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Equipped with a light transmittance meter which shall maintain unit accuracy within + or – 2 percentage points (certified by an independent testing laboratory);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Designed to maintain repeatability within + or – 1 percentage point; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Equipped with a portable carrying case.</text>
        </para>
        <aftertext>(Manufacturers shall provide information to the Division regarding any change in specifications of any approved products used for tint inspection and certification in Maryland.)</aftertext>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Care of Test Equipment and Tools.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Test equipment and tools shall be maintained in proper working order at all times.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any test equipment or tool requiring calibration shall be calibrated as required by the manufacturer, or more frequently, if necessary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any test equipment or tool that is not permanently mounted shall be kept together in or within close proximity to the inspection bay.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Division may add or delete test equipment and tools from those set forth in <cite path="11|14|01|.07|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> by notifying licensed inspection stations in writing and requiring them to obtain the additional equipment within 90 days of the written notification.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Inspection stations shall have the following reference material for the appropriate class of station:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Class A inspection stations and any Class F fleet inspection stations inspecting the types of vehicles inspected by a Class A inspection station shall have:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Current model year brake, ball joint and tire guide specifications by July 1st of that year; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Emission guide specifications that are within two model years by July 1st of that year (for example, on July 1, 2011, such stations would be required to have either 2010 or 2011 model year emission guide specifications).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Class C, D, F, R, and G inspection stations are required to have current model year brake specifications by July 1st of that year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <aftertext>
      <strong>
        <em>Agency Note:</em>
      </strong>
      <em>The required specifications may take the form of a printed or electronic reference source from a computerized system, provided the reference material contains required specifications by July 1st of that year.</em>
    </aftertext>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Calibration and Certification of Equipment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Licensed inspection stations shall calibrate their equipment once a month, or as required by <cite path="11|14|01|.07|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maryland manufacturers, second-stage manufacturers, or authorized dealers:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>May calibrate the standard automotive air pressure gauge specified in <cite path="11|14|01|.07|J.|(1)">§J(1) of this regulation</cite> daily;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Shall certify the standard automotive air pressure gauge specified in <cite path="11|14|01|.07|J.|(1)">§J(1) of this regulation</cite> at least semiannually; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Shall certify the scale or scales specified in <cite path="11|14|01|.07|J.|(2)">§J(2) of this regulation</cite> at least semiannually.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The calibration and certification data specified in §E(1) and (2) of this regulation shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Recorded on a form furnished by the Division;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Made available to Division personnel on request; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Given, with respect to the calibration date specified in <cite path="11|14|01|.07|E.|(1)">§E(1) of this regulation</cite>, to the supervising trooper or civilian employee of the Division at the time of the monthly station check.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If any inspection tool or test equipment is found to be inoperative, the licensee shall have the equipment repaired or replaced within 72 hours. During this time, all unused inspection certificates shall be surrendered to the Division and all other issued materials may be retained by the licensee. Complete inspections, reinspections, or repair order certifications requiring the use of the inoperative equipment may not be performed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Upon repair or replacement of the inoperative equipment or tool within 72 hours, the unused inspection certificates shall be returned to the licensee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>If the equipment or tool is not repaired or replaced within 72 hours, the unused certificates shall be retained by the Division and the licensee required to remove the inspection station sign from public view. All other issued materials shall be retained by the licensee. However, no complete inspections or repair order certifications may be performed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>If the equipment or tool is not repaired or replaced within a total of 90 days, the license shall be suspended or revoked and all issued materials returned to the Division, except where a valid back order receipt is in evidence.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Maryland manufacturers, second-stage manufacturers, or authorized dealers operating under <cite path="11.15.27.08">COMAR 11.15.27.08</cite> and State-operated weight facilities shall be equipped with a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Standard automotive air pressure gauge as specified by the Maryland State Police in concurrence with the Maryland Department of Transportation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Scale or scales capable of accurately measuring the weight of a lift axle on a four-axle dump truck.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>The Division Commander shall approve all required measuring devices of this regulation before use.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Agreement of Licensee.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon compliance with the requirements of Regulations .02—.07 of this chapter and being licensed as an authorized inspection station, the licensee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Agrees to act in the best interest of the State and the general public and comply with the agreement contained in the application for an authorized inspection station license;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Acknowledges that the licensee understands the license may be revoked, suspended, or refused for the reasons provided in these regulations and, upon revocation, suspension, or refusal, the licensee shall surrender the license and all related materials issued by the Division; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Acknowledges that the Division reserves the right, in the interest of public safety and in determining compliance with the subtitle, to conduct covert vehicle inspections at authorized inspection stations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The licensee may not use as a defense, to a charge of violating any provision of this subtitle, that a fictitious safety equipment repair order was presented to the registered inspection mechanic as part of a covert vehicle inspection.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Obligations of Authorized Inspection Stations, Maryland Manufacturers, Second-Stage Manufacturers, and Dealers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Inspections.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At the request of a vehicle owner, dealer, or agent, the licensee shall perform a complete inspection or a reinspection of a vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whether the vehicle's equipment meets minimum safety standards or is rejected because it does not, the licensee shall give the owner, dealer, or agent a copy of the Division's vehicle inspection report which shall list all defective equipment, if any.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a rejected vehicle is repaired and returned within 30 days and within 1,000 miles after the original inspection to the same authorized inspection station where it was rejected, only the defective equipment or any defect visually observed is required to be reinspected. Otherwise, a complete inspection shall be performed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Appointments shall be honored, but if a complete inspection or reinspection cannot be performed when scheduled, an appointment for the complete inspection or reinspection shall be set for not more than 3 business days from the date of the original appointment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Reinspections.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For a reinspection, the registered inspection mechanic who originally performed the complete inspection shall perform the reinspection on the appointment date, if possible.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the registered inspection mechanic who performed the original complete inspection is not available on a scheduled reinspection appointment date, the licensee is responsible for a complete reinspection and may charge only the appropriate fee for reinspection of the equipment indicated defective when the original complete inspection was performed, or shall refund the fee for the original complete inspection.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the registered inspection mechanic who performed the original complete inspection has had the mechanic's registration suspended or revoked as a result of an administrative action, the licensee shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Refund the initial inspection fee; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If there is another registered inspection mechanic at the station, have the vehicle completely reinspected and only charge the fee for the reinspected equipment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the facility's authorized inspection station license is suspended or revoked as a result of an administrative action, the facility's owner shall refund the initial inspection fee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The licensee shall have available for use by all inspection personnel the Vehicle Inspection Handbook including all supplements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in §D(1) and (2) of this regulation, the licensee and the supervisor shall permit only registered inspection mechanics to perform inspections and only within the designated inspection area.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Certification of defects on safety equipment repair orders which require only a visual inspection may be performed outside the designated area but on the premises of the business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The inspection and certification of defect #61 "TINT" on safety equipment repair orders may be performed outside the designated inspection area but on the premises of the business.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The licensee and the supervisor shall permit only registered inspection mechanics to sign inspection certificates, vehicle inspection reports, safety equipment repair orders, or post manufacture window tint inspection reports.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Maryland manufacturers, second-stage manufacturers, or authorized dealers certifying equipment repair orders under <cite path="|11.15.27">COMAR 11.15.27</cite> are responsible for supplying a list of individuals authorized to certify safety equipment repair orders to the Automotive Safety Enforcement Division (ASED), and shall notify the ASED of changes to the list within 10 days.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The licensee shall discontinue inspections and notify the Division of the following circumstances and may not resume inspections until authorized to do so by the Division:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Change in ownership, partnership, corporate representatives, or trade name;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Change in location of the facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any remodeling or significant change to the inspection area;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Request of the licensee to cancel the licensee's license or application; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any circumstance which prevents a complete inspection, the issuance of an inspection certificate, or a repair order certification.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Notifying the Division.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The licensee or supervisor shall immediately notify the Division of the following circumstances:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Change of inspection or supervisory personnel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Stolen, lost, or damaged inspection certificates, license, sign, or records pertaining to inspection;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Conviction of criminal or motor vehicle laws, restrictions imposed on driver's license, or loss of driver's license of any registered inspection mechanic; or any condition or circumstance which may affect the mechanic's ability to conduct inspections or sign inspection certificates or safety equipment repair orders; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Anything unusual to indicate the serial number plate has been tampered with.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a licensee does not have a registered inspection mechanic in the licensee's employ, the licensee shall surrender all unused inspection certificates to the Division and remove the inspection station sign from public view. If a registered inspection mechanic is not employed within 90 days, the license shall be cancelled.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The licensee, when applicable, shall display the issued authorized inspection station sign on his property in a manner visible to the public on the main thoroughfare where the business is located.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>The licensee shall prominently display in public view the following in a frame and under clear glass or plastic:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Authorized inspection station license;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Required official inspection procedure chart with approved inspection fee; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Registered inspection mechanic list.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>The licensee or supervisor shall assure that the inspection area is kept clear.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Inspection Fee.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The licensee of an authorized inspection station open to the public may establish a fee for a complete inspection based on the times listed in this section at the hourly flat rate charged for similar mechanical repairs:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Vehicles 10,000 pounds and under GVWR — 1.5 hours, which includes 0.4 hour for adjustment of headlights;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Vehicles 10,000 pound and under GVWR with 4-wheel drive or full floating axles — 2.0 hours, which includes 0.4 hour for adjustment of headlights, and with each additional axle add 1 hour;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Vehicles over 10,000 pounds GVWR with front and rear brakes — 2.9 hours, which includes 0.4 hour for adjustment of headlights, and with each additional axle add 1.5 hours;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Vehicles over 10,000 pounds GVWR without front brakes — 2.4 hours, which includes 0.4 hour for adjustment of headlights and with each additional axle with brakes add 1.5 hours;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Trailers under 10,000 pounds GVWR without brakes — 0.5 hour, and with each axle with brakes add 0.5 hour;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Trailers over 10,000 pounds GVWR — 0.5 hour:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Each additional axle with single wheels add 0.75 hour; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Each additional axle with dual wheels add 1.5 hours.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Motorcycles — 0.75 hour; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Vehicles with post manufacture window tint applied to windows required to meet at least 35 percent light transmittance and compliant with all other post manufacture window tinting regulations under this subtitle — 0.2 hour of hourly flat rate in addition to applicable inspection fees established under this section.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the defects are not repaired at the authorized inspection station and the vehicle is returned for reinspection and certification, a prorated inspection fee may be charged for the reinspection of those defects requiring jacking, lifting, measuring, or testing. A fee, if charged, will be based on defect or defects inspection as set forth in the safety equipment repair order certification procedures. However, an additional fee may not be charged for the reinspection of those defects which may be visually inspected and do not require the use of test or inspection equipment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Safety Equipment Repair Order Certification Procedures. A fee for certification of defects on a safety equipment repair order may be charged as follows and based on the prevailing hourly labor flat rate at the authorized inspection station. Those defects which can be merged shall be charged at the single highest rate, for example, tires and steering, 0.2 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate, or tires and wheel alignment, 0.3 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate. The inspection fee for multiple defects which can be merged may not be higher than the highest single time increment. Those which cannot be merged may be charged separately provided the total inspection fee is not exceeded. An inspection fee may not be charged for the certification of a SERO with defects which may be visually inspected. These defects are noted with an asterisk on the SERO and do not require the use of test or inspection equipment. The licensee may establish a fee for certification of a SERO which cannot be visually inspected based on the following fee charged for inspections:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Defect #50 brakes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Vehicles over 10,000 pounds GVWR with dual wheels — 1.5 hours of the facility's hourly labor flat rate per axle for removing each wheel and inspecting the brakes on each axle;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Vehicles over 10,000 pounds GVWR with single wheels — 0.5 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate per axle for removing each wheel and inspecting the brakes on each axle; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>All other vehicles requiring wheel removal — 0.5 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate per axle for removing each wheel and inspecting the brakes on each axle.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Other defects:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Defect #51 tires — 0.2 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Defect #52 steering — 0.2 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Defect #53 exhaust system — 0.3 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Defect #54 windshield wipers*;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Defect #55 headlights* — 0.3 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate to check for aim; and an additional 0.1 hour may be added if adjustment is needed;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Defect #56 taillights*;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Defect #57 horn*;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Defect #58 driver's seat — 0.2 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Defect #59 suspension/shocks — 0.2 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>Defect #60 bumper or bumpers*;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xi)</num>
            <text>Defect #61 glass* tint — 0.2 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate to test the light transmittance of windows equipped with post manufacture window tint and required to have at least 35 percent light transmittance;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <aftertext>
      <strong>
        <em>Agency Note</em>
      </strong>
      <em>: Before use of the station's window tint meter is permitted and a fee is charged to inspect regulated windows equipped with post manufacture window tint, the vehicle must first be compliant with all other post manufacture window tinting regulations under this subtitle. The inspection and certification for the defect "tint" not requiring the use of a window tint meter shall be performed without charge and only by an authorized inspection station approved to inspect that class of vehicle.</em>
    </aftertext>
    <para>
      <num>(xii)</num>
      <text>Defect #62 load cover*;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(xiii)</num>
      <text>Defect #64 stop lights*;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(xiv)</num>
      <text>Defect #65 tag light or lights*;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(xv)</num>
      <text>Defect #66 dash lights*;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(xvi)</num>
      <text>Defect #67 wheel alignment — 0.3 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(xvii)</num>
      <text>Defect #68 rearview mirrors*;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(xviii)</num>
      <text>Defect #69 door latch or door handle*;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(xix)</num>
      <text>Defect #70 fuel system — 0.2 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate, except cap*;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(xx)</num>
      <text>Defect #71 turn signals*;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(xxi)</num>
      <text>Defect #72 wheel or wheel lugs — 0.2 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(xxii)</num>
      <text>Defect #73 hood catch or hood catches*;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(xxiii)</num>
      <text>Defect #74 floor/trunk pan or pans — 0.2 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(xxiv)</num>
      <text>Defect #76 fenders or flaps*;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(xxv)</num>
      <text>Defect #77 speedometer/odometer — 0.2 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(xxvi)</num>
      <text>Defect #78 hazard warning lamps*;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(xxvii)</num>
      <text>Defect #79 parking lamps*;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(xxviii)</num>
      <text>Defect #80 side marker lamps*;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(xxix)</num>
      <text>Defect #81 fog/auxiliary lamps — 0.3 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(xxx)</num>
      <text>Defect #82 emergency warning lamps*;</text>
      <text>(xxxi) Defect #83 back-up lamp or lamps*;</text>
      <text>(xxxii) Defect #84 reflectors*;</text>
      <text>(xxxiii) Defect #85 external air brake components — 0.3 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate;</text>
      <text>(xxxiv) Defect #86 low air warning device*;</text>
      <text>(xxxv) Defect #87 clearance lamp*;</text>
      <text>(xxxvi) Defect #88 identification lamps*;</text>
      <text>(xxxvii) Defect #89 safety belts — 0.3 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate;</text>
      <text>(xxxviii) Defect #90 lift axle air/weight ratio — 0.5 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate; and</text>
      <text>(xxxix) Defect #91 diesel emission — 0.5 hour of the facility's hourly labor flat rate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>Any class of authorized inspection station open to the public may certify any defect on a safety equipment repair order which is indicated as visually certifiable. Defects which can be visually certified are indicated by an asterisk after the defect on a safety equipment repair order.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>A request for an inspection fee increase shall be justified to the satisfaction of the Division before being charged. Inspection fee increases shall be approved by the Division. Requests to increase the inspection fee shall be submitted to the Division on the approved form.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|14|01|.11">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Records.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To enable the Division to determine the ability of each authorized inspection station to continue to conduct inspections and make corrections to equipment, each authorized inspection station shall maintain on their premises, adequate records in strict numerical sequence and as otherwise required by the Division. These records shall be available to the Division and other police officers during normal working hours. The inspection certificates and the Division's vehicle inspection reports shall be maintained for at least 8 months from the date of issuance and safety equipment repair orders and certifications for at least 2 years from the date of certification. Post manufacture window tint inspection reports and medical exemption forms shall be maintained by authorized inspection stations as required by the Division. These records shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Inspection certificates issued;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Safety equipment repair order certifications filed numerically by calendar year;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Two-part vehicle inspection reports, for the appropriate vehicle classes, signed by the registered inspection mechanics who performed the inspections;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Two-part post manufacture window tint inspection reports, completed and signed by the registered inspection mechanics who performed the inspections of  post manufacture window tint applied to regulated windows of vehicles; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Post manufacture window tint medical exemption forms issued by the Division.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The two-part vehicle inspection report shall be printed in black ink and made from carbonless paper, so that the second part shall  have the exact information on it as the first part. The original of the two part vehicle inspection report shall be white in color and the carbonless copy shall be yellow in color. The inspection report shall be completed in black ink. The original of the report shall be maintained at the inspection station and the copy shall be given to the vehicle owner, owner's agent, or the dealer. The vehicle inspection report shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Contain the name, complete address, and phone number of the owner, owner's agent, or dealer requesting the vehicle inspection;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Contain the year, make, model, and serial number or manufacturer's vehicle identification number (VIN) as obtained from the vehicle and indicate any information relevant to possible tampering with a serial number plate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Indicate the inspection station assigned number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Contain the date of initial inspection which shall include the name of the month, a two-digit date, and the year (for example, June 04, 2011);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Indicate the odometer reading at the time of inspection on the applicable vehicles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Indicate whether equipment required to be inspected meets established safety standards;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Indicate wheels or drums removed for inspection;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Indicate the measurements and minimum specifications of brake discs and maximum specifications of brake drums;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Indicate brake lining or pad thickness measurements at the thinnest point above the rivet head on riveted lining or the thinnest point on bonded lining;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Indicate ball joint or king pin play measurements obtained by use of a ball joint checker. If no play is present, a zero will be sufficient. If the vehicle is equipped with wear-indicating ball joints, note this on the vehicle inspection report;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Indicate a "P" for headlight alignment that passes, or an "F" for headlight alignment that fails, in the block for headlight readings obtained by use of a Division-approved headlight tester before adjustments are made; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Indicate the work order number from a preprinted numbered internal work order that cross-references the initial inspection and any repair work performed by the inspection station related to the inspection.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Initial inspections and any repair work performed by the inspection station related to the inspection shall be documented on a preprinted numbered internal work order.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Permission shall be obtained from the vehicle owner or agent before any repair resulting from an inspection is performed at the authorized inspection station.  If any such repair work over $50 is necessary, this permission should be in writing. All the requirements of the auto repair facilities law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcl">Commercial Law Article, Title 14, Subtitle 10, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall be complied with by each authorized inspection station.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The inspection station shall give the owner, the owner's agent, or the dealer the completed carbonless copy of the two-part vehicle inspection report, and on reinspection shall indicate on the original report whether the equipment has been repaired and meets established safety standards.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The two-part post manufacture window tint inspection report shall be printed in black ink and made from carbonless paper, so that the second part shall have the exact information on it as the first part. The original shall be white in color and the carbonless copy shall be yellow in color. The inspection report shall be completed in black ink.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The post manufacture window tint inspection report shall be completed as required by the Division and shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Contain the date of inspection which shall include the name of the month, a two-digit date, and the year (for example, June 04, 2011);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Contain, when applicable, the corresponding inspection certificate number or safety equipment repair order number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Contain the year, make, model, and serial number or manufacturer's vehicle identification number (VIN) as obtained from the vehicle;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Contain the name, address, and phone number of the owner, owner's agent, or the dealer requesting the vehicle inspection;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Indicate the percentage of light transmittance of each regulated window containing post manufacture vehicle window tint;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Indicate in the appropriate (Pass / Fail) box the results of the post manufacture window tint inspection;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Contain the written signature and legibly printed name of the registered inspection mechanic who performed the inspection; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Contain the name, address, station number, and classification of the authorized inspection station using a legible stamp and black ink.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Upon completion of the post manufacture window tint inspection report, the original of the report shall be maintained at the inspection station as required by the Division and the carbonless copy shall be given to the vehicle owner, owner's agent, or the dealer for their records.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The post manufacture window tint medical exemption form shall be established and issued only by the Division for the purpose of providing notification and documentation to an authorized inspection station performing an inspection of a vehicle that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is owned by a person who must be protected from the sun for medical reasons and has been determined by the Division that the owner has met the medical exemption requirements established in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|22-406">Transportation Article, §22-406, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Excluding the light transmittance requirement, is compliant with all other post manufacture window tinting regulations under this subtitle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The post manufacture window tint medical exemption form issued by the Division shall be maintained by the authorized inspection station as required by the Division.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The Division may require the licensee to maintain certain other administrative records pertaining to the inspection process.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>A Maryland manufacturer, second-stage manufacturer, or authorized dealer as specified under <cite path="|11.15.27">COMAR 11.15.27</cite> who certifies safety equipment repair orders for lift axle air/weight ratio for dump service registration vehicles shall maintain safety equipment repair orders for at least 2 years. These safety equipment repair order certifications shall be filed numerically for each calendar year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Recording VIN. Under <cite path="11|14|01|.11|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite>, if a vehicle has more than one VIN, the registered mechanic shall, if the numbers are obtainable, record each VIN on the inspection certificate and the vehicle inspection report. On vehicles classified as homemade trailers, the VIN plate shall be attached to the outside of the left portion of the trailer tongue as near as possible to the front of the trailer body. If this is not practical, the plate shall be attached to the outside of the left side rail of the frame as near as possible to the front of the trailer. The plate shall be attached with rivets.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Revocation, Suspension, or Refusal of Authorized Inspection Station License.</heading>
    <text>The following may be cause for revocation, suspension, or refusal of an authorized inspection station license:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Failure to maintain any of the standards or requirements set forth in these regulations;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Failure to notify the Division of personnel, physical plant, or equipment changes;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Failure to maintain required records;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Change in ownership, partnership, corporate representatives, or trade name;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Change in location of the facility or inspection area;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Failure to maintain inspection tools and test equipment in proper working condition;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Violation of any provision or requirement of these regulations, or violation of any part of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 23, Subtitle 1, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Vehicle Sale or Transfer of Ownership.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An inspection is required when a used vehicle is sold or ownership is transferred or when a used vehicle is to be titled and registered in the State. As requested by a vehicle owner, owner's agent, or dealer, a certified inspection mechanic at an inspection station shall perform a complete inspection, as set forth in this subtitle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An inspection is not required for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Sales or transfers of used vehicles to a licensed or foreign dealer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sales or transfers accompanied by a signed statement by the purchaser or transferee that the sale or transfer is made for the purpose of rebuilding, as defined in Regulation .01B(27) of this chapter, or dismantling the vehicle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Transfers between spouses or between former spouses when the transfer occurs as a result of a settlement or court order predating the divorce;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Transfers between parent and child or child and parent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Transfers of co-owned vehicles when a co-owner's name is being removed from the title;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Sales or transfers of used vehicles which are not to be both titled and registered in the State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Transfers of used vehicles among State agencies;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Transfers of used vehicles as described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-503">Transportation Article, §13-503</cite>.2, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The transfer of a used vehicle into a written inter vivos trust in which the transferor is the primary beneficiary; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The transfer of a used island vehicle, as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-935">Transportation Article, §13-935, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, registered, or to be registered, as a Class K (farm area/island) vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Either the transferor or the transferee may obtain required inspection certificates for vehicles registered or to be registered as:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Class E (truck) over 3/4 ton manufacturer's rated capacity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Class F (tractor); or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Class G (freight trailer or semitrailer).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a used vehicle is transferred other than by voluntary transfer or is transferred by a political subdivision of the State after that subdivision obtains the vehicle by proceedings pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcp">Criminal Procedure Article, Title 12, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the transferee shall obtain the inspection certificate from an authorized inspection station.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Inspection Certificate.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon successful completion of an inspection, the registered inspection mechanic who performed the inspection shall issue a prenumbered inspection certificate before the vehicle leaves the premises. The inspection certificate shall be completed in black ink and:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Contain the serial number or manufacturer's identification number (vehicle identification number) obtained from the vehicle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Contain the make, type, year, and current odometer reading of the vehicle when applicable;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Contain the name, address, station number, and classification of the authorized inspection station using a legible stamp and black ink;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Contain a certification date which shall include the name of the month, a two-digit date, and the year, for example, January 02, 2010, or March 23, 2012;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Contain the written signature and legibly printed name of the registered inspection mechanic who performed the inspection; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Be distributed as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The original copy of the certificate shall be furnished to the vehicle owner, dealer, or agent;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The purchaser's copy shall be given to the owner, dealer, or agent who shall deliver this copy to the purchaser upon transfer of ownership of the vehicle;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Inspection station copy shall be maintained as required by Regulation .11 of this chapter; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Additional instructions are on the reverse side of the copies of the inspection certificate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the original inspection certificate is lost, damaged, or contains incorrect or illegible information and a duplicate certificate is necessary, the following will apply:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A duplicate certificate may only be issued by the inspection mechanic who issued the original certificate unless authorized otherwise by the Division;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except for corrections, a duplicate certificate shall contain exactly the same date, odometer reading, and all other pertinent information as the original certificate; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When possible, the original certificate and all copies will be marked VOID, cross-referenced with the duplicate certificate and filed as required by Regulation .11 of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Inspection certificates will be issued to each authorized inspection station by the Division.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Inspection certificates shall remain valid for 90 calendar days from the date the inspection certificate is issued.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An inspection certificate issued for a used vehicle owned and held in inventory by a dealer licensed under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 15, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall remain valid for 6 months or 1,000 miles from the date the inspection certificate was issued, whichever occurs first.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A vehicle titled and registered with the Administration may be transferred and retitled to another owner within 30 days from the date of the last inspection without requiring a reinspection.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|14|01|.16">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Safety Equipment Repair Orders.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The vehicle owner or his agent shall present the No. 3, 4, and 5 copies of the safety equipment repair order to an authorized inspection station. The registered inspection mechanic shall inspect as set forth in the Vehicle Inspection Handbook, or as directed by the Division, only those defects indicated on the repair order to determine if the defects have been corrected and meet or exceed established safety standards. Inspection mechanics who are presented with a fictitious safety equipment repair order as defined in Regulation .01B(13) of this chapter, shall complete an inspection of only those defects indicated on the fictitious safety equipment repair order in accordance with established procedures and in a manner identical to an actual repair order. If the defects have been corrected and meet or exceed established safety standards, the registered inspection mechanic shall certify the safety equipment repair order using the method prescribed for inspection certificates contained in Regulation .15A(3)—(5) of this chapter, in the space provided and copies shall be distributed as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Number 3 (inspection station/police department) copy — retained and filed as required by Regulation .11 of this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Number 4 (owner/agent) copy — returned to the vehicle owner or the owner's agent for his records; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Number 5 (State Police compliance copy) — returned to the vehicle owner or the owner's agent to be forwarded to the Division.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Important instructions for the vehicle owner and authorized inspection station are on the reverse sides of the owner's and inspection station copies.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a notice of suspension is presented for certification, the procedures set forth in <cite path="11|14|01|.16|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> will apply and the copies shall be distributed as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Letter (white) copy — returned to vehicle owner/agent to be forwarded to the Division;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Yellow (inspection station/police department) copy — retained on file as required by <cite path="11|14|01|.16|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Goldenrod (owner/agent) copy — returned to vehicle owner/agent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A dump service registration vehicle registered under <cite path="|11.15.27">COMAR 11.15.27</cite> that receives a safety equipment repair order for an inaccurate lift axle air/weight ratio shall be inspected during normal business hours by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Maryland manufacturer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A Maryland second-stage manufacturer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An authorized dealer; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A State-operated weight facility.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A vehicle owner or the vehicle owner's agent receiving a safety equipment repair order under <cite path="11.15.27.08|C.">COMAR 11.15.27.08C</cite> shall present for certification the No. 3, 4, and 5 copies of the safety equipment repair order to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Maryland manufacturer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A Maryland second-stage manufacturer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An authorized dealer; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A State-operated weight facility.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A diesel vehicle as defined in <cite path="11.21.02.01">COMAR 11.21.02.01</cite> that receives a safety equipment repair order for violating emissions standards under <cite path="11.21.02.06">COMAR 11.21.02.06</cite> shall be inspected during normal operating hours by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Maryland emissions inspector; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A diesel emissions retester in Maryland as prescribed in <cite path="11.21.02.08">COMAR 11.21.02.08</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A vehicle owner or owner's agent receiving a safety equipment repair order under <cite path="|11.21.02">COMAR 11.21.02</cite> shall present for certification copies 3, 4, and 5 of the safety equipment repair order to a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maryland emissions inspector; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A diesel emissions retester in Maryland as prescribed in <cite path="11.21.02.08">COMAR 11.21.02.08</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Suspension of Vehicle Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Whenever the owner of a vehicle fails to comply with a safety equipment repair order within the time prescribed by law, a notice of suspension of the registration plates shall be issued.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Whenever the owner of a vehicle fails to comply with a notice of suspension which requires the registration plates to be returned to the Administration within 10 days, a tag pick up order shall be issued. The registration plates are subject to confiscation by a police officer, as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|23-101">Transportation Article, §23-101(g), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, following procedures established by the Division, and shall be forwarded to the Administration upon confiscation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall retain the confiscated registration plates until the suspension is rescinded. Upon satisfactory proof of correction of defective equipment, the Maryland State Police shall notify the Administration, and registration plates shall be released or issued to the owner of the vehicle.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Administrative Hearings.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Complaints of violations of these regulations will be investigated by the Division. If the investigation reveals a violation which warrants an administrative hearing, all parties shall be afforded an opportunity for a hearing after reasonable notice.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A hearing held as a result of a violation which warrants emergency suspension shall be conducted in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|29.01.01">COMAR 29.01.01</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a person fails to appear for a hearing scheduled for alleged violations of the Transportation Article, Maryland Vehicle Law, Annotated Code of Maryland, or any of the regulations duly promulgated, and has notice of the hearing given by the Division pursuant to the provisions of §§B and D of this regulation, the Division may revoke, suspend, or cancel the authorized inspection station license or the inspection mechanic's registration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Emergency suspension hearings and hearings on other violations resulting in the imposition of administrative penalties that are not accepted may be appealed to the Office of Administrative Hearings in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-205">State Government Article, §10-205, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|23-101">23-101</cite>-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|23-109">23-109</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|24-106">24-106</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date: November, 1965</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-03-07">Chapter revised effective March 7, 1980 (7:5 Md. R. 475)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-10-31">Chapter revised effective October 31, 1988 (15:22 Md. R. 2556)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-10-09">Regulation .01B amended effective April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 686); October 9, 1995 (22:20 Md. R. 1544)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-01">Regulation .03 amended effective April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 686)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-10-09">Regulation .04 amended effective October 9, 1995 (22:20 Md. R. 1544)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-01">Regulation .04A amended effective April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 686)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-01">Regulation .05A and C amended effective April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 686)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-01">Regulation .06 amended effective April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 686)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-01">Regulation .07 amended effective April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 686)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-10-09">Regulation .07C amended effective October 9, 1995 (22:20 Md. R. 1544)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-10-09">Regulation .07H adopted effective October 9, 1995 (22:20 Md. R. 1544)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-01">Regulation .08 repealed effective April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 686)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-01">Regulation .09 amended effective April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 686)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-10-09">Regulation .10 amended effective October 9, 1995 (22:20 Md. R. 1544)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-01">Regulation .10F—I amended effective April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 686)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-10-09">Regulation .11 amended effective October 9, 1995 (22:20 Md. R. 1544)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-01">Regulation .11B amended effective April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 686)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-10-09">Regulation .15D, E adopted effective October 9, 1995 (22:20 Md. R. 1544)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-01">Regulation .16B amended effective April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 686)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" discontinuity="true" effective="1998-03-23">Chapter revised effective March 23, 1998 (25:6 Md. R. 488)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2006-01-01">Regulation .01B adopted as an emergency provision effective January 1, 2006 (33:4 Md. R. 349); emergency provision extended at 33:15 Md. R. 1275; emergency status expired December 28, 2006</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2006-03-27">Regulation .01B amended effective March 27, 2006 (33:6 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2007-03-09">Regulation .01B amended as an emergency provision effective March 9, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 824); emergency provision expired September 5, 2007</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2007-09-10">Regulation .01B amended effective September 10, 2007 (34:18 Md. R. 1580)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2000-07-10">Regulation .04D adopted effective July 10, 2000 (27:13 Md. R. 1212)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2006-03-27">Regulation .09 amended effective March 27, 2006 (33:6 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2000-07-10">Regulation .10L amended effective July 10, 2000 (27:13 Md. R. 1212)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2000-07-10">Regulation .16F, G adopted effective July 10, 2000 (27:13 Md. R. 1212)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" discontinuity="true" effective="2012-02-01">Chapter revised effective February 1, 2012 (39:1 Md. R. 18)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
