<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Safety Standards for Trucks, Truck Tractors, Commercial Buses, and Type I School Vehicles</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <text>The standards, requirements, and procedures set forth in this chapter are applicable to equipment originally installed by the manufacturer or required by federal or State requirement on trucks (over 10,000 pounds GVWR), multipurpose passenger vehicles having a chassis rating greater than 10,000 pounds, truck tractors, commercial buses, and type I school vehicles.  Any questions regarding these standards or specifications shall be referred to the Automotive Safety Enforcement Division of the Maryland State Police. Any person constructing or reconstructing a vehicle shall assure the vehicle meets or exceeds all applicable federal and State safety standards.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Steering, Alignment, and Suspension.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Steering. Inspect the entire steering system including steering, wheel, steering column, lash, linkage, free play, and power steering for missing, loose, damaged, or worn parts.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Steering Wheel. The steering wheel shall be inspected to determine whether it is circular (complete rim) and free of cracks, breaks, or objects which will interfere with the safe steering of the vehicle. The inspection will also be made to determine whether the steering wheel is original equipment or equivalent, including diameter.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Inspect for missing, broken, or altered rim.</td>
                <td>(a) Steering wheel rim is broken, cut, or altered to the point that it is not continuous.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) Inspect for cracks or breaks which would interfere with<br/>safe steering.</td>
                <td>(b) There are cracks or breaks large enough to grasp clothing, hand, or fingers (including horn ring).</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(c) Inspect for objects which would interfere with safe steering. <br/>(d) Inspect for hand controls of vehicles equipped for physically disabled persons.</td>
                <td>(c) There are objects attached which would interfere with safe steering (if vehicle is equipped with hand controls for physically disabled, special equipment is acceptable provided it is part of the manual controls including steering knobs).</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(e) Inspect steering wheel for size and equivalency to original equipment.</td>
                <td>(d) Controls are not readily accessible (within arm's length) or are binding, damaged, or jammed.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td proof="needed"/>
                <td>(e) Steering wheel is not original or equivalent including size.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Energy Absorbing Steering Column. Some model vehicles may be equipped with an energy absorbing steering column. This special column was designed to absorb energy by controlling the collapsing of its components.  It collapses under impact from wither end of the column—steering gear end or steering wheel end. To determine whether the components are capable of functioning as designed, a careful inspection shall be performed, and include any objects on the steering column. An external examination of either shear pins or collapsible mesh-type material shall also be performed.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Inside Passenger Compartment:<br/>   (i) Inspect for separation of shear capsule from bracket and general looseness of wheel and column.<br/>  (ii) Inspect for objects mounted on steering column which would prevent it from collapsing upon impact.</td>
                <td>(a)<br/>  (i) Shear capsule is separated from bracket, or if wheel and column can be moved as a unit.<br/>  (ii) Objects (tachometer, etc.) mounted on steering column.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) Under Hood: Inspect for condition of shear pins and mesh-type collapsible portion.</td>
                <td>(b) Column shows indication of having been collapsed.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>Figure 1—TYPICAL SHEAR CAPSULE LOCATION.</aftertext>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Coupling. On heavier vehicles, there may be a flexible coupling in the steering column located just above the steering gear, usually known as "rag joint", "pot joint", or "U joint".</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) Steering Column (Heavy Vehicles):<br/>Inspect flexible coupling in steering column (if equipped) for excessive misalignment and tightness of adjusting screw or nut.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a)<br/>  (i) Flexible coupling is badly misaligned.<br/>  (ii) Clamp bolt (nut) is loose or missing.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>Figure 2—POT JOINTS, U-JOINT, RAG JOINT.</aftertext>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Lash, Free Play, and Travel. Inspect the steering system to determine whether excessive wear or improper adjustment of the linkage or steering gear exists. The vehicle shall be on a dry surface. If equipped with power steering, the engine shall be running and the fluid level and belt tension shall be within manufacturer's recommendation. (See Figure 3)</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td colspan="2" data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Lash or Free Play: <br/>   With front wheels in straight ahead position, turn steering wheel until turning motion can be observed at front wheels. Measure lash.</td>
                <td colspan="2">(a) A total movement in excess of that shown in the following table is measured at the steering wheel rim before the front wheels move.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="5">(b) Travel: <br/>   Turn steering wheel through a full right and left turn and feel for binding and jamming conditions (on vehicles without power steering it may be desirable to jack front wheels slightly).</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Steering Wheel<br/>Diameter up to</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Lash</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center">16 inches</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">2 inches</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center">18 inches</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">2-1/4 inches</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center">20 inches</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">2-1/2 inches</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center">22 inches</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">2-3/4 inches</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td proof="needed"/>
                <td colspan="2">Roughness, jamming, binding, or any excessive play in the steering linkage is present when turning the wheels from full right to full left.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>Figure 3—STEERING LASH OR FREE PLAY.</aftertext>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Linkage. Linkage Play. Excessive free play causes wheel shimmy, erratic brake action and steering control problems. Make sure any looseness detected is not wheel bearing free play. Spring or Torsion Bar Height. Optimum front spring height is established as part of the overall design of front wheel alignment angles.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td colspan="2" data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Steering Linkage Play.</td>
                <td colspan="2">(a) Measurement is found to be in excess of:</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="4">With the front end lifted properly, grasp front and rear of tire and attempt to turn assembly right and left—record movement<br/>at extreme front or rear sidewall of tire.</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Wheel Diameter up to</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Lash</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center">16 inches</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">1/4 inch</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center">17 inches</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">3/8 inch</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center">18 inches</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">1/2 inch</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) Follow procedure under wheel bearings—suspension for correct lifting. If equipped with brakes on the steering axle, <br/>they should be applied during the inspection either by another person or by use of a portable brake depressor, to eliminate wheel bearing play.</td>
                <td colspan="2">(b) Tie rod or drag link balls and sockets have play in excess of 1/8 inch.<br/>(c) Joints are not secured with cotter pins or other locking devices.<br/>(d) Steering stops allow tire to rub frame, metal, or other chassis parts.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(c) Visually inspect steering linkage for any gross misalignment of parts.</td>
                <td colspan="2">(e) Tie rods, tie rod ends, center or drag link, pitman arm, or idler arm are grossly misaligned.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(d) Visually inspect steering box and mounting.</td>
                <td colspan="2">(f) Steering box is leaking or mounting is loose.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>Figure 4.</aftertext>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Power Steering.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Inspect power steering belts for proper condition and tension.</td>
                <td>(a) Belts are frayed, loose, or cracked.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) With engine running inspect power steering system including gears, hoses, hose connections, cylinders, valves, pump and pump mounting for condition, rubbing, and leaking.</td>
                <td>(b) Hoses or hose connections have been rubbed by moving parts or are leaking.<br/>(c) Cylinders, valves, or pump show evidence of leakage or malfunction.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(c) Inspect power steering reservoir fluid level.</td>
                <td>(d) Pump mounting parts are loose, missing, or broken.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td proof="needed"/>
                <td>(e) Fluid level is less than manufacturer's recommendations.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td proof="needed"/>
                <td>(f) Power steering removed and not converted to full manual steering.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Wheel Alignment. There are five basic factors which are the foundation to front wheel alignment: caster, camber, toe-in, steering axis inclination, and toe-out on turns. All are mechanically adjustable except steering axis inclination and toe-out on turns. Overall front wheel alignment can be somewhat grossly indicated by measurement of front wheel toe. Excessive toe-in or toe-out is a general indication that a complete check should be made of all front wheel alignment factors. Rear wheel misalignment on vehicles with fixed rear suspension can be caused by broken or damaged springs, trailing rods, or center bolts and improper toe or camber adjustment on vehicles with independent rear suspension. If during road test there are no undesirable steering or handling reactions, caster and camber check is not necessary.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Toe (In—Out): <br/>  (a) With wheels held in a straight ahead position, drive vehicle slowly over the measuring device and record results.</td>
              <td>(1)<br/>  (a) Side slip or scuff exceeds 50 feet per mile.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(b) Measure dimensions A and B.</td>
              <td>(b) Dimension is beyond inspection limits.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>Figure 5—TOE (IN-OUT)</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>Caster. Caster is the forward or backward tilt, from vertical of the spindle support arm at the top. Improper caster can cause hard steering, low speed shimmy, wander, and brake pull problems.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(a) Measure caster (caster can only be measured with gauges).</td>
              <td>(a) There are adverse steering or handling reactions and the inspection limits are exceeded.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>Figure 6—CASTER ANGLES.</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>Camber. Camber is the inward or outward tilt of the top of the wheel from vertical. Improper camber can cause erratic tire wear problems, hard steering, and wander.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(a) Measure camber (camber can only be measured with gauges).</td>
              <td>(a) There are adverse steering or handling reactions and the inspection limits are exceeded.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>Figure 7—CAMBER ANGLES.</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>Rear Wheel Alignment. The wheelbase of a vehicle with tandem rear axles is determined by measuring from the center of the front wheel to the midpoint between the tandem axles. When measuring for tracking, the dimensions shall be taken between rear wheel centers. (See Figure 8 or 9)</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(a) Rear Wheel Alignment: Observe whether rear wheels follow front wheel tracks in "straight ahead" travel. <br/>(b) Alternate Method:</td>
              <td>(a) Rear wheel does not follow the front wheel track in "straight ahead" travel or if frame is bent, broken, or rusted to affect tracking.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(i) With vehicle on a level surface, adjust tracking gauge to the distance between the front and rear wheels of vehicle on one side and compare distance with the front and rear wheels on the opposite side. (Front wheels shall be in a straight ahead position.)</td>
              <td proof="needed">
                <p>WARNING</p>
                <p>Do not reject if vehicle is designed with different tread widths—front and rear.</p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(ii) Using a tape measure, determine the distance between the center of the front wheel spindle and the center of the rear axle drive shaft and compare from side to side (front wheels shall be in a straight ahead position).</td>
              <td>(b) The wheel base on one side is different from the wheel base on the other side by more than 1 inch.<br/>(c) Rear axle is obviously misaligned.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>
      <strong>
        <em>Agency Note:</em>
      </strong>
      <em> Not applicable if vehicle specifications indicate different left and right wheel base dimensions.</em>
    </aftertext>
    <aftertext>Figure 8—REAR WHEEL ALIGNMENT-TANDEM BUSES.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>Figure 9—TRUCK WHEEL BASE.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>Figure 10 — TYPICAL BALL JOINT.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>Figure 11 — PRE LOADED BALL JOINT.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>Figure 12 — WEAR INDICATING BALL JOINT.</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Suspension. Inspect the suspension system for missing, broken, damaged, worn, rusted, or modified wheel bearings, ball joints, control arms, springs, torsion bars, or frame that would affect vehicle stability.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ball Joints. In checking for motion of ball joints, check in accordance with manufacturer's specifications, keeping in mind that the load carrying joint is unloaded in procedures(a) and (b), below, and that a pry bar pressure sufficient only to lift the weight of the wheel assembly is required. If the inspector uses the leverage of a pry bar to exert excessive pressure, he can easily force an apparent ball joint movement and get a false reading. This may result in expensive replacement of perfectly good joints.  Therefore, only a 12- to 18-inch pry bar should be used.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td proof="needed">
                  <p>(a) Ball Joint Wear (without wear indicators).<br/>   (i) With the vehicle properly jacked, position a pry bar under the front tire and, with a lifting motion only sufficient to overcome the weight of the wheel assembly, move wheel up <br/>and down and observe movement shown on dial indicator or <br/>ball or joint checker (see Fig. 13).</p>
                  <p>(ii) Grasp the tire and wheel assembly at the top and bottom. Move in and out to detect looseness (more horizontal movement is permitted because of the nature of most ball joint construction). Some manufacturers do not accept horizontal movement as<br/>being indicative of ball joint wear. If this measurement is required it shall be made at the sidewall of the tire.</p>
                </td>
                <td proof="needed">
                  <p>(a)<br/>   (i) Ball joint movement is in excess of manufacturer's specifications.</p>
                  <p>(ii) Ball joint is equipped with tightener repair kit. Control bushings are not to be considered repair kits or tighteners. Refer to §C(1)(b) for procedures to check control bushing-type ball joints.</p>
                  <p>(iii) Ball joint has been repaired by heating or bending the socket assembly to eliminate movement.</p>
                  <p>(See Figure 10)</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) Ball Joint Wear (preloaded). Using the same method as in §C(1)(a)(i) and (ii) inspect for ball joint movement relative to <br/>its socket. These ball joints (marked "**" in specifications) are preloaded by rubber or springs under tension, and should have very little movement in a vertical direction.</td>
                <td proof="needed">
                  <p>(b) Ball joint movement is in excess of manufacturer's specifications.</p>
                  <p>(See Figure 11)</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ball Joint (wear-indicating). Some manufacturers provide a wear-indicating ball joint to facilitate inspection in which case a visual inspection is made with joints loaded.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Ball Joint Wear (wear-indicating): In vehicles with wear-indicating ball joints, support vehicle with ball joints loaded, wheels on the ground. Wipe grease fitting and checking surface free of dirt and grease; determine whether checking surface extends beyond the surface of the ball joint cover.</td>
                <td proof="needed">
                  <p>(a) Manufacturer's specifications for replacement are exceeded.<br/>(b) Ball joint is equipped with a tightener or repair kit.<br/>(c) Ball joint has been repaired by heating or bending the socket assembly to eliminate movement.</p>
                  <p>(See Figure 12)</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) Wear is indicated by the protrusion of the 1/2 inch diameter boss (exaggerated for illustration),into which the grease fitting is threaded. This round boss projects .050 inch beyond the surface of the ball joint cover on a new, unworn joint.</td>
                <td proof="needed"/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>Figure 13—BALL JOINT JACKING PROCEDURE.</aftertext>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Ball Joints (nonload carrying). Inspection of nonload carrying ball joints shall also be performed with the joints unloaded. With the vehicle properly jacked, inspect for any noticeable looseness.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Ball Joint Wear (nonload carrying): Using the same method <br/>as in §C(1) inspect for ball joint movement relative to its socket.</td>
                <td>(a) Any noticeable looseness is detected in a nonload carrying ball joint.<br/>(b) Manufacturer's specifications are exceeded.<br/>(c) Ball joint is equipped with a tightener or repair kit.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td proof="needed"/>
                <td>(d) Ball joint has been repaired by heating or bending the socket assembly to eliminate movement.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>King Pin or Spindle Bolts. Inspection of king pins or spindle bolts shall be made to determine whether there are any missing, broken, or worn parts that may affect the steering or suspension of the vehicle.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td colspan="2" data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Hoist the vehicle under the axle or control arm and grasp the top and bottom of the tire and attempt to move the assembly<br/> in and out. Record measurement at the sidewall of the tire.</td>
                <td colspan="2">Measurement at sidewall of tire is found to be in excess of:</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td proof="needed" rowspan="4" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Wheel Diameter up to</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Play</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">16 inches</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1/8 inch</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">17-18 inches</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1/4 inch</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">18 inches or more</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3/8 inch</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>Figure 14.</aftertext>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Wheel Bearings. Wheel bearings out of adjustment can cause wander, unequal brake action, and noise due to interference of parts.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td colspan="2" data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td proof="needed" rowspan="2">
                  <p>(a) Wheel Bearings and Suspension: With the vehicle lifted properly <br/>(if equipped with ball joints, they must be loaded), grasp the front tire <br/>top and bottom and rock it in and out, and record movement. To verify that any looseness detected is in the wheel bearing, notice the movement between the brake drum or disc and the backing plate or splash shield.</p>
                  <p>(b) Spring or torsion bar on lower arm, hoist at frame (see Figure 13).</p>
                </td>
                <td colspan="2">(a) Suspension play measurement at the sidewall of the tire is found to be in excess of:</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle"><em><u>Wheel Diameter up to</u></em><br/>16 inches <br/>17-18 inches<br/>18 inches or more</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle"><em><u>Play</u></em><br/>1/4 inch<br/>3/8 inch<br/>1/2 inch</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(c) Spring or torsion bar on upper arm, hoist at lower arm close to ball joint (see Figure 13).</td>
                <td colspan="2">(b) Wheel bearings are loose, rough, galled, or otherwise defective.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Springs and Torsion Bars.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Springs and Torsion Bars: With unloaded vehicle on a<br/>level surface, visually inspect the heights of the four corners<br/> of the vehicle. If necessary, use a measuring device and determine differences from side to side. Visually inspect for broken spring leaves or torsion bar damage. Inspect spring shackles, bushings and U-bolts. Visually inspect for presence and conditions of lift kits, blocks, or modification to suspension system and components.</td>
                <td>(a)<br/>   (i) Any spring, main, or torque leaf is broken.<br/>   (ii) Any spring with more than four leaves has two or more leaves broken.<br/>   (iii) Any spring with four or less leaves has a broken leaf.<br/>   (iv) Any torsion bar is broken.<br/>   (v) Any spring center bolt is broken.<br/>   (vi) More than two spacers are installed in coil springs or are loose.<br/>   (vii) Shackles or U-bolts are missing, broken, worn, loose, or extended causing gross misalignment of steering linkage or drive line angles.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) Hitches or Coupling Devices: Inspect fifth wheels on<br/>truck tractors for proper alignment, distortion, deformation, cracks, or missing parts.</td>
                <td>(viii) Any object or equipment extends below the bottom edge of a wheel rim.<br/>   (ix) Frame is rusted, broken, or damaged to affect the suspension, or the frame has been repaired and not fishplated, or the body is not securely attached to the frame.<br/>   (x) Multiple blocks are used as a means of raising the vehicle.<br/>   (xi) There is any evidence of looseness of any lift kit or suspension component.<br/>   (xii) Lift kit does not provide a means of aligning the spring center bolt, spring and axle or axle housing.<br/>   (xiii) U-bolts are not of sufficient length to protrude at least 1/4 inch beyond nut when tightened.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td proof="needed"/>
                <td>(b)<br/>   (i) Fifth wheel is distorted or cracked or is not properly aligned.<br/>   (ii) Mounting bolts or rivets are missing, cracked, or broken.<br/>   (iii) Fifth wheel is not properly or securely mounted.<br/>   (iv) Mounting holes for bolts or rivets which mount the fifth wheel have become elongated.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Air Suspension. Some school buses, commercial buses, trucks, and truck tractors may be equipped with air suspension systems. Inspection of the system consists of checking for air leaks, proper height and ride level.  CAUTION: The inspector should not use a creeper under the vehicle unless the vehicle is properly jacked and supported.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) With entire system drained of air, and while observing brake air pressure gauge, determine pressure at which air begins to lift the vehicle. Pressure regulator valve should not allow air into the suspension system until at least 55 psi is in braking system.</td>
                <td>(a) Air begins to lift the vehicle before 55 psi is indicated on pressure gauge.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) With air in system at normal operating pressure, inspect hoses, connections, and bellows for leaks and excessive deterioration (open air-operated doors and apply service brakes fully).</td>
                <td>(b) Air leakage rate is greater than 3 psi in 5 minutes.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(c) With air at normal operating pressure, observe height and level of vehicle relative to ground surface (this will indicate function of pressure regulator and height control valves).</td>
                <td>(c) Vehicle is resting on one or both axles or if the vehicle is not level (is listing to right or left).</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Air Suspension. Retractable Axle (not applicable to school vehicles). Some large vehicles may be equipped with retractable axles. If the axle is the type having independent suspension, the toe shall be checked the same as for the front suspension systems (see Figure 5).</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) On vehicles equipped with retractable axle(s), with air in <br/>the system at normal operating pressure, activate the axle lift control switch to wheels up and wheels down positions.</td>
                <td>(a) Axle fails to respond properly to the axle lift control switch.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) If retractable axle has independent suspension, inspect for toe.</td>
                <td>(b) Toe (in or out) is not reasonably close to zero (±/1/16 inch).</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(c) If retractable axle has independent suspension, with system activated and wheels down, inspect for ball joint wear as follows:<br/>  (i) Mark ball joints (upper and lower) with center punch as indicated in Figure 15, measure and record distance between punch marks.<br/>  (ii) Upper Ball Joint. Carefully place jack under axle so that jack screw extends through lower control arm, and raise upper control arm until wheel is clear of floor. Measure distance between punch marks.<br/>  (iii) Lower Ball Joint. Carefully place jack on top of lower control arm near ball joint and extend jack ram to underside of upper control arm—apply force until lower ball joint is fully compressed. Measure distance between punch marks.</td>
                <td>(c) Second measurement between punch marks on either ball joint exceeds first measurement by more than 3/32 inch.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>Figure 15—CHECKING BALL JOINTS FOR WEAR.</aftertext>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Shock Absorbers (if equipped).</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) With vehicle on a level surface, push down on each corner <br/>of the vehicle and release.<br/>(b) With vehicle on a hoist or jacked, visually inspect for missing, broken, loose, or damaged shock absorbers, mounting brackets, bolts or bushings, and excessive leakage.</td>
                <td>(a) Vehicle continues free rocking motion for two cycles after release, or shock absorbers are worn, damaged, or leaking to the extent vehicle stability is affected.<br/>(b) Shock absorbers, mounting bolts, bushings, or mounts are missing, broken, or loose.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td proof="needed"/>
                <td>(c) Severe leakage (not slight dampness) is present.<br/>(d) Any bushing is missing any portion of the bushing or is damaged, deteriorated, or dry rotted to a point that the bushing is broken or loose.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Lift Axle Air Pressure System. The lift axle shall have a certified air pressure to ensure the minimum load of 12,000 pounds for an evenly loaded vehicle with a gross vehicle weight of 70,000 pounds.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) The lift axle shall be designed so that when in the down position the axle can only be fully engaged. Check for proper operation.</td>
                <td>(a) The lift axle can be fully engaged and the axle is not in the down position.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) An air pressure adjustment control may not be located in <br/>the cab of the vehicle.</td>
                <td>(b) The air pressure adjustment control is located in the cab of the vehicle.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(c) A standard automotive air pressure valve for the lift axle shall:<br/>  (i) Be supplied on each vehicle that uses a lift axle;<br/>  (ii) Have an external valve stem;<br/>  (iii) Be located on the outside of the passenger side of the vehicle toward the rear of the cab, and shall be inspected for proper location;<br/>  (iv) Be readily accessible and visible to enforcement personnel.</td>
                <td>(c) The standard automotive air pressure valve:<br/>  (i) Is not supplied or is not in the proper location;<br/>  (ii) Does not have an external valve stem;<br/>  (iii) Is not located on the outside of the passenger side of the vehicle toward the rear of the cab;<br/>  (iv) Is not readily accessible and visible to enforcement personnel.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(d) Measure pounds per square inch (PSI) of air pressure on <br/>the lift axle using a standard automotive air pressure gauge and compare the PSI reading with the air pressure on the certification.</td>
                <td>(d) The air pressure on the lift axle does not measure equal to, or greater than, the PSI for 12,000 pounds axle load appearing on the manufacturer's certification.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Brakes.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Brake Inspection—Heavy Vehicles. Certain items of special interest shall be considered by the inspector when evaluating the braking on large, heavily loaded vehicles.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Safety. The vehicle or combination of vehicles may weigh many tons and too much stress cannot be put upon the safety of the inspector and others when testing the stopping ability of the vehicles. These tests shall be conducted with extreme care in order to prevent possible skidding, jackknifing, load shifting, and overturning. In particular, extreme care shall be used in testing liquid cargo-carrying vehicles under partially loaded conditions because of the sudden surging of the cargo.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Practicality.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A thorough brake inspection includes the inspection of the inside of the brake assembly. The removal of wheel hubs and drums from large commercial vehicles is difficult because of size and weight problems and extreme care shall be taken to assure they are properly returned to the axle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A thorough examination of the hydraulic, vacuum, or air systems will normally give a fair idea of general condition of the braking system, especially when augmented by a practical performance demonstration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Service Brake Performance Tests.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Road. Simple tests and visual procedures. Service brake tests shall be conducted on a substantially level, dry, hard, smooth surface road or area that is free from loose material, oil, or grease. Using the service brake only, the stopping ability of the vehicle shall be tested by one of the following methods:</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Service Brake Test: Method (1)—On Road: At a speed of 20 mph apply service brakes firmly. Observe whether the vehicle comes to a smooth stop.</td>
                <td>(a) Required stopping distance is greater than that contained in brake performance chart.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) Service Brake Test: Method (2)— On Road: Mount an approved decelerometer at centerline of vehicle. Level the decelerometer. At the speed of 20 mph, apply service brake firmly. Observe decelerometer reading. Determine whether vehicle pulls to the right or left.</td>
                <td>(b) The vehicle develops less deceleration than that contained in the brake performance chart.<br/>(c) Vehicle pulls severely to the right or left upon brake application.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Platform Test. Before attempting inspection by this method, the inspector should be trained and experienced in the use of the equipment and the equipment must have adequate capacity.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Method (3)—Platform Tester:<br/>Drive vehicle onto drive-on-and-stop platform tester. Apply brakes firmly at a speed from 4 to 8 mph without wheel lockup. All braking action shall take place on the platform.</td>
                <td>(a) Required stopping distance is greater than that contained in brake performance chart.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) This equipment may be used to inspect the relative effectiveness of each wheel. There shall be braking action on <br/>all wheels and the action on any one wheel shall be 75 percent <br/>or more of the action of the other wheel on the same axle.</td>
                <td>(b) Any wheel fails to indicate braking action. If the reading on any one wheel is less than 75 percent of the reading on the other wheel on the same axle.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Dynamic Brake Inspection. This test is for stations equipped with a roller-type brake dynamometer. The rollers should be dry, smooth and free of oil or grease. The equipment indicates both braking effort and imbalance. Brakes on front and rear axles are evaluated separately.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Method (4)—Roller-Type Brake Dynamometer (Force Measuring Type):<br/>   (i) Adjust tire to proper inflation.<br/>   (ii) Position vehicle on dynamometer rolls and begin test.<br/>   (iii) Follow equipment manufacturer's recommended testing procedures.</td>
                <td>(a) Readings are less than requirements on brake performance chart.<br/>(b) Any wheel fails to indicate braking action. If the reading on any one wheel is less than 75 percent of the reading on other wheel on the same axle.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Hydraulic System.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Tests and visual inspection procedures. Recommended for inspection programs which must accommodate a large volume of vehicles. Results will indicate whether a vehicle has reasonably safe brakes at the time of inspection. The engine shall be running when vehicles are checked with power assisted hydraulic systems. These procedures are applicable to vehicles equipped with hand controls for the physically handicapped.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Hydraulic System Leakage Test:<br/>While the vehicle is stopped, depress brake pedal under moderate foot force. The pedal height shall remain constant<br/>for 1 minute.</td>
                <td>(a) Brake pedal height cannot be maintained for 1 minute. <br/>(b)<br/>   (i) Less than 1/3 of the total available pedal travel remains.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) Pedal Reserve Test:<br/>   (i) While the vehicle is stopped, depress brake pedal under moderate foot force.<br/>   (ii) On vacuum assisted hydraulic systems with master cylinder booster, pedal travel has no significance. Do not<br/>inspect this item.</td>
                <td>(c) Air power assist push rod moves slowly toward master cylinder while air pressure is maintained for 1 minute.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(c) Hydraulic system with air power assist test for leakage. Apply 2-3 psi air pressure and maintain for 1 minute.</td>
                <td proof="needed"/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At least one wheel and drum assembly shall be removed from each axle equipped with brakes. On disc brakes only wheel assembly removal is necessary. Any wheel or drum assembly removal shall be on alternate sides. Always inspect a brake assembly which shows evidence of leaking fluid or grease. Do not remove hydraulic wheel cylinder dust boots for inspection. Leakage can be determined by pushing on the outside of the boot.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Hydraulic System—Visually inspect condition of hydraulic system.<br/>  (i) Inspect wheel cylinders for leakage and operation. Do not remove dust covers.</td>
                <td>(a)<br/>  (i) Wheel cylinders leak.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(ii) Inspect hydraulic hoses and brake lines for leaks, cracks, chafing, flattened or restricted section, and improper support.</td>
                <td>(ii) Hoses, brake lines are cracked, chafed, flattened, restricted, are rusted and pitting is visible, are insecurely fastened, or lines have been repaired or replaced with copper tubing or other material not designed for hydraulic brake lines. Hoses or brake lines are mounted to contact wheels or body during steering or suspension movement.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(iii) Inspect master cylinder for leakage and fluid level (be sure no dirt gets into reservoir when cover is removed and that the gasket is serviceable).</td>
                <td>(iii) Master cylinder leaks.<br/>  (iv) The fluid level in any section is less than 1/2 full.<br/>  (v) The gasket does not properly seal master cylinder.<br/>  (vi) Wheel cylinders fail to operate.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) Dual Hydraulic Circuits—In addition to the above, if vehicle is equipped with a brake warning light:<br/>  (i) Test for operation of light;<br/>  (ii) With ignition switch on, apply moderate foot force, and observe light; <br/>  (iii) Inspect both sections of reservoir.</td>
                <td>(b)<br/>  (i) Light is burned out.<br/>  (ii) Light comes on when brake pedal is depressed.<br/>  (iii) The fluid level in any section is less than 1/2 full.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td proof="needed"/>
                <td>(c)<br/>   (i) Brakes fail to function when applied.<br/>   (ii) Brakes do not remain applied until released.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Drums and Discs.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Some vehicles have a combination of disc (caliper) type brakes on the front wheels and drum-type brakes on the rear wheels.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>On vehicles equipped with disc brakes, some drag can be felt when turning the wheel and tire. This drag is not excessive if the wheel can be turned readily with both hands.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Brake Drums:<br/>   (i) Inspect the condition of the drum friction surface for any crack extending to the open edge of the drum (short hairline cracks should not be considered).<br/>   (ii) Inspect any crack on the outside of the drum.<br/>   (iii) Inspect for mechanical damage.<br/>   (iv) Inspect for contaminated friction surface.<br/>   (v) Measure inside diameter of drum.</td>
                <td>(a)<br/>   (i) There is a crack on the friction surface extending to the open edge of the drum.<br/>   (ii) There is any external crack.<br/>   (iii) There is evidence of excessive mechanical damage other than wear.<br/>   (iv) Friction surface is contaminated with oil, grease, or brake fluid.<br/>   (v) Inside drum diameter is greater than manufacturer's recommended limit, or the diameter stamped on the drum.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) Brake Discs (if equipped):<br/>   (i) Inspect for any crack extending to edge of disc.<br/>   (ii) Inspect for mechanical damage. <br/>   (iii) Inspect for contaminated friction surface.</td>
                <td>(b)<br/>   (i) There is any crack extending to the edge of the disc.<br/>   (ii) If a crack extends into the weld or more than one-half the outside diameter of a BF Goodrich steel disc.<br/>   (iii) There is evidence of excessive mechanical damage other than wear.<br/>   (iv) Friction surface is contaminated with oil, grease, or brake fluid.<br/>   (v) Thickness of disc is less than manufacturer's recommended limit or the thickness stamped on the disc.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Brake Linings and Pads.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Condition of Linings and Pads: <br/>  (a) Bonded Linings: Measure the lining thickness at the thinnest point.</td>
              <td>(1)<br/>  (a) Thinnest point of remaining bonded lining is less than 2/32 inch.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(b) Riveted Linings:<br/>      (i) Inspect for loose or missing rivets.<br/>      (ii) Measure lining thickness above rivet head at thinnest point.</td>
              <td>(b) Riveted Linings:<br/>      (i) Any rivet is loose or missing.<br/>      (ii) Remaining lining is less than 2/32 inch above any rivet head.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(c) Wire-Backed Linings: Inspect for wire showing in the friction surface.</td>
              <td>(c) Wire backing is visible in the friction surface.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(d) Bolted Linings (for buses and heavy vehicles):<br/>      (i) Inspect for loose or missing bolts.<br/>      (ii) Measure lining thickness at center of shoe.</td>
              <td>(d) Bolted Linings (for buses and heavy vehicles):<br/>      (i) Any fastening parts are loose or missing.<br/>      (ii) Remaining lining is less than 5/16 inch at center of shoe.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(e) All linings: Inspect for broken or cracked linings, and parts of linings not firmly attached to shoe. Also inspect for contamination and excessively uneven lining wear.</td>
              <td>(e)(i) Lining is broken, cracked, or not firmly and completely attached to shoe.<br/>      (ii) Friction surface is contaminated with oil or grease.<br/>      (iii) Lining wear is extremely uneven.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(f) Pads (Disc Brakes): Inspect thickness of friction pads. <br/>Many newer disc brake friction pads for vehicles in excess of 10,000 pounds GVWR are manufactured with a heat dissipater which is, in most instances, approximately 7/32 of an inch thick between the friction pad and the metal pad plate. These dissipaters, if allowed to contact the rotor, will cause damage to the rotor. Therefore, when measuring disc brake friction pad thickness, it must first be determined if the braking system being inspected is equipped with these heat dissipators. If heat dissipators are present, the brake friction pad thickness shall be measured so that no portion of the heat dissipator is included in the measurement. If no heat dissipators are present, the brake friction pad thickness will be measured in the normal manner to the metal pad plate or rivets.</td>
              <td>(f)(i) Any pad is less than 2/32 inch.<br/>       (ii) Any pad on BF Goodrich Air Actuated Disc Brakes has 1/8 inch or less lining remaining.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Mechanical Linkage. Includes the parking brake and manual brake controls on vehicles equipped for physically handicapped persons.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Condition of Mechanical Components:</td>
              <td>(1)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(a) Inspect for worn pins and missing or defective cotter pins.</td>
              <td>(a) Mechanical parts are missing, broken, or badly worn.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(b) Inspect for broken, missing or worn springs, cables, clevises, couplings, rods, and anchor pins.</td>
              <td>(b) Grease retainers are leaking (dampness is not cause for rejection).</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(c) Inspect for frozen, rusted, or inoperative connections, missing spring clips, and defective grease retainers.</td>
              <td>(c) There is excessive friction in pedal and linkage or in brake components.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(d) Inspect pedal shaft and bearings for high friction, wear, <br/>and misalignment.</td>
              <td>(d) Pedal levers are improperly positioned or misaligned.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(e) Inspect for restriction of shoe movement at backing plate <br/>and for binding between brake shoes and anchor pins.</td>
              <td>(e) Conversion of a self-adjusting mechanism that is not completely converted.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Vacuum System.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Condition of Vacuum Booster System: Visually inspect system for collapsed, broken, badly chafed, and improperly supported hoses and tubing, and loose or broken hose. clamps.</td>
              <td>(1)<br/>  (a) Hoses and tubing are leaking, collapsed, broken, badly chafed, improperly supported, or loose because of broken clamps.<br/> ( b) Hose or tubing is in good condition but exposed to danger from excessive heat, flying debris or rubbing.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Operation of Vacuum Booster System: <br/>  (a) Determine whether system is operating by first stopping engine, then depress brake pedal several times to deplete all vacuum in system. <br/>  (b) Then depress pedal with a light force. While maintaining this force on the pedal, start engine, and observe whether pedal moves slightly when engine starts.</td>
              <td>(2) Service brake pedal does not move slightly when engine is started while pressure is maintained on pedal.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Vacuum Reserve and Low Vacuum Indicators:<br/>  (a) Build full vacuum, then shut off engine and make as<br/> many full brake applications as possible. <br/>  (b) On vehicles with low vacuum indicator, build full <br/>vacuum, then shut off engine and reduce vacuum by making a series of moderate brake applications. A visible or audible signal should function when vacuum reaches 8 inches Hg on gauge.</td>
              <td>(3)<br/>  (a) Vacuum reserve is insufficient to make one full application after engine shutoff.<br/>  (b) Indicator fails to function when the system is reduced to 8 inches Hg vacuum.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Air System—Function: Compressor—Low Indicator—Governor.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) With air system fully charged, open all drain cocks in<br/>the system until gauge indicates zero pressure.</td>
              <td>(1) Time required to build pressure from 50-90 psi at fast idle exceeds:<br/>   (a) Single unit vehicle and school vehicle—3 minutes; or<br/>   (b) Combination vehicle—5 minutes.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Then close drain cocks and run engine at fast idle; <br/>record time to raise air pressure from 50-90 psi on gauge.</td>
              <td>(2) Low pressure warning fails to function when pressure is lowered to 60 psi.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Observe gauge pressure at which signal on low pressure indicator goes out or off.</td>
              <td>(3) Governor cut-out pressure is higher than 135 psi.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(4) Continue running engine and observe gauge pressure <br/>when governor cuts out.</td>
              <td>(4) Governor cut-in pressure is lower than 80 psi.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(5) With engine idling, make a series of brake applications<br/> and observe pressure when governor cuts in.</td>
              <td proof="needed"/>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Air Leakage and Reserve. It may be desirable to install in the system an air gauge (0-150 psi) which has 5 or 10 psi increments, so that small changes in pressure can be more easily observed.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td colspan="2" data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="2">(1) Air Leakage in System:<br/>Inspection for air leakage shall be made in two ways:</td>
              <td colspan="2">(1) Leakage exceeds the following limits:</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Brakes Fully Applied</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Brakes Released</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(a) With a fully charged system, stop engine and record <br/>the pressure drop in psi per minute with brakes fully applied.<br/>   (b) With a fully charged system, stop engine and record <br/>the pressure drop in psi per minute with brakes released.</td>
              <td>Single unit school vehicles—3 psi per minute. Combination vehicles—4 psi per minute.</td>
              <td>Single unit vehicles and school vehicles—2 psi per minute. Combination vehicles—3 psi per minute.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Compressed Air Reserve:<br/>   (a) Make a series of brake applications until low pressure warning signal operates. Stop engine and make one full<br/>brake application.<br/>   (b) With a fully charged system, stop engine and make <br/>one full brake application. Measure drop in reservoir pressure.</td>
              <td colspan="2">(2)<br/>   (a) Air reserve is not sufficient to permit one full brake application after engine is stopped.<br/>   (b) Reservoir pressure is lowered more than 20 percent of the first reading.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed">
                <p>(3) General Condition:<br/>   (a) Inspect all air hoses, tubes, and connections. Check attachments of all connecting lines and look for proper supporting parts. Be sure lines are free from contact with <br/>frame, axles, exhaust system, or other lines.</p>
                <p>(b) Inspect for leaks that may be heard from valves, diaphragms, piston cups, and connections. <br/>   (c) Inspect air pressure relief valve, tension and condition of compressor drive belts. Check air intake cleaner for being clogged or restricted.</p>
              </td>
              <td proof="needed" colspan="2">
                <p>(3)<br/>   (a) There are leaks, breaks, crimps, or cracks in the air hoses, tubes, or connections.<br/>   (b) Lines are being chafed by moving parts, or are touching the exhaust system.</p>
                <p>(c) Leaks in valves, diaphragms, piston cups, or connections can be heard.<br/>   (d) Air pressure relief valve does not operate.<br/>   (e) Compressor drive belts are badly worn, frayed, or loose.<br/>   (f) Air intake cleaner is clogged or restricted enough to prevent proper air intake.</p>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Air Brakes—Parking and Emergency Systems. Commercial buses and some trucks may be equipped with hand-operated controls for parking and emergency air brake systems.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Air Brake Parking and Emergency Systems:<br/>   (a) With air pressure in the braking system at operational <br/>level, set parking brake control and observe functioning of parking and emergency braking at wheels.</td>
              <td>(1)<br/>   (a) System fails to function properly. <br/>   (b) Vehicle can be moved with zero air pressure in system.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(b) Drain air from the system and observe whether parking <br/>and emergency brakes remain in an applied position (with no air pressure in the system, vehicle should remain "braked").</td>
              <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Actuator Reserve.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Actuator Reserve Test: <br/>   (a) On air or vacuum mechanical brakes, measure the stroke <br/>of  the air or vacuum chambers from fully released to fully applied position.<br/>   (b) On air-over-hydraulic brake systems, measure air chamber travel from fully released to fully applied position (some <br/>systems include a rod gauge for visual checking).</td>
              <td>(1)<br/>   (a) The push rod travel on S-Cam Brakes exceeds the maximum stroke listed in S-Cam Brakes—Push Rod Travel Limits Chart.<br/>      (i) Push rod travel on BF Goodrich Air Actuated Disc Brakes exceeds manufacturer's specification.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Push Rod/Slack Adjuster Angle: Measure push rod/slack adjuster angle with brakes applied.</td>
              <td>(2) Push rod/slack adjuster angle is less than 90 degrees with brakes applied.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Wedge Brakes Shoe Movement: Measure total shoe movement from released to applied positions.</td>
              <td>(3) Brake shoe movement on wedge brakes exceeds 1/16 inch.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <text>Figure 16—BRAKE CHAMBER PUSH ROD TRAVEL (TYPICAL).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Emergency Brakes. To avoid confusion between emergency and parking brake systems, refer to definitions (see §T). On vehicles equipped with spring-type emergency brake systems, manual operation of the control valve will also provide an effective parking brake system.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Emergency System—Function: <br/>   (a) Fully apply the emergency operating control, or release air pressure from the spring brake actuator using the manual control valve. Then:<br/>      (i) Observe locking and holding feature of the actuating mechanism.<br/>      (ii) Observe operating mechanism for "bottoming" before brakes are fully applied.<br/>      (iii) Observe if spring brakes apply when control valve is manually operated.<br/>      (iv) Inspect for worn, missing, or defective cotter pins, springs, rods, yokes, couplings, or anchor pins and cables.<br/>     (v) Observe if mechanism releases brakes when release control is operated.</td>
              <td>(1)<br/>   (a)<br/>      (i) Operating mechanism fails to hold brakes in applied position without manual effort.<br/>      (ii) Operating mechanism "bottoms" before brakes are fully applied.<br/>      (iii) Spring brakes fail to apply when control valve is operated.<br/>      (iv) Mechanical parts are missing, broken, or badly worn, or pull cables are badly worn, stretched, frayed, or not operating freely.<br/>      (v) Brakes do not fully release when release control is operated.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Emergency System—Performance:<br/>   (a) Method. At a speed of 10 mph apply emergency brake firmly. Vehicle must come to a stop within a reasonable distance.<br/>   (b) Method. Mount and level an approved decelerometer at centerline of vehicle. At a speed of 20 mph, apply emergency brake firmly. Observe decelerometer reading.</td>
              <td>(2)<br/>   (a) The vehicle fails to stop within a reasonable distance after emergency brake application.<br/>   (b) A decelerometer reading of at least 6 feet per second per second cannot be obtained.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>Parking Brakes. An emergency brake can also serve as a parking brake but a parking brake is not adequate to serve as an emergency brake. Most large vehicles with hydraulic brake systems and some large vehicles with air brake systems will have a parking brake located on the propeller (drive) shaft.  This type of parking brake is usually open and easily inspected.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Set the parking brake firmly to determine the reserve travel of the hand lever or foot pedal.</td>
              <td>(1)<br/>   (a) There is less than 1/3 pedal or lever reserve remaining.<br/>   (b) Brake fails to hold the vehicle on any grade on which it is operated.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Inspect the band or disc-type parking brake on the propeller (drive) shaft for the presence of oil or grease, condition of lining and adjustment.</td>
              <td>(2)<br/>   (a) There is oil or grease on the drum, disc, or lining.<br/>   (b) The lining is worn through to the steel band or shoe.<br/>   (c) The lining fails to make proper contact with the drum or disc when brake is applied.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Spring-type parking air brake system—inspect only for setting and release, not for travel reserve of the hand lever or foot pedal.</td>
              <td>(3) Spring-type parking air brake system fails to set or release.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>Brake Performance Chart. As of July 1, 1972, all vehicles subject to the regulations of the Bureau of Motor Carrier Safety are subject to the stopping requirements in this Brake Performance Chart except the column pertaining to Emergency Brake System, which are effective on vehicles manufactured after July 1, 1973.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed" data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
              <td colspan="3" data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Service Brake Systems</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Emergency<br/>Brake Systems</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">I</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">II</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">III</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">IV</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">V</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
              <td data-text-align="center">Braking force<br/>as a percentage<br/>of gross vehicle<br/>or combination<br/>weight</td>
              <td data-text-align="center">Deceleration<br/>in feet per<br/>second per<br/>second</td>
              <td data-text-align="center">Application<br/>and braking<br/>distance in<br/>feet from<br/>initial speed<br/>of 20 mph</td>
              <td data-text-align="center">Application<br/>and braking<br/>distance in<br/>feet from<br/>initial speed<br/>of 20 mph</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Passenger-carrying vehicles.<br/>  (a) Vehicles with a seating capacity of 10 persons or less, including driver, and built on a passenger car chassis.</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">65.2</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">21</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">20</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">54</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(b) Vehicles with a seating capacity of more than 10 persons, including driver, and built on a passenger car chassis; vehicles built on a truck or bus chassis and having a manufacturer's GVWR of 10,000 pounds or less.</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">52.8</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">17</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">25</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">66</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(c) All other passenger-carrying vehicles (including motorcycles).</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">43.5</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">14</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">35</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">85</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Property-carrying vehicles.<br/>   (a) Single unit vehicles having a manufacturer's GVWR of 10,000 pounds or less.</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">52.8</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">17</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">25</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">66</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(b) Single unit vehicles having a manufacturer's GVWR of more than 10,000 pounds except truck tractors. Combinations <br/>of a 2-axle towing vehicle and trailer having a GVWR of 3,000 pounds or less. All combinations of 2 or less vehicles in drive-away or tow-away operation.</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">43.4</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">14</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">35</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">85</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(c) All other property-carrying vehicles and combinations <br/>of property-carrying vehicles.</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">43.5</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">14</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">40</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">90</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>This deceleration as measured in brake tests cannot be used to compute the values in Column 4 because it is not sustained at the same rate over the entire period of the stop. The deceleration increases from zero to a maximum during a period of brake system application and brake force build-up. Also, other factors may cause the deceleration to decrease after reaching a maximum. The added distance which results because of a maximum deceleration is not sustained is included in the figures in Column 4 but is not indicated by usual brake testing devices for checking deceleration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>There is a definite mathematical relationship between the figures in Columns 2 and 3. If the decelerations set forth in Column 3 are divided by 32.2 feet per second per second, the Column 2 figures will be obtained (for example, 17 divided by 32.2 gives 52.8 percent). Column 2 is included in the tabulation because certain brake testing devices utilize this factor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The decelerations as in Column 3 are an indication of the effectiveness of the basic brakes, and as measured in practical brake testing are the maximum braking decelerations attained at sometime during the stop.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The distances in Column 4 and the decelerations in Column 3 are not directly related. Brake system "application and braking distance in feet" (Column 4) is a definite measure of the overall effectiveness of the braking system, being the distance traveled between the point at which the driver starts to move the braking controls and the point at which the vehicle comes to rest. It includes distance traveled while the brakes are being applied and the distance traveled while the brakes are retarding the vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The distance traveled during the period of brake system application and brake force buildup varies with vehicle type, being negligible for many passenger cars and greatest for combinations of commercial vehicles. This fact accounts for the variation from 20 to 40 feet in the numerical values in Column 4 for the various classes of vehicles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The deceleration requirement in Column 3 is the same for all classifications of vehicles except for passenger vehicles, not including buses, because brakes on vehicles in the second, third and fourth classifications are all capable with reasonable maintenance of producing the designated deceleration as measured by brake testing devices. A higher deceleration requirement is warranted for passenger cars in view of United States Department of Transportation/Federal Highway Administration test data.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>Decelerometers.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The method of brake system application and braking distance is not to be confused with the distance indicated by the inertia-type decelerometer and other existing brake testers, which often are purported wrongly to measure the vehicle stopping distance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The pendulum and U-tube decelerometers used for brake testing are instruments scaled to read deceleration or equivalent braking force (sometimes referred to as brake efficiency) in percentages. The principle of the pendulum-type decelerometer is that a pendulum on a vehicle moving at a uniform speed will assume a vertical position. When the vehicle speed is reduced by application of the brakes, the pendulum will swing forward to an angle away from the vertical. The tangent of the angle through which the pendulum moves is directly proportional to the deceleration. Basically, the U-tube fluid-type instrument is a closed glass tube formed in the shape of a U. When vehicle speed is reduced by braking, the inertia of the fluid causes the level in the glass tube to fall. The distance the level of the liquid falls is proportional to the deceleration in feet per second per second, which is read from a scale on the front part of the glass tube.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The vehicle will normally pitch because the lines of action of the inertia and braking forces are different. In order to minimize erroneous responses, the decelerometer, if used, should be put as close to the center of the vehicle as practical.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>Brake Testing Machines.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>These types of brake testers measure braking force at each wheel. The effectiveness of the brake testers that measure braking force in the testing of vehicles other than passenger vehicles or light trucks is very questionable.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The dimensions of these brake testers do not permit practical and reliable testing on combination vehicles. Use should therefore be restricted to two-axle vehicles. The simulated road surface of surface of these machines will occasionally exhibit much higher coefficients of friction than is possible on the highway. Excessive braking should therefore be avoided, be avoided, because braking distribution information is distorted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For drive-on-and-stop test machines, the vehicle is driven on the pads at speeds of 4 to 8 mph. When the brakes are applied at the time the vehicle is moving on the pads, the braking effort at each wheel causes a proportionate movement of the pad against the measuring system. The braking force on the pads is measured by indicating or recording instruments.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The roller-type brake testing machine has powered rollers that turn the individual wheels while the brakes are applied in order to measure the brake force developed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>S.</num>
      <text>Test Wheel Equipment. Any type of fifth or test wheel equipment can be used, if it obtains the following results:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>It measures the distance within plus or minus 3 percent of the values obtained by the "hot-shot" method, which uses an electrically fired gun.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The road speed of the test wheel is measured with a speedometer designed to hold the indicating hand at the speed from which the stop is initiated. The speedometer shall indicate the speed to within plus or minus 2 percent of the speed timed with a stopwatch over a measured mile.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>T.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Brake system" means a combination of one or more brakes and their related means of operation and control.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Deceleration" means the rate of reduction of the speed of the vehicle, expressed in feet per second per second.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Equivalent braking ratio" means the percentage ratio of the sum of retarding forces developed by each braked wheel to the "as tested" gross weight of the vehicle or combination.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Emergency brake system" means a brake system used for retarding and stopping the vehicle in the event of a malfunction in the service brake system (this function may be performed by the parking brake system or by a portion of the service brake system, or by a separate brake system).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Parking brake system" means a brake system used to hold and maintain a vehicle in a stationary position (a positive mechanical means is employed to hold the brake applied when the vehicle is unattended).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Pedal reserve" as applied to hydraulic, mechanical, or power-assisted hydraulic brakes, means the amount of total pedal travel left in reserve when the pedal is depressed to the brake-applied position (the purpose of the pedal reserve check is to ascertain the degree of the brake adjustment and to demonstrate satisfactory brake actuating system condition).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Service brake system" means a brake system used for retarding, stopping, and controlling the vehicle under normal operating conditions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Stopping distance" means the distance traveled by a vehicle from the point of application of force to the brake control, to the point at which the vehicle reaches a full stop.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Wheels and Tires.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Tire Inspection. Reference is made to Figures 17 and 18 for visual aid in determining tire wear. A radial ply tire may not be used with a nonradial-type tire on the same axle. All tires on the steering axle shall be the same size and type of construction. All tires shall be the same size on the same axle.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect for tire wear:<br/>  (a) Tires without tread wear indicators.<br/>  (b) Tires with tread wear indicators.<br/>  (c) For cord exposure. <br/>(2) Inspect for tread cuts, snags, or sidewall cracks.<br/>(3) Inspect for bumps, bulges, or knots.<br/>(4) Inspect for fabric breaks, and exposed or damaged body cords.<br/>(5) Inspect for regrooved or recut tires (note: regrooved tires <br/>are not permitted on school vehicles or on any steering axle).</td>
              <td>(1)<br/>  (a) Tire is worn so that less than 2/32 inch tread remains when a measurement is made in any groove at three locations spaced approximately equally around outside of tire. Exception: 4/32 inch on front tires or steering axle.<br/>   (b) Tire is worn so that the tread wear indicators contact the road in any two adjacent grooves at three locations spaced approximately equally around outside of tire. Exception 4/32 inch on front tires or steering axle.<br/>   (c) Tire has a worn spot that exposes the cord through the tread.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(6) Inspect for mismatching of tire types.</td>
              <td>(2) Tire has tread cuts, snags, or sidewall cracks in any direction, and deep enough to expose cords.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(7) Inspect for mismatching of tire sizes (duals).</td>
              <td>(3) Tire has visible bumps, bulges, or knots indicating partial failure or separation of the tire structure.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(8) Inspect for tire size.</td>
              <td>(4) Tire has an unrepaired fabric break or sidewall has damaged body cords.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(9) Visually inspect for restricted usage marking on tire such <br/>as reclassified tires.</td>
              <td>(5) Tire has been regrooved or recut below original groove depth, except those that are designed and can be readily identified as regroovable.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(10) Inspect for recapped tires on front wheels or steering <br/>axle of school vehicle.</td>
              <td>(6) Tires are not the same size on the same axle.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(11) Inspect valve stems for leaks, damage or cracks.</td>
              <td>(7) The diameter of one of the duals is not within 1/2 inch of the other, or if the gauge block can be inserted between the tire and caliper.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed"/>
              <td>(8) Tires are smaller than manufacturer's specified minimum or of a larger size that causes tire and body contact during different vehicle attitudes.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed"/>
              <td>(9) Tire is:<br/>   (a) Marked "For Farm Use Only";<br/>   (b) Marked "Off Highway Use Only";<br/>   (c) Marked "For Racing Use Only";<br/>   (d) A metal studded snow tire during period when prohibited (April 1—October 31 in Allegany, Carroll, Frederick, Garrett, and Washington counties. Reject in other areas at any time).</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed"/>
              <td>(10) Recapped tires are used on the front wheels or steering axle of a school vehicle.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed"/>
              <td>(11) Valve stem is leaking, cracked, or damaged, or shows evidence of wear.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <text>Figure 17—TIRE CONSTRUCTION</text>
      <text>Figure 18—TIRE WEAR</text>
      <text>Figure 19—MATCHING OF TIRES.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Wheel Inspection.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect wheel bolts, nuts, or lugs.</td>
              <td>(1) Wheel bolts, nuts, studs, or lugs are loose, missing, or damaged.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Inspect for wheel damage.</td>
              <td>(2) Any part of the wheel is bent, cracked, rewelded, or damaged, to affect safe operation of the vehicle; loose or missing spokes on spoke-type wheels; or any wheel not the original, equivalent, or the one designated by the wheel manufacturer (Specialty Equipment Market Association, SEMA, or U.S./D.O.T. approved wheels and adapters are acceptable.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Inspect for rims and lock rings for matching, condition, tightness of nuts and clamps, and evidence of slippage.</td>
              <td>(3) Rims and lock rings are obviously mismatches; nuts and clamps are loose; or there is evidence of slippage.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Fuel System.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The fuel system includes the fuel tank, fuel pump, and necessary piping to carry the fuel from the tank to the carburetor or to the injection system.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Visually examine the fuel tank, fuel tank support straps, filler tube (rubber, plastic, metal), tube clamps, fuel tank vent hoses or tubes, filler housing drain, overflow tubes, filler cap, fuel filter, carburetor, or injector system.</td>
              <td>(1)<br/>   (a) Any part of system is not securely fastened. <br/>   (b) There is fuel leaking at any point in the system.<br/>   (c) Fuel tank cap is missing.<br/>   (d) Overflow or vent tube is missing or obstructed.<br/>   (e) Filler tube is leaking, collapsed, or deteriorated.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Inspect for proper operation of choke, hand throttle, and accelerator.</td>
              <td>(2) If choke, throttle, or accelerator does not function properly, such as binding, roughness, or failure to return to released position.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Exhaust System.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The exhaust system includes the exhaust manifold, and all piping leading to and including the muffler, catalytic converter, resonator, and the tail piping.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) With engine running and the vehicle on a hoist, lift, or over a pit, visually inspect the exhaust pipes, mufflers, resonators, and tail pipes <br/>for leaks, deterioration, proper mounting, damage and general condition.<br/>   (a) Rusted or corroded areas shall be given particular attention. <br/>   (b) Holes in the system made by the manufacturer for drainage are <br/>not cause for rejection.</td>
              <td>(1) Vehicle has no muffler. <br/>(2) There are loose or leaking seams or joints. <br/>(3) There are holes caused by corrosion or temporary repairs made to the exhaust pipe, muffler, resonator, or the tail pipe. Welding or brazing is considered a permanent repair if it does not leak. <br/>(4) Tail pipe end is pinched or obstructed or does not extend beyond the passenger or driver area.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) The tail pipe shall extend beyond the passenger or occupant compartment and the enclosed cargo area if it is open to the driver or passenger area.</td>
              <td>(5) The system is not properly mounted, or securely fastened, or if the seam of a muffler or resonator in a school vehicle faces the fuel tank, fuel lines, or floor of the vehicle.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Type I school buses shall have a full length tail pipe extending beyond the rear wheels and exiting beyond the side or rear of the body unless the vehicle is equipped with a left side exhaust system which meets the following criteria: <br/>   (a) The exhaust pipe may not pass within 12 inches of the gasoline tank or its connections unless a suitable baffle is installed between the exhaust system and these components. On vehicles with left side mounted gasoline tanks, compliance with this requirement may be more difficult; however, this requirement shall still be met.</td>
              <td>(6) There are loose muffler baffles; the vehicle is equipped with cut-out or similar device; or the system is not original or equivalent.<br/>(7) Any part of the system passes through the occupant compartment, or there are any leaks in the heat exchange boxes or ducts of vehicle using engine exhaust heat to warm the interior of the vehicle.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(b) No part of the exhaust system may pass within 12 inches of any flexible brake hose or vacuum booster unless a suitable baffle is <br/>installed between the exhaust system and these components.</td>
              <td>(8) The tail pipe does not extend beyond the occupant compartment and the enclosed cargo area if it is open or the occupant compartment.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(c) The exhaust pipe should be at approximately a 45-degree angle <br/>as it approaches the left body line to prevent back pressure and heat buildup. <br/>   (d) The exhaust pipe shall be deflected downward as it approaches <br/>the left side of the body.</td>
              <td>(9) On a school vehicle, the system passes directly under the emergency door, there is a reduction in size of tail pipe after it leaves muffler, or system does not extend to outside, not more than 1/4 inch beyond the rear bumper as originally designed.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(e) The exhaust pipe shall exit behind the driver's compartment.</td>
              <td>(10) Exhaust pipe, muffler, or tail pipe is not leak proof construction. Flexible pipe that does not leak is acceptable, except on school vehicles.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed"/>
              <td>(11) It emits continuous exhaust fumes or smoke which obscures persons or objects from view.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed"/>
              <td>(12) On a school vehicle, the system passes directly under the emergency door, or there is any reduction in size of the tail pipe after it leaves the muffler.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed"/>
              <td>(13) Type I school vehicle with left side exhaust does not meet the requirements established.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Emission Control System on School Vehicles.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation represents the current recommendations of the Vehicle Emissions Inspection Panel of the Motor Vehicle Manufacturers Association, Inc., regarding engine maintenance inspection required to minimize vehicle emissions. This section is advisory and is primarily related to 1968 and later models.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The inspection of emission control systems applies only to spark ignition engines, not to diesels.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>This regulation is applicable to school vehicles only.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Crankcase Ventilation. The ventilation system of the crankcase is common to engines using either an "air injection" system of control or an "engine modification" system. The engine should be warm and running at idle before inspection of vent system.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center">
                <em>Procedures</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Crankcase Ventilation Valve: Inspect valve to make sure it is an approved device.</td>
              <td>(1) Valve is not designed for the vehicle if originally equipped.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Plumbing Connections: Inspect plumbing connections for tightness and proper routing of blow-by fumes and fresh air.</td>
              <td>(2) Plumbing is loose, restricted, broken, leaking, or improperly routed.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Operation: Disconnect crankcase ventilation valve from engine. A definite "hissing" noise is heard if valve is OK, caused by air being "sucked" into the valve and hose. Place finger or thumb over end of valve and feel for suction.</td>
              <td>(3) There is no hissing sound or suction.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Air Injection Type—Idle Speed and Timing. An air injection-type exhaust emission control system can be identified by an air pump and a distribution system to the exhaust ports. The air pump is normally driven by a belt off the crankshaft or water pump pulleys. Only the plumbing, idle speed and ignition timing need be inspected. Reference is made to the Idle Setting Limits Table I.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Installation: With engine stopped, inspect hose connections and belts for tightness and breakage. Inspect ignition wiring for damage or deterioration. With engine running, inspect for air or vacuum leaks.</td>
              <td>(1)<br/>  (a) Belt is loose.<br/>  (b) Connections are loose, broken, or leaking.<br/>  (c) Ignition wires are damaged or deteriorated.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Idle Speed: With engine at operating temperature and at idle speed:<br/>  (a) Automatic Transmission: Check idle speed as recommended by vehicle manufacturer;<br/>  (b) Manual Transmission: Place transmission in neutral and check idle speed.</td>
              <td>(2) Idle speed is beyond limits in Table I.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Basic Ignition Timing: Disconnect vacuum spark advance line(s) and insert plug(s). Connect timing light and check basic ignition timing (when finished replace line(s)).</td>
              <td>(3) Basic timing is beyond limits in Table I.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Engine Modification Type—Idle Speed and Timing. An "engine modification" control system may be most easily identified as one without an air pump. The emissions are primarily controlled by engine design. The items to be inspected are vacuum, idle speed, ignition timing, and idle air-fuel mixture by measuring the carbon monoxide (CO) content of the exhaust. Refer to Table II, Idle Setting Limits.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Installation. With engine stopped, inspect vacuum hose connections for tightness, or breakage. Inspect ignition wiring for damage or deterioration. With engine running inspect for air or vacuum leaks.</td>
              <td>(1) Connections are loose, broken, or leaking.<br/>(2) Ignition wires are damaged or deteriorated.<br/>(3) Idle speed is beyond limits in Table II.<br/>(4) Basic timing is beyond limits in Table II.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Idle Speed: With engine at operating temperature and at idle speed.<br/>  (a) Automatic Transmission: Check idle speed as recommended by vehicle manufacturer;<br/>  (b) Manual Transmission: Place transmission in neutral and check idle speed.</td>
              <td proof="needed"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Basic Ignition Timing: Disconnect vacuum spark advance line(s) and insert plug(s). Connect timing light and check basic ignition timing. (When finished remove plug(s) and replace line(s).)</td>
              <td proof="needed"/>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Engine Modification-Type Fuel Mixture (Carbon Monoxide). The carbon monoxide (CO) concentration in the exhaust of most vehicles may not be more than 3 percent. Be sure that the testing is done by an experienced operator and that the exhaust analyzer is properly calibrated.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Idle Fuel Mixture: With engine at normal operating temperature and idle speed, insert sampling probe into tail pipe and note carbon monoxide (CO) concentrations. (Major leaks in the exhaust system could cause erroneous readings.)</td>
              <td>(1) Carbon monoxide concentrations are greater than limits in Table II.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <text>
        <table class="no-border-heading">
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="4" data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Table I<br/>IDLE SETTING LIMITS TABLE (Exhaust Air Injection Systems)</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="bottom">
                <em>Manufacturer</em>
              </td>
              <td colspan="2" data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>RPM<br/>Manufacturer's<br/>Specifications</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">
                <em>Basic Ignition <br/>Timing in Degrees</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">American Motors Corp.</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">+100</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">-25</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">±3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">Ford Motor Co.</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">+100</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">-50</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">±3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">General Motors Corp.</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">+100</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">-50</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">±3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">International Harvester Co.</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">+100</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">-25</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">±3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">Jeep Corp.</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">+100</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">-25</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">±3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">Other</td>
              <td colspan="2" data-vertical-align="middle">As specified by the particular manufacturer</td>
              <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <text>
        <table class="no-border-heading">
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="5" data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Table II<br/>IDLE SETTING LIMITS TABLE (Engine Modification Systems)</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="bottom">
                <em>Manufacturer</em>
              </td>
              <td colspan="2" data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>RPM<br/>Manufacturer's<br/>Specifications</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">
                <em>Basic Ignition <br/>Timing in Degrees</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">
                <em>Mixture</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">American Motors Corp.</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">+100</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">-25</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">±3</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3% CO Maximum</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">Ford Motor Co.</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">+100</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">-50</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">±3</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3% CO Maximum*</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">General Motors Corp.</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">+100</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">-50</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">±3</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3% CO Maximum</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">International Harvester Co.</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">+100</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">-25</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">±3</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Set with tachometer method</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">Jeep Corp.</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">+100</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">-25</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">±3</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3% CO Maximum</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">Other</td>
              <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
              <td colspan="2" data-vertical-align="middle">As specified by the particular manufacturer</td>
              <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <text>* or 13.3/1 Air-Fuel Ratio-Minimum.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Bumpers and Rear Metal Frame.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Bumpers shall be inspected for broken or missing parts, abnormal protrusions, sharp edges, or conditions that could be hazardous to persons. The bumpers shall be securely mounted to the vehicle and be capable of absorbing a reasonable degree of impact. Every truck with a GVWR over 10,000 pounds, except truck tractors and vehicles engaged in drive-away/tow-away operations, which is so constructed that the body or the chassis assembly, if without a body, has a clearance at the rear end of more than 30 inches from the ground when empty, shall be equipped with a permanent rear bumper or metal frame attached to the underside of the rear of the truck. The bumper or frame may not be any wider than the width of the truck, and may not be more than 30 inches above the highway when moving and shall be constructed of heavy gauge steel. The maximum transverse distance from the widest part of the vehicle at the rear to the bumper or metal frame may not exceed 18 inches. The frame shall be constructed so as not to interfere with lights or other warning devices. Any truck so constructed and maintained that the body, chassis, or other parts thereof afford the protection required by this section shall be deemed in compliance with this section. The provisions of this section do not apply to vehicles where the installation of the required bumper or metal frame would prevent operation of the vehicle to secure its designated purpose.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Bumpers: Applies to all bumpers of vehicles where equipped. Front bumper does not have to extend to extreme <br/>sides of vehicle except on school vehicles. Inspect bumpers <br/>for hazardous condition and unsafe mounting.</td>
              <td>(1)(a) Bumper is broken or missing.<br/>     (b) Abnormal protrusions or conditions which could be hazardous.<br/>     (c) Bumpers not securely mounted or capable of absorbing a reasonable degree of impact.<br/>     (d) School vehicle bumpers do not extend to the extreme sides of the vehicle.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Rear Metal Frame: Inspect frame for proper size, proper mounting, interference with lights or warning devices, and<br/>type of construction.</td>
              <td>(2)(a) Rear protector frame does not conform to requirements.<br/>     (b) Is missing when required.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Rear Wheel Protector Flaps.</heading>
    <text>A person may not operate, cause or permit to be operated any bus or truck on the highways of this State unless it is equipped with suitable metal protectors or substantial flexible flaps behind the rearmost wheels of the vehicle to prevent the projection of rocks, dirt, water, or other substances to the rear and to minimize side spray. This regulation does not apply to any farm tractor or any vehicle registered as a farm truck or to uncoupled truck tractors or other vehicles where the construction is such that complete freedom around the wheel area is necessary to secure the designed use of the vehicle.</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="center">
              <em>Procedures</em>
            </td>
            <td data-text-align="center">
              <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>A. The protectors or flaps shall have a ground clearance of<br/> not more than one-third of the horizontal distance from the bottom edge of the protector or flap to the centerline of the <br/>axle, provided, however, that no protector or flap need be<br/>closer to the ground than 6 inches under any condition of loading. The protector or flap shall extend laterally at least <br/>the width of the tire or tires being protected.</td>
            <td>A. Measurement A is longer than 1/3 the length of Measurement B and the vehicle is not equipped with flaps (see Figures 20 and 21).<br/>B. Protector or flap does not extend laterally at least the width of tire or tires.<br/>C. Protectors or flaps not securely attached to the vehicle.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>B. If any truck or bus is so designed or constructed that the objectives of this regulation are accomplished by reason of fender or body construction or other means of enclosure, <br/>either permanent or temporary, then the requirements of this regulation have been satisfied.</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>Figure 20—REAR WHEEL PROTECTOR FLAP REQUIREMENTS.</text>
    <text>Figure 21—REAR WHEEL PROTECTOR FLAP REQUIREMENTS.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Fenders.</heading>
    <text>Fender inspection shall include condition, mounting, and coverage of wheels and tires. If the body of the vehicle does not provide coverage, the vehicle shall then be equipped with suitable metal protectors or substantial flexible flaps behind the rearmost wheels of the vehicle.</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="center">
              <em>Procedures</em>
            </td>
            <td data-text-align="center">
              <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>A. Fenders shall be securely attached to the vehicle and inspected for tears, sharp or jagged edges, sufficient coverage of the wheel and tire both from the body outward and to the front and rear of tires and wheels. Fenders may be extended outward to compensate for tire and wheel changes provided these extensions:</td>
            <td>A.<br/>  (1) Fender has tears, sharp or jagged edges. <br/>  (2) Fender is not securely fastened to the body. <br/>  (3) Fender does not extend outward from the body to cover the top of the wheel and tire.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>(1) Provide required coverage of wheels and tires; <br/>  (2) Are constructed of substantial materials;</td>
            <td>(4) The rear of all fenders do not extend downward to the horizontal centerline of the wheel.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>(3) Are securely attached to fenders the fenders;<br/>  (4) Have all edges rolled to eliminate sharp or jagged edges;</td>
            <td>(5) Fronts of all fenders do not extend forward from the vertical centerline of the wheel to at least within a 45-degree angle of the horizontal centerline.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>(5) Do not contact tires during different vehicle attitudes;<br/>  (6) On trucks and truck tractors, applies only to front fenders and rear fenders when equipped.</td>
            <td>(6) Fender has been extended downward to compensate for suspension modifications.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td>(7) Fender is missing.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td>(8) The vehicle is not equipped with flaps behind the rear wheels when required.</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>Figure 22—FENDERS.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Body and Sheet Metal — Applicable to School Vehicles Only.</heading>
    <text>Body exterior components and sheet metal parts, if damaged or dislocated so that they project from the vehicle to present a safety hazard to occupants, pedestrians, or other vehicles, may be cause for rejection of the vehicle.</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
              <em>Procedures:</em>
            </td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
              <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>A. Protruding Metal: Inspect for torn metal parts, moldings, rub rails, etc., which may protrude from vehicle.</td>
            <td>A.<br/> (1) Body components or sheet metal are subject to rejection if a condition exists which is hazardous to occupants, pedestrians or other vehicles.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td>(2) Torn metal, broken glass, or other loose or dislocated parts protrude from the surface of the vehicle which is hazardous to occupants, pedestrians, or other vehicles.</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>Figure 23—SCHOOL VEHICLE CONSTRUCTION AND SEATING.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Lighting.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General Lamp and Reflector Inspection. This includes all original equipment, exterior lighting plus whatever lights are authorized. School vehicles have special marking and lighting to assure their identity. Refer to diagrams of front and rear views (Figures 27 and 29).</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Visual Check of Lamp Function: Turn on the night driving lights and visually check the following: (Check (a) and (b) <br/>with ignition switch on, engine should not be running.)</td>
              <td>(a) A bulb or sealed beam unit fails to light.<br/>   (b) Turn signals do not properly indicate right or left when so switched.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(a) Actuate turn signal lever to right and left, and observe function of turn signal lights (1962 or newer motor vehicles <br/>shall be so equipped. Turn signals shall emit white or amber light to the front and red or amber to the rear).</td>
              <td>(c) Turn signals do not self-cancel if so equipped (if, because of age of the vehicle, parts are not available, this defect may be certified.)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(b) Place vehicle in all forward gears and check back-up <br/>lamps (if vehicle is so equipped).</td>
              <td>(d) Back-up lamp system functions when the vehicle is in any forward gear, or back-up lamp system fails to function when vehicle is in reverse.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(c) If vehicle is so equipped, actuate the following and <br/>observe lamps:<br/>      (i) Hazard warning lamps (1968 or newer motor vehicles shall be so equipped);<br/>      (ii) Brake system warning lamps (if equipped);<br/>      (iii) Indicator lamps for: hazard warning lamps, turn <br/>signals, high beam headlamps and school vehicle flashing warning lamps; <br/>   (iv) Stop lamps (1968 or newer motor vehicles shall have<br/>two red or amber stop lamps; all others one);<br/>   (v) Headlamps—upper and lower beam: Headlamps shall<br/>emit white light.</td>
              <td>(e) A lamp shows color contrary to law (red or blue light to the front; white light to the rear, except license plate lamps and back-up lamps when vehicle is in reverse. <br/>   (f) A lamp fails to light proper filament when switched.<br/>   (g) A required or authorized lamp, lens, or reflector is obscured by any object or shielded by a nontransparent material.<br/>   (h) A lamp or reflector is not mounted to properly direct or reflect light.<br/>   (i) A lamp assembly or reflector is loose or improperly mounted.<br/>   (j) A tail lamp has a cracked or broken lens which emits a white light to the rear.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Observe function of:<br/>   (a) Tail lamps (red, two on 1972 or newer models; all <br/>others one). <br/>   (b) Parking lamps (white or amber to the front; red to the<br/> rear). In addition, every bus, truck, or truck tractor 80 inches <br/>or more in overall width shall be equipped as required in §§A(2)(c), (d), (e), and (f).<br/>   (c) Side marker lamps, one amber front and one red rear <br/>on each side. Vehicles over 30 feet in overall length one <br/>amber centrally located with respect to length of the vehicle.</td>
              <td>(k) A lamp, lens, or reflector is not an approved type.<br/>   (l) Equipped with any unauthorized emergency or warning lamps.<br/>   (m) A school vehicle manufactured after December 31, 1972, and the alternating flashing warning lamps are not equipped with shields or hoods.<br/>   (n) Headlamp output is less than 5,000 candlepower on high beam or less than 3,500 candlepower on low beam.<br/>   (o) Indicator lamps (if equipped) fail to function.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(d) Reflectors: one amber front and one red rear on each<br/> side. Vehicles over 30 feet in overall length, one amber centrally located with respect to length of the vehicle. 1972 <br/>or newer models shall be equipped with at least two red reflectors on the rear. All other models shall have one. Reflectors may be combined with other lamps.</td>
              <td>(p) Dash lamps do not illuminate fuel gauge, oil pressure gauge, alternator gauge, temperature gauge, speedometer, odometer, air pressure, or vacuum gauge.<br/>  (q) Any required lamp is missing.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(e) Clearance lamps: two amber front and two red rear to indicate overall width of the vehicle. One on each side of the vertical centerline of the vehicle at the same height and as near the top of the vehicle as possible. If the vehicle is equipped with three red identification lamps on the top rear, the rear clearance lamps may be mounted at the top or bottom of the vehicle.</td>
              <td proof="needed"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(f) Identification lamps: three amber front and three red rear grouped in a horizontal row with lamp centers spaced not less than 6 inches or more than 12 inches apart and mounted on a permanent structure of the vehicle as close as possible to vertical centerline of the vehicle. Required on front of all 1972 or newer trucks and buses and all truck tractors. Rear of all trucks and buses. If the cab of the vehicle is not more than 42 inches at the front roof line, a single identification lamp mounted at the center of the cab is acceptable.</td>
              <td proof="needed"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(g) License plate lamp or lamps—White.</td>
              <td proof="needed"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(h) Emergency/Warning Lamp when permitted or required. School vehicles manufactured before January 1985 shall be equipped with two front and two rear alternately flashing red warning lamps unless approved otherwise. School vehicles manufactured after December 1984 shall be equipped with two front and two rear alternately flashing amber warning lamps in addition to the two front and two rear alternately flashing red warning lamps. After January 1, 1994, all school vehicles shall be equipped with two front and two rear alternately flashing red and amber warning lamps. On school vehicles manufactured after December 31, 1972, the warning lamps shall be equipped with shields or hoods.</td>
              <td proof="needed"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(i) Red and Blue: Law enforcement vehicles; Red and/or White: Fire department, rescue vehicles, ambulances, State vehicles used for hazardous material spills; Amber: Service, maintenance, tow-trucks, escort, and slow moving farm vehicles.</td>
              <td proof="needed"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(j) Dash Lamps.</td>
              <td proof="needed"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(k) All interior lamps (school vehicle only):<br/>     (i) Interior lamps to illuminate aisle;<br/>     (ii) Stepwell lamp;<br/>     (iii) Red identification lamp for emergency door (if equipped);<br/>     (iv) Indicator lamp or signal for operation of flashing warning lamps;<br/>     (v) Indicator lamps to monitor warning, turn signal, and hazard lamps.</td>
              <td proof="needed"/>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <text>Figure 24—TRUCK TRACTOR LIGHTING REQUIREMENTS.</text>
      <text>Figure 25—SINGLE UNIT TRUCK LIGHTING REQUIREMENTS.</text>
      <text>Figure 26—COMMERCIAL BUS LIGHTING REQUIREMENTS.</text>
      <text>Figure 27—TYPE I SCHOOL VEHICLE LIGHTING REQUIREMENTS.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Preparation for Headlamp Aim Inspection. Preparation for headlamp and aim inspection is to be done by owner of vehicle before inspection. Frame leveling and wheel alignment inspection is done before inspection. Frame leveling and wheel alignment inspection is done at the station. Any one of the items listed below can affect the inspection results and may cause rejection of the vehicle. To prevent this and reduce inspection time, the owner should have the first three items completed before inspection.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Remove excessive ice and mud from under fenders.<br/>(b) Inflate tires to recommended pressures.<br/>(c) Be sure that lenses are clean; check for burned out bulbs and proper beam switching.<br/>(d) Check for faulty wheel alignment or improper tracking of the rear axle.</td>
                <td proof="needed"/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Headlamp.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>High Beam. Vehicle shall be equipped with either the dual headlighting system consisting of four 5 1/4-inch diameter units, two of which shall be No. 1 and two of which shall be No. 2; or four 6 1/2 × 4 1/2 inch rectangular units, two of which shall be No. 1A and two of which shall be No. 2A; four 5.93 × 3.64-inch rectangular-type F units, two of which shall be LF units and two of which shall be UF units; or a single headlighting system consisting of two 7-inch units; or two 8 × 5 inch rectangular units; or an approved bulb and reflector-type system. All units bearing the marking No. 2 shall be inspected and aimed on low beam. All units bearing the marking No. 1 or no number shall be inspected and aimed on high beam. Headlamp inspection and aiming by the photoelectric-optical method, not applicable to school vehicles, requires a level area sufficient for the vehicle and test equipment. The test equipment shall be accurately calibrated to the floor and accurately aligned to the vehicle. Additional lighting information is contained in §§E, F, and G (limits are in inches at 25 feet). Labeling requirements for sealed beam headlamps manufactured on or after July 1, 1979: 5 3/4 inch type 1-1C1, type 2-2C1; 6 1/2 inch by 4 1/2 inch type 1A-1A1, type 2A-2A1; 7 inch type 2-2D1; 8 inch by 5 inch type 2B-2B1; type F 5.93 inch by 3.64 inch—low beam—LF, high beam—UF. Type F units require a special aimer adapter and must be aimed in accordance with the manufacturers' recommended procedures. Bulb and reflector-type headlamps currently approved contain a 9004 Sylvania bulb in a normal reflector unit or an H-4 bulb in a sealed reflector unit. Sealed reflector units contain a glass bubble which encases the bulb when in place which can be detected by removing the bulb and determining if the bubble exists.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <aftertext><strong>Agency Note</strong>: Labeling requirements for sealed beam headlamps manufactured on or after July 1, 1979: 5 3/4 inches Type 1-1C1, Type 2-2C1; 6 1/2 inches by 4 1/4 inches Type 1A-1A1, Type 2A-2A1; 7 inches Type 2-2D1; 8 inches by 5 inches Type 2B-2B1</aftertext>
    <aftertext>Figure 28.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>Figure 29—TYPE 1-SCHOOL VEHICLE HEADLAMP CONFIGURATIONS.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>
      <table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
              <em>Procedures:</em>
            </td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
              <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>(a) High Beam (Type 1):<br/>    (i) With the vehicle in the inspection area and test equipment properly calibrated and aligned to the vehicle, switch headlamps to high beam and observe hot spot.</td>
            <td>Center is:<br/> (a) Horizontally:<br/>    (i) More than 4 inches right, or <br/>    (ii) More than 4 inches left of the vertical centerline;</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>(ii) When properly aimed, the center (hot spot) of the high intensity zone is set on the vertical and horizontal centerlines of the lamp.</td>
            <td>(b) Vertically:<br/>    (i) More than 4 inches above, or <br/>    (ii) More than 4 inches below the horizontal centerline.</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </aftertext>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>Low Beam. Inspect the low beam headlamp in the same method as indicated for high beam. Always inspect the following sealed beam units on low beam only: 5 3/4 inch diameter or 6 1/2 × 4 1/4 inch rectangular marked type 2 or 2A and 7 inch diameter or 8 × 5 inch rectangular marked type 2 or 2B.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(a) Low Beam (Type 2):<br/>   (i) Under same procedure as high beam aim inspection, <br/>switch headlamps on low beam and observe either the center <br/>of the high intensity zone or the left and top edges of the zone.<br/>   (ii) When properly aimed: Edges of high intensity zone —<br/>Top edge centered on horizontal centerline, left centered on vertical centerline.<br/>   (iii) Center of high intensity zone. Adjust hot spot to <br/>15 inches horizontally and 11 inches vertically.</td>
              <td proof="needed">
                <p>(a) Beam pattern:<br/>   (i) Left edge is horizontally more than 4 inches right or left of the vertical centerline; or <br/>   (ii) Top edge is vertically more than 4 inches above or below the horizontal centerline;</p>
                <p>(b) Hot spot is:<br/>   (i) Horizontally less than 11 inches or more than 19 inches; or<br/>   (ii) Vertically less than 7 inches or more than 15 inches.</p>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Headlamp—Applicable School Vehicles Only.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To compensate for the various conditions of loading encountered during inspection, the frame or body floor shall be made level before checking. This will provide a standard condition for inspecting all vehicles and may be accomplished by using a combination of blocks under the rear wheels or a lifting device (jack) or both for the front end. A spirit level may be laid along the frame side member.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td proof="needed">
                  <p>(a) Headlamp Aim:</p>
                  <p>(b) High Beam: Attach mechanical aimer to headlamp unit according to instructions. Take readings.</p>
                </td>
                <td>High Beam:<br/> (a) Horizontal aim is more than:<br/>   (i) 4 inches to the left; or<br/>   (ii) 4 inches to the right.<br/> (b) Vertical Aim is:<br/>   (i) more than 4 inches up; or<br/>   (ii) more than 4 inches down.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(c) Low Beam: Attach mechanical aimer to headlamp <br/>unit according to instructions. Take readings.</td>
                <td>Low Beam:<br/> (a) Horizontal aim is more than:<br/>   (i) 4 inches to the left; or<br/>   (ii) 4 inches to the right.<br/> (b) Vertical aim is:<br/>   (i) more than 4 inches up; or<br/>   (ii) more than 4 inches down.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Place vehicle in a darkened location of sufficient size for the vehicle and an additional 25 feet from lamps to screen. Level the vehicle frame as described in §C(1). The vehicle shall be located accurately in front of the screen. An approved marked screen and adequate test area are required.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>High Beam: With vehicle properly located, switch <br/>headlamps  to high beam and observe center of high <br/>intensity zone on the screen.</td>
                <td>Center is:<br/> (a) Horizontally:<br/>   (i) More than 4 inches right; or<br/>   (ii) More than 4 inches left of vertical centerline.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td proof="needed"/>
                <td>(b) Vertically:<br/>   (i) More than 4 inches above; or<br/>   (ii) More than 4 inches below the horizontal centerline.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>Figure 30—AIMING SCREEN BEAM PATTERN-HIGH BEAM.</aftertext>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Inspect the low beam headlamp in the same method indicated as for high beam. Always inspect the following sealed beam units on low beam only: 5 3/4 inch diameter or 6 1/2 × 4 1/4 inch rectangular units marked type 2 or 2A and 7 inch diameter or 8 × 5 inch rectangular units marked type 2 or 2B.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Low Beam: With vehicle properly located, switch headlamps <br/>to low beam and observe left and top edges of high intensity zone on the screen.</td>
                <td>(a) Left edge is horizontally:<br/>   (i) More than 4 inches left; or<br/>   (ii) More than 4 inches right of vertical centerline.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td proof="needed"/>
                <td>(b) Top edge is vertically:<br/>   (i) More than 4 inches above; or<br/>   (ii) More than 4 inches below the horizontal centerline.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>Figure 31— AIMING SCREEN BEAM PATTERN-LOW BEAM.</aftertext>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Fog Lamp and Auxiliary Driving Lamps. If a vehicle is equipped with either fog lamps or auxiliary driving lamps they shall be properly aimed.  Fog lamps shall be mounted on the front of the vehicle at a height not more than 30 inches or less than 12 inches above the level surface on which a vehicle stands. Only two fog lamps are allowed by law. Auxiliary driving lamps shall be mounted on the front of the vehicle at a height not more than 42 inches or less than 16 inches above the level surface on which the vehicle stands. Only two auxiliary driving lamps are allowed by law. The mounting heights of auxiliary driving lamps do not apply to emergency vehicles.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Auxiliary Driving or Fog Lamp Aim Inspection:<br/>   (a) Under the same procedure as for headlamp inspection switch on the lamps and observe the location of the high intensity zone or hot spot on the screen. <br/>   (b) Symmetrical Beam: When properly aimed, the center of <br/>the high intensity zone is set 4 inches below the horizontal centerline of the lamp and centered on the vertical centerline. <br/>   (c) Asymmetrical Beam: When properly aimed, the center of the high intensity zone is set 7 inches below a horizontal centerline of the lamp and centered on the vertical centerline. <br/>   (d) Measure height of auxiliary driving or fog lamp.</td>
              <td>(1) Symmetrical:<br/>   (a) Center of high intensity zone is more than:<br/>      (i) Horizontally: 4 inches left, or 4 inches right of the vertical centerline; or<br/>      (ii) Vertically: Less than 4 inches below the horizontal centerline.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed"/>
              <td>(2) Asymmetrical Beam: Same as low beam headlamps:<br/>   (a) Center of high intensity zone is more than:<br/>      (i) Horizontally: 4 inches left, or 4 inches right of the vertical centerline; or<br/>      (ii) Vertically: Less than 7 inches below the horizontal centerline.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed"/>
              <td>(3) Fog lamps or auxiliary driving lamps are mounted higher or lower than allowed.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed"/>
              <td>(4) Vehicle is equipped with more than two fog lamps.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed"/>
              <td>(5) Vehicle is equipped with more than two auxiliary driving lamps</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Asymmetrical beam" (nonsymmetrical) means a beam in which both sides are not symmetrical with respect to the median vertical plane of the beam. All lower beams are asymmetrical.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Back-up lamp" means a lamp used to provide illumination behind the vehicle, and to provide an indicator when the vehicle is in reverse gear.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Clearance lamp" means (on trucks and buses 80 inches or more wide) a lamp which shows to the front or rear of a vehicle, mounted on the permanent structure of the vehicle as near as practicable to the upper left and right extreme edges to indicate overall width and height of the vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Cornering lamp" means a steadily burning lamp used when the turn signal system is operating to supplement the headlamps by providing additional road illumination in the direction of the turn.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Driving lamp" means the auxiliary lamp or lamps that may be used to supplement the upper beam of the regular headlamps.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Emergency warning lamp" means a lamp which provides a flashing light to identify an authorized vehicle on an emergency mission. The emergency signal may be an oscillating lamp, a rotating beacon, or pairs of alternately or simultaneously flashing lamps.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Fog lamps" means a lamp which may be used with the lower beam headlights to provide illumination under condition of rain, snow, dust, or fog.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Hazard warning lamp" means a turn signal lamp which flashes simultaneously to warn of the presence of a vehicular hazard.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Headlamps.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Five and 3/4 Inch Round Sealed Beam Unit.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>"Type 1 sealed beam unit" means a sealed beam unit 5 3/4 inches in diameter having a single filament and providing only an upper beam distribution of light. This unit is identified by a number 1 on the lens and is aimed on the upper beam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>"Type 2 sealed beam unit" means a sealed beam unit 5 3/4 inches in diameter having two filaments, one filament providing the lower beam and one filament providing fill-in light for the upper beam. This unit is identified by a 2 on the lens and is aimed on the lower beam.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Seven Inch Round Sealed Beam Unit" means a sealed beam unit 7 inches in diameter providing an upper and lower beam. This unit is identified by a number 2 on the lens and is aimed on the lower beam. If there is no identifying number on lens, it means a sealed beam unit 7 inches in diameter providing an upper and lower beam. It is aimed on the upper beam.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Eight Inch by 5 Inch Rectangular Sealed Beam Unit" means a sealed beam unit providing an upper and lower beam. This unit is identified by a number 2B on the lens and is aimed on the lower beam.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Six 1/2 by 4 1/2 Inch Rectangular Sealed Beam Unit.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Type 1A—means a sealed beam unit having a single filament and providing only an upper beam distribution of light. The unit is identified by a number 1A on the lens and is aimed on the upper beam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Type 2A—means a sealed beam unit having two filaments, one filament providing fill-in light for the upper beam. This unit is identified by a number 2A on the lens and is aimed on the lower beam.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>"Bulb and reflector headlamps" means a lamp assembly providing an upper and lower beam light by means of a replaceable bulb. These lamps are aimed on lower beam. They shall be capable of producing at least 5,000 candlepower output on upper beam and 3,500 candlepower output on lower beam, and must be capable of being aimed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>5.93 x 3.64 Inch Rectangular Sealed Beam Unit.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Type LF—sealed beam unit having a single beam filament and providing only a lower beam distribution of light. The unit is identified by the designation LF on the lens. A special aimer adapter is required for aiming, and aiming must be accomplished in accordance with the manufacturer's recommended procedures.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Type UF—sealed beam unit having a single beam filament and providing only a upper beam distribution of light. The unit is identified by the designation UF on the lens. A special aimer adapter is required for aiming, and aiming (if applicable) must be accomplished in accordance with the manufacturer's recommended procedures.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Headlamp lower beam" means a distribution of light so directed as to avoid glare in the eyes of oncoming drivers while providing illumination ahead of the vehicle and intended for use in congested areas and on highways when meeting other vehicles within a distance of 500 feet.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Headlamp upper beam" means a distribution of light intended primarily for distant illumination and for use on the open highway when not meeting other vehicles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Identification lamps" (on trucks and buses 80 inches or more wide) means lamps used in groups of three, in a horizontal row, which show to the front or rear or both, having lamp centers spaced not less than 6 or more than 12 inches apart, mounted on the permanent structure as near as practicable to the vertical centerline and the top of the vehicle, to identify certain types of vehicles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Indicator lamp" means a lamp visible to the operator of a vehicle that indicates:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Appropriate electrical circuits are in operation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Malfunction of vehicle performance; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Requirement for remedial action by the operator of the vehicle.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Lane changer" means a device, usually incorporated in the turn signal switch which will actuate the turn signal lamps when held by the driver. It is intended for momentary use for signaling a lane change. When released by the operator, it will return to neutral and de-activate the signal lamp.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"License plate lamp" means a lamp used to illuminate the license plate on the rear of a vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"Operating units or switches" means devices by which the functioning lamps are controlled.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>"Parking lamp" means lamps used to designate the front of a parked vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>"Passing lamp" means an auxiliary lamp or lamps that may be used to supplement the low beam of a standard headlamp system. It is not intended for winding roads or congested city areas.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>"Reflective devices" means a device used on vehicles to give an indication to an approaching driver by reflected light from the headlamps of approaching vehicles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>"SAE Lighting Identification Code" means a series of standardized markings for lighting devices which a manufacturer or a supplier may use to mark his product to indicate the SAE lighting standard or standards to which the device is designed to conform. The code is not intended to limit the manufacturer or supplier in applying other markings to the devices.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>"Sealed beam headlamp assembly" means a major lighting device used to provide general illumination ahead of the vehicle. It consists of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>One or more sealed beam units (bulb assembly);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Means for mounting securely to the vehicle;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Means to permit required aim adjustment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>"Sealed beam unit" means an integral and hermetically sealed optical assembly with the name "Sealed Beam" molded in the lens.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>"Side marker lamp" means a lamp on the left and right sides, beamed to the side, and intended to indicate vehicle length. They are located near the front and rear on each side and, for vehicles over 30 feet in length, are also located at the midpoint (intermediate side marker).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>"Stop lamp" means a lamp giving a steady warning light to the rear of a vehicle, to indicate the intention of the operator of the vehicle to reduce speed or stop.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>"Symmetrical beam" means one in which both sides are symmetrical with respect to the median vertical plane of the beam. Lamps having symmetrical beam are:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Five 3/4 inch diameter type I;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Five 3/4 inch diameter type 2 (upper beam filament);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Six 1/2 by 4-1/4 inch type 1A;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Six 1/2 by 4-1/4 inch type 2A (upper beam filament);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Eight by five inch type 2B (upper beam filament);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>All 7 inch diameter units (upper beam filament).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>"Tail lamp" means a lamp used to designate the rear of a vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>"Turn signal lamp" means a lamp which provides a flashing warning light to indicate the intended direction of the turn.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>SAE Identification Code (J759C SAE Handbook).</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The following list is an identifying code for lights and signaling devices:</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="bottom">
                  <em>Device</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>SAE Identification<br/>Code Designation</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) Reflex Reflectors:</td>
                <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(i) Class A</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">A</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(ii) Class B (used before 1969 only)</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">B</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(b) Motorcycle and motor driven cycle turn signal lamps</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">D</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(c) Side turn signal lamps—vehicles 30 ft. (9.1m) or more in length</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">E</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(d) Side turn signal lamps—vehicles less than 30 ft. (9.1m) in length</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">E2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(e) Fog lamps</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">F</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(f) Sealed beam headlamps (marking applies to housing or unit)</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">H</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(g) Turn signal lamps—Class A</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">I</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(h) Turn signal lamps—Class A spaced less than 4 in. (102mm) from headlamp</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">I2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(i) Turn signal flasher</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">J590e or J5906</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(j) Hazard warning signal flasher</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">J945b or J945</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(k) Warning lamp alternating flasher</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">J1054</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(l) Cornering lamps</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">K</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(m) License plate lamps</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">L</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(n) Motorcycle and motor driven cycle headlamps—motorcycle type</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">M</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(o) Motor cycle and motor driven cycle headlamps—motor driven cycle type</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">N</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(p) Spot lamps</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">O</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(q) Parking lamps</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">P</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(r) Clearance or side marker or identification lamps</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">P1 or P2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(s) Combination clearance and side marker lamps</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">PC</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(t) Turn signal operating units Class A</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Q</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(u) Turn signal operating units Class B</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">QB</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(v) Vehicular hazard warning signal operating unit</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">QC</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(w) Backup lamps</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">R</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(x) Stop lamps</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">S</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(y) Tail lamps</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">T</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(z) Supplemental high mounted stop and turn signal lamps</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">U</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(aa) Liquid burning emergency flares</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">V</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(bb) Warning lamps for emergency, maintenance and service vehicles</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">W or W1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(cc) Warning lamps for school buses</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">W2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(dd) 360-degree emergency warning lamps</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">W3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(ee) Emergency warning device</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">W4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(ff) Electric emergency lanterns</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(gg) Driving lamps</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Y</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(hh) Auxiliary low beam lamps</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Z</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All equipment for testing headlamps shall comply with the Society of Automotive Engineers Recommended Practice for Headlamp Inspection Equipment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Headlamp Testing Machines.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Headlamp Testing Machine. When a headlamp testing machine is used, it shall give results equivalent to those obtained using a screen. It shall be in good repair and adjustment, and shall be used in accordance with the manufacturer's instructions. A machine using a photoelectric cell or cells to determine aim should also have a visual screen upon which the beam pattern is projected proportionally to its appearance and aim on a screen at 25 feet. The visual screen shall be plainly visible to the operator and have horizontal and vertical reference lines to permit visual appraisal of the lamp beam.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Mechanical Aimer (applicable to school vehicles only). When a mechanical aimer is used, it shall be in good repair and adjustment, and shall be used according to the manufacturer's instruction and shall be calibrated to the slope of the floor on which the vehicle stands.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Screen (applicable to school vehicles only). When a screen is used, it should be 5 feet high x 12 feet wide with a matte white surface well shaded from extraneous light, and properly adjusted to the floor on which the vehicle stands. Provisions may be made for moving the screen so that it can be aligned parallel with the rear axle so that a horizontal line drawn perpendicularly from the centerline of the screen will pass an equal distance midway between the two headlamps. The screen shall be provided with a fixed vertical centerline, two laterally adjustable vertical tapes, and one vertically adjustable horizontal tape.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Electrical System.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Electrical System. To save time, the inspector should develop his own plan or sequence for checking miscellaneous electrical items, many of which can be inspected while inspecting other items.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Horn shall be securely fastened, produce audible but not harsh or loud sound, and have a horn button readily accessible to the operator. <br/>(2) Switches shall all function properly.<br/>(3) Wiring shall be well insulated.<br/>(4) Connections shall be tight and secure.</td>
              <td>(1) Horn:<br/>   (a) Is loose;<br/>   (b) Fails to function;<br/>   (c) Produces loud or harsh sound;<br/>   (d) Not equipped with horn button within arm's reach of operator.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(5) Automatic Transmission Only: Neutral safety starting switch—determine that starter operates with gear selector in P and N only.</td>
              <td>(2) Switches: Fail to function.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(6) Battery—Check general condition.</td>
              <td>(3) Wiring:<br/>   (a) Insulation is bare, cracked, or broken;<br/>   (b) Shows evidence of burning or short-circuiting.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed"/>
              <td>(4) Connections are loose or shows signs of excessive corrosion.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed"/>
              <td>(5) Starter operates with gear selector in any gear other than P and N:<br/>   (a) Gasoline ignition engine: Apply parking brake and remove center wire from coil or distributor before checking to be sure that engine does not start with vehicle in running gear. On Delco Remy high energy ignition system disconnect harness connector at distributor on V6 and V8 engines. Disconnect at coil on inline 4 and 6 cylinder engines;<br/>   (b) Diesel engine: Apply parking brake, fully apply service brake, and pull stop out to no-fuel position before checking.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed"/>
              <td proof="needed"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed"/>
              <td proof="needed"/>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Interior and Emergency Equipment — Applicable to School Vehicles Only.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Seats, Stanchions, Rails.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Seats and Seat Belts: <br/>   (a) Inspect seats for secure anchorage to floor; <br/>   (b) Inspect seats for condition of frames, springs, and cover material; <br/>   (c) Inspect driver's and occupant's seat belt webbing for fraying, splitting, tearing, malfunctioning buckles; loose, damaged, or missing anchorages or damaged or weakened floor pan; <br/>   (d) Inspect for torn or broken interior metal trim, etc., which may present a hazard to occupants.</td>
              <td>(1)<br/>   (a) Any seat anchor bolts are not securely fastened to floor or side mounting rail.<br/>   (b) Cover material is torn, springs are exposed, seat frame is loose, cracked or broken.<br/>   (c) Driver's seat belt is missing.<br/>   (d) Seat belt webbing is frayed, split or torn.<br/>   (e) Buckles do not operate properly.<br/>   (f) Belt anchorages are loose, badly corroded, or not fastened to belt.<br/>   (g) Belt mounting surfaces are badly deformed, damaged, or corroded.<br/>   (h) Floor pans are damaged or weakened at anchorage.<br/>   (i) Occupant's seat belts are missing when required.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Stanchions and Guard Rails (when applicable): Inspect all stanchions, guard rails, grab handles, etc., for tightness, mounting, and general condition.</td>
              <td>(2)<br/>   (a) Looseness is detected, or fastening parts are missing, broken, or cracked.<br/>   (b) Cover material or padding is torn (when applicable).</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Visors and Defroster. Sun visors shall be located in front and above the driver and passenger positions.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Sun Visors:<br/>Inspect sun visor for loose, missing or broken parts which would prevent it from being adjusted, or holding an adjustment.</td>
              <td>(1)<br/>   (a) Visor is missing.<br/>   (b) Visor on driver's side cannot be positioned to protect driver's eyes from sun.<br/>   (c) Visor is difficult to adjust or will not maintain a set adjustment.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Windshield Defroster:<br/>Inspect for presence and proper functioning of windshield defroster. The device and/or auxiliary fans, etc., shall keep windshield, window at driver's left, and glass in service door clear.</td>
              <td>(2) Windshield and defroster defogger is missing or fails to function properly.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Heaters, Step or Stepwell, and Vents.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Interior Heaters:<br/>   (a) Inspect heater or heaters for capability of maintaining inside temperature of 50°F at minimum average January outside temperature.<br/>   (b) Inspect for leakage and general condition of heating system including heater hoses, tubing, shielding, valves, and controls.</td>
              <td>(1)<br/>   (a) Heater cannot maintain a temperature of 50°F at minimum average January outside temperature.<br/>   (b) Leakage or malfunction of heating system is detected.<br/>   (c) Interior heater or pipes are not properly shielded.<br/>   (d) Cut off valve in engine compartment is not present.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Step or Stepwell: Inspect general condition of step or stepwell at all door entrances.<br/>(3) Ventilation: Check for function and general condition of ventilating system.</td>
              <td>(2)<br/>   (a) Step or stepwell is blocked or cluttered, or surface material is loose.<br/>   (b) Light for the stepwell is missing or fails to function.<br/>   (c) Step or stepwell is not covered with nonskid material.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed"/>
              <td>(3) System fails to furnish fresh air under operating conditions.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Fire Extinguisher, First Aid Kit, and Tire Chains. Every school vehicle shall be equipped with a dry chemical fire extinguisher, and first aid kit container mounted in plain view in the driver's compartment, and where applicable, tire chains.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Fire Extinguisher:<br/>   (a) Inspect for presence, location, condition, and accessibility of the fire extinguisher. Every school vehicle shall be equipped with a nontoxic dry chemical fire extinguisher having a rating of at least 5lb./10B.C. and equipped with a gauge.</td>
              <td>(1) Extinguisher:<br/>   (a) Is missing; <br/>   (b) Seal is broken;<br/>   (c) Is not readily accessible to driver;<br/>   (d) Gauge shows low-reading.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) First Aid Kit: Inspect for presence, accessibility, and general condition of first aid kit. It shall be readily identifiable and contain at least the following:<br/>   (a) Four adhesive bandages;<br/>   (b) Four adhesive tapes—1 inch by 5 yards;<br/>   (c) One bandage compress—2 inches by 48 inches;<br/>   (d) Four bandage compresses—4 inches by 4 inches;<br/>   (e) Two gauze compresses—3 inches by 3 inches;<br/>   (f) Three gauze compresses—24 inches by 72 inches;<br/>   (g) Two triangular bandages—40 inches;<br/>   (h) One gauze bandage—2 inches by 6 yards;<br/>   (i) One wire splint;<br/>   (j) Two tourniquets;<br/>   (k) One pair of forceps;<br/>   (l) One pair of scissors;<br/>   (m) Unit kit—empty.</td>
              <td>(2) First aid kit contents:<br/>   (a) Are missing;<br/>   (b) Are not readily accessible;<br/>   (c) Package seals are broken;<br/>   (d) Not readily identifiable.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Tire Chains:<br/>When tire chains are required, inspect for presence and condition of tire chains.</td>
              <td>(3) Tire chains:<br/>   (a) Are missing, when required;<br/>   (b) Are not serviceable;<br/>   (c) Are not proper size.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Warning Devices.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Inspect for presence, condition, and accessibility of:<br/>(1) At least three red electric lanterns or three red emergency reflectors which meet Bureau of Motor Carrier Safety <br/>Standards;</td>
              <td>Warning devices:<br/> (1) Are missing, do not function as designed, or are not of <br/>an approved type;</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) At least three red-burning fuses, 30-minute stand-up <br/>type, stored in a canister near the driver.</td>
              <td proof="needed">
                <p>(2) Are improperly stored;</p>
                <p>(3) Are not readily accessible.</p>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Color.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">Color—Inspect for proper color:</td>
              <td>Colors do not match standard.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Body—National School Bus Yellow;</td>
              <td proof="needed"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Lettering, body trim, and bumpers shall be black. <br/>Bumpers may be covered with a retroreflective material.</td>
              <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Signs and Lettering.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Signs and Lettering—Inspect for Lettering:</td>
              <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) "SCHOOL BUS" front and rear (8 inch by 1 inch stroke black lettering mounted as high as possible);</td>
              <td>(1) When required, are missing, illegible, or obscured.<br/>(2) Are not proper size or color.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) "EMERGENCY DOOR OR EXIT" inside and outside<br/>(2 inch by 3/8 inch stroke black lettering, mounted directly above the door or on the door above the glass);</td>
              <td>(3) Are not located as required or permitted.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Operation of Emergency Door or Exit Latch (6 inch black arrow by 3/4 inch stroke indicating direction to release door <br/>or exit, inside and outside;</td>
              <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(4) "STOP ON SIGNAL" when required (4 inch by 3/4 inch stroke black lettering below rear window);</td>
              <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(5) Side Emergency Windows (if equipped):<br/>   (a) "EMERGENCY EXIT" (2 inch by 3/8 inch stroke black lettering, mounted directly above the emergency exit on both <br/>the inside and outside surfaces of the bus);<br/>   (b) Operating instructions necessary to unlatch and open emergency exit shall be in letters of a color that contrasts <br/>with its background and located within 6 inches of the release mechanism on the inside surface of the vehicle (A decal containing the instructions may be placed on the window. <br/>For buses manufactured after July 31, 2009, the decal shall be transparent except for the lettering.);</td>
              <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(6) Rear Emergency Window (if equipped): <br/>   (a) "EMERGENCY EXIT" (at least 2 inch by 3/8 inch stroke black lettering, mounted above the window on the inside of the vehicle and above or below the window on the outside of the vehicle);<br/>   (b) Operating instructions necessary to unlatch and open emergency exit shall be in letters of a color that contrasts with its background and located within 6 inches of the release mechanism on the inside and outside surface of the vehicle (Decals containing the instructions may be placed on the window. For buses manufactured after July 31, 2009, the decal shall be transparent except for the lettering.);</td>
              <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(7) Roof Vent/Emergency Exit:<br/>   (a) "EMERGENCY EXIT" (in letters at least 2 inches high, of a color that contrasts with its background and located on an inside and outside surface of the exit, or within 12 inches of the roof exit opening);<br/>   (b) Operating instructions necessary to unlatch and open emergency exit shall be in letters of a color that contrasts with its background and located within 6 inches of the release mechanism on the inside and outside surface of the vehicle.</td>
              <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Retro-Reflective Tape.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Retro-Reflective Tape: Each opening for a required emergency exit on a school vehicle manufactured after May 2, 1994 shall <br/>be outlined around its outside perimeter with yellow retro-reflective tape having a minimum width of 1 inch.</td>
              <td>Retro-reflective tape:<br/>  (1) Is missing when required, or is loose, defective or obscured;<br/>  (2) Is not the proper size or color;<br/>  (3) Is not located as required.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Identification. Inspect for presence, size, and condition of required or permitted identification.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Required:<br/>   (a) Vehicles owned by local Boards of Education:</td>
              <td>Identification:<br/>(1) When required, is missing, illegible, or obscured;</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(i) Name of school system (both sides of vehicle 6-1/2 <br/>inches high by 1 inch stroke),<br/>     (ii) Identification number (all four sides 6 inches high by <br/>3/4 inch stroke visible directly from the front, rear, and each side);</td>
              <td proof="needed">
                <p>(2) Is not proper size;</p>
                <p>(3) Is not located where required or permitted;</p>
                <p>(4) Is not required or permitted.</p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(b) Vehicles contracted to local Boards of Education:<br/>     (i) Contractor's name (to rear of entrance door 3 inches high by 1/2 inch stroke in a 16 inch x 30 inch area),<br/>     (ii) Identification number (all four sides 6 inches high by <br/>3/4 inch stroke visible directly from the front, rear, and each side;</td>
              <td proof="needed"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(c) All other vehicles:<br/>       (i) Owner's name (to rear of entrance door 3 inches high by 1/2 inch stroke),<br/>       (ii) Identification number (all four sides 6 inches high by 3/4 inch stroke visible directly from the front, rear, and each side).</td>
              <td proof="needed"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Permitted:<br/>   (a) ICC number (to rear of entrance door 3 inches high by 1/2 inch stroke);<br/>   (b) Address of owner (to rear of entrance door 3 inches high by 1/2 inch stroke);<br/>   (c) Telephone number of owner (to rear of entrance door 3 inches high by 1/2 inch stroke).</td>
              <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Mirrors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Outside Mirrors. Every vehicle shall be equipped with an outside rearview mirror on the driver's side providing a view of the highway  for a distance of at least 200 feet to the rear. Every school vehicle shall be equipped with at least one convex mirror, not less than 7-1/2 inches in diameter, which shall be firmly mounted on the left front corner forward of the seated driver so that he may observe a reflection of the road from the front bumper to a point where direct observation is possible. One outside rearview mirror on each side of a school vehicle shall be mounted forward of the driver's seat and have an area not less than 50 square inches (minimum 5 inches wide by 10 inches high). Additionally on school vehicles manufactured after December 31, 1972, there shall be on each side of the vehicle a convex mirror of not less than 20 square inches of reflective surface. The convex mirrors may be incorporated in the plain rearview mirror provided the plain view reflective area is not reduced, or they may be mounted independently. Either type shall be independently adjustable.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Rearview Mirror or Mirrors: From the driver's position, visually inspect all exterior mirrors for a clear and reasonably unobstructed view to the rear. Look for correct location, stable mounting, cracks, sharp edges, unnecessary protrusions, ease <br/>of adjustment and ability to hold an adjustment.<br/>(2) Outside Crossview Mirror: (convex) (applicable to school vehicles only): From the driver's seat visually inspect the exterior crossview mirror for unobstructed view of area forward of seated driver which is not directly observable.</td>
              <td>(1) Mirror:<br/>   (a) Is missing (when required);<br/>   (b) Mounting is loose so that rear vision is impaired;<br/>   (c) Is obscured by windshield pillar or unwiped portion of the windshield;<br/>   (d) Is cracked, pitted, or clouded to the extent that rear vision is obscured;<br/>   (e) Does not provide an unobstructed view to the rear;<br/>   (f) Cannot be adjusted or will not hold an adjustment;<br/>   (g) Does not meet minimum size requirements (school vehicles only).</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Inside Mirrors. Every vehicle shall be equipped with an inside rearview mirror except as noted in §B(1) and (2). The inside rearview mirror shall be clear view glass and adjustable, and provide a clear stable reflected view 200 feet to the rear. School vehicles shall be equipped with a mirror 6 inches by 30 inches, metal backed, framed with rounded corners, and firmly mounted as far forward as possible, and provide a clear stable reflected view of the road surface to the rear of the vehicle for a continual distance beginning not more than 200 feet to the rear.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Interior Rearview Mirror:<br/>(1) From the driver's position, visually inspect interior mirror <br/>for proper mounting, location, cracks, sharp edges, ease of adjustment and ability to hold an adjustment.</td>
              <td>Mirror:<br/> (1) Is missing (when required);</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) If vehicle is originally designed or constructed so that the view through an inside rearview mirror is obstructed, or the vehicle is equipped with tinting, stickers, etc., on the window behind the driver, the inside rearview mirror is not required. However, the vehicle shall be equipped with outside rearview mirrors on both sides (not applicable to school vehicles).</td>
              <td>(2) Mounting is loose so that rear vision is impaired;<br/> (3) Is cracked, pitted, or clouded to the extent that rear vision <br/>is obscured;<br/> (4) Does not provide an unobstructed view to the rear;<br/> (5) Cannot be adjusted or will not hold an adjustment;<br/> (6) Does not meet minimum size requirements (school vehicles only).</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|14|04|.16">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Vehicle Glazing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Safety glazing material is marked with the manufacturer's distinctive designation or trademark, model number and the letters "AS" followed by a number from 1 through 16B, which indicates where the glazing may be used on the vehicle.  Safety glazing material also has  the symbol "DOT" (Department of Transportation) and a manufacturer's code mark that the NHTSA (National Highway Traffic Safety Administration) assigns to the manufacturer. Any questions regarding glazing shall be referred to the Automotive Safety Enforcement Division of the Department of State Police.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Proper Marking and Operation.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed">
                <p>(1) Proper Marking: Inspect glazing material for proper markings. The following is a brief list of "AS" markings<br/>and applications.</p>
                <p>Safety glazing material marked:  <br/>    (a) AS-1 is used in the windshield and may be used<br/>anywhere in a motor vehicle.</p>
                <p>(b) AS-2 may be used anywhere in a motor vehicle <br/>except for the windshield.</p>
                <p>(c) AS-3 may be used in windows to the rear of the <br/>driver in trucks, truck tractors, buses and multipurpose<br/>passenger vehicles. The vehicle must be equipped with <br/>an outside rearview mirror on each side.</p>
                <p>(d) AS-10 may be used where bullet resistance is required anywhere in a motor vehicle including the windshield.</p>
              </td>
              <td>(1) Improper or unmarked glazing materials are used for specific positions.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Window on Driver's Side: Inspect operation of window <br/>at driver's side. Window shall open and close readily even though the vehicle has approved turn signals.</td>
              <td>(2) Window on driver's side does not open and close as designed to permit arm signals.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed">
                <p>(3) Side Windows, Emergency Window Exits, and Roof Vent/Emergency Exits (school vehicles only):</p>
                <p>(a) Side Windows.<br/>       (i) Open and close each passenger compartment side window and inspect for proper operation. <br/>       (ii) Inspect passenger compartment side windows for unframed exposed edges of glass.</p>
                <p>(b) Side Emergency Windows (if equipped).<br/>       (i) Inspect inside release mechanism.<br/>       (ii) Check operation.<br/>       (iii) Check function of audible signal.</p>
              </td>
              <td>(3) Side Windows, Emergency Window Exits, and Roof Vent/Emergency Exits (school vehicles only):<br/>   (a) Side Windows.<br/>      (i) Any side window fails to function as designed.<br/>      (ii) Any exposed edges of glass are not framed or framing is loose or broken.<br/>   (b) Side Emergency Windows (if equipped).<br/>      (i) Window release mechanism is loose or broken.<br/>      (ii) Window will not operate properly.<br/>      (iii) Audible signal fails to function in driver's compartment and indicate to the seated driver when the engine is running a distinctive audible signal when release mechanism is moved, or sounds continuously when release mechanism is latched.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed">
                <p>(c) Rear Emergency Window (if equipped).<br/>       (i) Inspect inside and outside release mechanism.<br/>       (ii) Check operation.<br/>       (iii) Check function of audible signal.</p>
                <p>(d) Roof Vent/Emergency Exit.<br/>       (i) Inspect release mechanism.<br/>       (ii) Check operation.<br/>       (iii) If equipped, check function of audible signal.</p>
              </td>
              <td>(c) Rear Emergency Window (if equipped).<br/>      (i) Window release mechanism is loose or broken.<br/>      (ii) Window will not operate property.<br/>      (iii) Audible signal fails to function in driver's compartment and indicate to the seated driver when the engine is running a distinctive audible signal when release mechanism is moved, or sounds continuously when release mechanism is latched. <br/>   (d) Roof Vent/Emergency Exit.<br/>      (i) Release mechanism is loose or broken.<br/>      (ii) Fails to operate properly.<br/>      (iii) Audible signal, if equipped, fails to function in driver's compartment and indicate to the seated driver when the engine is running a distinctive audible signal when release mechanism is moved, or sounds continuously when release mechanism is latched.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Signs and Materials on Windshield or Windows.  Inspect all glazing for unauthorized material or conditions that obscure the driver's vision.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed">
                <p>(1) Except as provided in <cite path="11|14|04|.16|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite>, a vehicle <br/>may not be equipped with any sign, poster, card, sticker, or <br/>other nontransparent material on the windshield, side wings, <br/>or side or rear windows of the vehicle.</p>
                <p>(2) This does not apply to:<br/>    (a) Materials placed on the windshield or rear window, <br/>within a 7 inch square area in the lower corner, or on the side windows of the vehicle to the rear of the driver, if the <br/>materials are placed so as not to interfere with the driver's clear view of traffic;<br/>    (b) Direction, destination, or termini signs on any passenger common carrier motor vehicle;<br/>    (c) An electronic toll collection device placed in the windshield of a vehicle in accordance with guidelines established by the Maryland Transportation Authority; or <br/>    (d) Security stickers authorized by a federal or State government agency that measure not more than 2 inches high and not more than 4 inches long, and are placed at the upper edge of the center of the windshield.</p>
                <p>(3) All vehicles equipped with permitted signs, posters, cards, stickers or other nontransparent materials on windows to the <br/>rear of the driver must be equipped with an outside rearview mirror on each side.</p>
              </td>
              <td>(1) (a) Glazed surfaces contain any sign, poster, card, decal, sticker, or other nontransparent material in violation of this regulation.<br/>     (b) Driver's vision is obscured.<br/>     (c) Equipped with permitted signs, posters, cards, stickers, or other nontransparent materials on windows to the rear of the driver and not equipped with an outside rearview mirror on each side.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Post Manufacture Window Tinting.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect all glazing for the application of post manufacture window tint. The following post manufacture window tint is prohibited on any window or windshield of any vehicle. Window tint that:<br/>   (a) Has a mirrored or one-way vision effect or a sparkling effect; <br/>   (b) Is red, yellow, or amber in color; or <br/>   (c) Changes to a red, yellow, or amber color.</td>
              <td>(1) Any glazing contains post manufacture window tint that causes a mirrored or one-way vision effect, a sparkling effect, is a prohibited color, or changes to a prohibited color.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Post manufacture window tint is prohibited on the following vehicles in the listed locations:<br/>   (a) The application of post manufacture window tint to the windshield or windows to the immediate right and left of the driver is prohibited on the following vehicles:<br/>     (i) Trucks, truck tractors and buses;<br/>     (ii) Multipurpose passenger vehicles which have a seating capacity for 16 or more passengers including the driver, or <br/>were previously registered as a school vehicle or a passenger bus, and used to primarily transport passengers, or used in the furtherance of a commercial enterprise; and <br/>     (iii) Limousines. <br/>   (b) Windows of these vehicles to the rear of the driver may be tinted with post manufacture window tint to any degree of darkness provided the vehicle is equipped with an outside rearview mirror on each side.</td>
              <td>(2) (a) Post manufacture window tint is applied to glazing in violation of this regulation.<br/>      (b) Equipped with permitted post manufacture window tint on any side or rear window and is not equipped with an outside rearview mirror on each side.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Post manufacture window tint is prohibited on all windows and windshield of a school vehicle.</td>
              <td>(3) Post manufacture window tint is applied to glazing in violation of this regulation.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(4) Post manufacture window tint is acceptable on the following vehicles in the listed locations:<br/>   (a) All other multipurpose passenger vehicles.<br/>     (i) All side windows of these vehicles to the immediate <br/>right and left of the driver are regulated windows requiring at least 35 percent light transmittance after the application of post manufacture window tint.<br/>     (ii) Windshield. Post manufacture window tint may not be applied to the windshield below the AS1 line or below 5 inches from the top of the windshield, whichever is less.<br/>     (iii) Windows of these vehicles to the rear of the driver may be tinted with post manufacture window tint to any degree of darkness.<br/>     (iv) When equipped with permitted post manufacture window tint on any side or rear window, the vehicle must be equipped with an outside rearview mirror on each side.<br/>   (b) Inspect the light transmittance of each vehicle window equipped with post manufacture window tint and required to have at least 35 percent light transmittance after the application of post manufacture window tint.</td>
              <td>(4) (a) Post manufacture window tint is applied to glazing in violation of this regulation.<br/>      (b) Equipped with permitted post manufacture window tint on any side or rear window and is not equipped with an outside rearview mirror on each side.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(5) Tint Manufacturer's Labels (if equipped): Tint manufacturer's labels may not be of a size or positioned in a manner that affects the driver's vision or obscures the glazing manufacturer's trademark or AS indicator.</td>
              <td>(5) Tint manufacturer label, if equipped, is of a size or positioned in a manner that affects the driver's vision or obscures the glazing manufacturer's trademark or AS indicator.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(6) Medical Exemption. (Applicable only to multipurpose passenger vehicles noted in <cite path="11|14|04|.16|D.|(4)">§D(4) of this regulation</cite>.) <br/><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|22-406">Transportation Article, §22-406, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, provides an exemption for a person who must be protected from the sun for medical reasons from having a light transmittance of at least 35 percent on regulated windows equipped with post manufacture window tint. The law requires the owner to have, in the vehicle at the time the vehicle is stopped by a police officer, a written certification that details the owner's medical need for tinted windows, from a physician licensed to practice medicine in the State. A vehicle owner whose vehicle is undergoing an inspection, or has been issued a safety equipment repair order for defect #61 "TINT", and indicates to the authorized inspection station their compliance with a medical exemption, shall be referred to the Automotive Safety Enforcement Division of the Department of State Police for examination of the vehicle owner's medical documentation and the vehicle's post manufacture window tint. If the owner meets the requirements specified in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|22-406">Transportation Article, §22-406, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, for the medical exemption and the vehicle is compliant with all post manufacture window tinting regulations in this chapter, excluding the light transmittance requirement of regulated windows equipped with post manufacture window tint, the Division, when applicable, shall be authorized to:<br/>   (a) Issue a post manufacture window tint medical exemption form to be provided to the authorized inspection station performing an inspection of the vehicle which shall permit the registered inspection mechanic to exempt the vehicle's windows equipped with post manufacture window tint from meeting the light transmittance requirement; or<br/>   (b) Certify the safety equipment repair order for defect #61 "TINT".</td>
              <td proof="needed"/>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Acute area" means the windshield area 8 inches wide by 5 inches high, located directly in front of the driver, centered vertically on the steering wheel of the vehicle and horizontally in the center of the critical area.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Cloudiness" means any degree of visible discoloration or separation, except tinting that does not affect clear vision.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Critical area" means the normal windshield wiper sweep, except the area obscured by the hood, fenders, or rearview mirror.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Discoloration" means a condition which impairs the transparency of the glazing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Non-critical area" means all windshield area outside the critical area.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Normal windshield wiper sweep" means the area of the windshield cleaned by the windshield wiper, excluding the return position on both passenger's and driver's sides.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Glazing Damage.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect all windows for modification, damage, sharp edges, and discoloration of the glazing.</td>
              <td>(1) (a) Any window is missing, modified, broken or has exposed sharp edges. <br/>   (b) There are cracks, discoloration, scratches, or conditions which interfere with the driver's view to the right or left.  <br/>   (c) The rear window is discolored so that the driver does not have a clear view 200 feet to the rear of the vehicle. <br/>   (d) The driver's view to the rear is obscured or obstructed and the vehicle is not equipped with an outside rearview mirror on each side.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Windshield: Inspect windshield for modification and<br/> any cracks, nicks, pits, chips, star breaks, half moons or <br/>bull's-eye fractures, discoloration, sharp edges, and wiper <br/>blade scratches.</td>
              <td proof="needed">
                <p>(2) Windshield:<br/>   (a) Is missing or has been modified.<br/>   (b) Driver's Side:<br/>     (i) Cloudiness exceeds 1 inch from the top or side or 1 inch into the critical area from the bottom. If the windshield is divided, the cloudiness may not exceed 1/2 inch from the center divider.<br/>     (ii) Acute area contains any one crack, nick, pit, chip, star break, half moon or bull's-eye fracture in excess of 1/4 inch in diameter or length, or any combination of individual cracks, nicks, pits, chips, star breaks, half moons or bull's-eye fractures which cumulatively exceed 1/4 inch in diameter or length, or any permanent condition which significantly interferes with the driver's vision.<br/>     (iii) Critical area contains wiper blade scratches which are severe enough to distort vision, or any one crack, nick, pit, chip, star break, half moon or bull's-eye fracture in excess of 1/2 inch in diameter or length, or any combination of individual cracks, nicks, pits, chips, star breaks, half moons or bull's-eye fractures which cumulatively exceed 1/2 inch in diameter or length, or any permanent condition which significantly interferes with the driver's vision except in the permitted cloudy area.<br/>     (iv) Non-critical area contains any intersecting cracks or any one crack or combination of individual cracks extending inward more than 2 inches separately or cumulatively from the outer frame on flat or curved windshields or over 4 inches on wraparound windshields, or any one crack, nick, pit, chip, star break, half moon or bull's-eye fracture in excess of 3/4 inch in diameter or length, or any combination of individual cracks, nicks, pits, chips, star breaks, half moons or bull's-eye fractures which cumulatively exceed 3/4 inch in diameter or length, or any permanent condition which significantly interferes with the driver's vision except in the permitted cloudy area. <br/>   (c) Passenger Side: <br/>     (i) Cloudiness exceeds 2 inches from the top or side or extends more than 2 inches into the critical area from the bottom. If the windshield is divided, the cloudiness may not exceed 1/2 inch from the center divider.</p>
                <p>(ii) Critical area contains wiper blade scratches which are severe enough to distort vision, or any one crack, nick, pit, chip, star break, half moon or bull's-eye fracture in excess of 1/2 inch in diameter or length, or any combination of individual cracks, nicks, pits, chips, star breaks, half moons or bull's-eye fractures which cumulatively exceed 1/2 inch in diameter or length, or any permanent condition which significantly interferes with the driver's vision except in the permitted cloudy area. <br/>     (iii) Non-critical area contains any intersecting cracks or any one crack or combination of individual cracks extending inward more than 4 inches separately or cumulatively from the outer frame on flat or curved windshields or over 6 inches on wraparound windshields, or any one crack, nick, pit, chip, star break, half moon or bull's-eye fracture in excess of 1-1/2 inches in diameter or length, or any combination of individual cracks, nicks, pits, chips, star breaks, half moons or bull's-eye fractures which cumulatively exceed 1-1/2 inches in diameter or length, or any permanent condition which significantly interferes with the driver's vision except in the permitted cloudy area.</p>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <text>Figure 32—VEHICLE GLAZING.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Windshield Wipers and Washers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The windshield wipers shall be inspected for operation, control, condition of blades and arms, or any missing part.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed">
                <p>(1) Windshield Wipers:<br/>   (a) Inspect for satisfactory operation (if vacuum operated, engine shall be idling and control full on). Windshield shall be free of insects, oil film, or other foreign matter, and should be continuously wet when tested. Wetting the windshield during school vehicle inspection may be waived if water is unavailable or the outside temperature is freezing or below.</p>
                <p>(b) Inspect for damaged, torn, or hardened rubber elements of blades. <br/>   (c) Inspect for damaged metal parts of wiper blades or arms. <br/>   (d) Inspect for proper contact of blades with windshield. Raise arm away from windshield and release. Arm should return to original position and cause the wiper blades to firmly contact the windshield.</p>
              </td>
              <td>(1)<br/>   (a) Wipers are inoperative or cannot be controlled or operated by the driver.<br/>   (b) A wiper blade is broken or missing.<br/>   (c) There is insufficient tension of arm to hold blade against windshield.<br/>  (d) There are worn or deteriorated blades that do not clean the windshield (within 5 cycles applicable to school vehicles only).<br/>  (e) Wiper arms and blades are not the original size.<br/>  (f) Not equipped with on/off switch within arm's length of driver.<br/>  (g) Arm or arms fail to return to park position.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Windshield Washers (school vehicles only). Inspect for proper operation of hand or foot control and an effective amount of fluid delivered to the outside of the windshield. System shall function when temperature is both above and below freezing point of water.</td>
              <td>(2)<br/>  (a) Reservoir is empty.<br/>  (b) System fails to function.<br/>  (c) Fluid in system is frozen.<br/>  (d) System does not provide fluid to the wiper area.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Hood and Catches.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Inspection shall consist of operation and presence of catches and safety catches, insuring that the hood covers at least the top part of the engine compartment; and if equipped with an air scoop or bubble, it does not extend higher than 1/3 the vertical height of the windshield.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Open hood and inspect safety catch for proper operation. Close hood and inspect for proper full closure. Manually inspect latch or remote control for proper operation (if engine is rear mounted, make a similar inspection of engine compartment and hood door). Stud and safety pin-type latch are acceptable provided pressure is necessary to remove the pin from the stud. If tilt cab vehicle, inspect locking and safety mechanism of the cab.</td>
              <td>(1) Hood does not cover at least the top of the engine compartment (full hood is required on school vehicles).<br/>(2) Air scoop or bubble is higher than 1/3 the vertical height of the windshield.<br/>(3) Hood latch and keeper not original equipment or equivalent.<br/>(4) Hood is not equipped with a proper operating safety latch.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Inspect for height of air scoop or bubble. <br/>(3) On vehicles where the engine extends inside the vehicle, the interior engine cover shall be inspected for proper sealing.</td>
              <td>(5) Latch and release mechanism of hood, engine cover, or tilt cab is broken, missing, or improperly adjusted, preventing the hood from being opened or closed, the engine cover from being removed or replaced or the tilt cab from being raised or lowered.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td proof="needed"/>
              <td>(6) Interior engine cover is not properly sealed to prevent the entrance of engine fumes or exhaust gages into the vehicle.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <text>Figure 33—HOOD SCOOP HEIGHT.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Doors, Handles, and Latches.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Inspection of doors, handles, latches, and hinges applies to all vehicles originally manufactured with doors and all other vehicles which are equipped doors.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect all doors, latches, hinges, and handles for broken or missing parts, proper operation, and improper adjustment <br/>(open and close doors). Electric push button or ring and cable means of opening the door are acceptable provided they are readily accessible.</td>
              <td>(1) Doors or door parts are missing, broken, or sagging so that the door cannot be tightly closed.<br/>(2) Latch or handle not original equipment or equivalent.<br/>(3) Door handle and latch do not provide a means of readily opening door.<br/>(4) Secondary or safety catch does not function properly.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Doors—Service, Emergency (applicable to school vehicles only). Service doors may be split-type, sedan-type, or jackknife-type with vertical closing edges covered with flexible material.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Service Door:<br/>   (a) From driver's position, inspect function of opening and closing operation; <br/>   (b) If door is equipped with a lock, determine if engine will start with door locked; check operation of audiovisual alarm with door locked;<br/>   (c) Inspect condition of flexible material on vertical closing edges (when applicable).</td>
              <td>(1) Service Door:<br/>   (a) Power or manual opening and closing device shows evidence of binding, jamming, excessive wear, or malfunction;<br/>   (b) Door is equipped with a lock and engine starts with door locked or audiovisual alarm fails to function with door locked and ignition switch on;<br/>   (c) Flexible material is loose, torn, or missing (when applicable).</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Emergency Door:<br/>   (a) Inspect for clear passageway to door;<br/>   (b) Inspect inside and outside quick release mechanism; <br/>   (c) Check length of stroke on slide bar or cam operated lock;<br/>   (d) Check function of buzzer indicating door is not fully closed; <br/>   (e) Inspect emergency red identification light (if equipped);<br/>   (f) Inspect emergency door gaskets.</td>
              <td>(2) Emergency Door:<br/>   (a) Passageway to emergency door is blocked or restricted in any manner to less than 12 inches wide;<br/>   (b) Door release mechanism fails to release when activated from inside and outside of the bus or if it opens without activating a release;<br/>   (c) Latch will not hold the door tightly closed;<br/>   (d) Slide bar has less than 1 inch stroke length;<br/>   (e) Buzzer fails to function in driver's compartment and indicate to the seated driver when the engine is running a distinctive audible signal when slide bar is moved;<br/>   (f) Red identification light fails to function when the headlamps or parking lamps are activated;<br/>   (g) Gaskets are torn, loose, or missing.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.20</num>
    <heading>Floor and Trunk Pans.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Floor and trunk pans shall be inspected for holes or rusted and weakened conditions.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect floor pan in occupant compartment (cab) or in <br/>cargo areas open to the occupant compartment for rusted out areas or holes which could permit entry of exhaust gases, <br/>which could not support occupants, or which affect secure mounting of seats.</td>
              <td>(1) Floor pan (or floor) is cracked, has holes or is rusted through or weakened to cause a hazard to an occupant, permits exhaust gases or engine fumes to enter an occupant compartment, or affects secure mounting of seats.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Inspect trunk pans for rusted out areas, holes, or openings which would permit entry of exhaust gases.</td>
              <td>(2) Trunk pans are rusted out, contain holes or openings.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Inspect floor covering for presence, adhesion, hazardous conditions, and sealing (applicable to school vehicles only).</td>
              <td>(3) Floor covering of school vehicle is missing, cracked, curled, or worn; not properly sealed or attached; or presents a tripping hazard.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(4) Inspect engine cover on COE and COF vehicles for rusted-out areas or holes which could permit entry of exhaust gases <br/>into the cab.</td>
              <td>(4) Engine cover is not properly sealed or has rusted-out areas or holes which could permit entry of exhaust gases into the cab.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.21</num>
    <heading>Speedometer and Odometer.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Speedometer, odometer, or hubometer will be inspected to determine if they are connected and operable, the dial and calibrations are legible, and calibrated in miles or kilometers.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Visually inspect speedometer and odometer for operation and legibility. Speedometer must register speed and odometer must register distance traveled. The speedometer may register speed in miles per hour or kilometers per hour or both and odometer may register distance traveled in miles or kilometers. If the odometer records a distance in kilometers, the vehicle shall be placarded in view of the driver with a wording "kilometers divided by 1.609 equals miles".</td>
              <td>(1) Speedometer or odometer, or both, are disconnected or inoperable.<br/>(2) Dial and calibrations not legible.<br/>(3) Speedometer does not register speed in miles per hour or kilometers or both.<br/>(4) Odometer does not register distance traveled.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.22</num>
    <heading>Preventive Maintenance — Applicable to School Vehicles Only.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The vehicle owner shall establish a preventive maintenance program recording inspection, repairs, and maintenance by vehicle number, and include at least annually a complete preventive maintenance inspection, to assure that each vehicle is in compliance with all sections of this handbook pertaining to school vehicles. When the wheels have been removed for inspection or maintenance, and after the wheels have been replaced, the vehicle shall be test-driven to assure there is no brake imbalance before the vehicle is released for pupil transportation. Before September of each year, the Administration shall determine that the annual preventive maintenance inspection on each vehicle has been performed within the previous 12 months, repaired or replaced systems or parts are operating properly, and the condition of the vehicle is in accordance with the established standards. The Administration may require a wheel or wheels to be pulled by the vehicle owners or mechanic, to verify condition and repair of brake and other systems. In the event of a change of vehicle ownership and before the vehicle is authorized to transport school children, the Administration may require a preventive maintenance inspection and accomplishment of any maintenance found necessary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Preventive Maintenance Inspection.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect program for technical adequacy and for compliance with accepted standards.</td>
              <td>(1) Preventive maintenance inspection has not been performed as required.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Inspect vehicle records for compliance with minimum requirements of established standards. Each entry should be checked against the actual condition of the item.</td>
              <td>(2) Records are unavailable or do not substantiate inspections, repairs, or maintenance performed as required.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Verify the vehicle preventive maintenance inspection certification.</td>
              <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(4) A preventive maintenance inspection shall include compliance with all items listed in the handbook.</td>
              <td proof="needed"/>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Regular Inspection. Regular inspections shall be performed twice annually as required.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Regular inspections shall include the items in the preventive maintenance inspection except pulling wheels and checking brake linings, pads, and drums.</td>
              <td>(1) Regular inspection has not been performed as required.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.23</num>
    <heading>Load Covers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not apply to a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Class K (farm area) vehicle as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-935">Transportation Article, §13-935, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Construction vehicle working within the confines of a public works construction work project site as outlined in the construction project's plans and specifications, provided the distance travelled does not exceed 1 mile or the distance specified in an extension granted by the Maryland Department of Transportation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Construction vehicle or mining equipment while crossing a highway between construction or mining sites; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Vehicle, within the Port of Baltimore for a distance not to exceed 1 mile, carrying a load of loose material between a stockpile or storage facility and a vessel docked at the Port.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This regulation applies to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Any vehicle, not otherwise exempted, manufactured on or before July 1, 1990 and carrying loose material if any part of the loose material is within 6 inches of the top of any bed enclosure it touches;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any vehicle, not otherwise exempted, manufactured after July 1, 1990 regardless of the loading of loose material;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>After January 1, 1992, any vehicle not otherwise exempted and regardless of loading of loose material.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The requirements of this regulation apply only to the issuance and certification of a safety equipment repair order and do not apply to a complete inspection required upon sale or transfer of ownership of a used vehicle. A safety equipment repair order may be certified only if the cover is present, fully covers the top of the bed, and meets the requirements of this regulation.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect cover for presence and size.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Cover is not present or does not fully cover the top of the vehicle bed.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Inspect cover for holes, rips, tears, or broken mesh.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Cover contains holes, rips, tears, or broken mesh which would permit any part of the load to blow, fall, or spill from the bed.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(3) Inspect cover for proper mounting.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(3) Cover is not securely attached to the bed.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(4) Inspect securement hardware for presence and condition.</td>
              <td>(4) Securement hardware is missing, broken, or damaged.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|23-101">23-101</cite>-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|23-105">23-105</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|24-106">24-106</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-10-03">Chapter revised effective October 3, 1980 (7:20 Md. R. 1880)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-10-31">Chapter revised effective October 31, 1988 (15:22 Md. R. 2557)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-10-09">Regulation .02 amended effective October 9, 1995 (22:20 Md. R. 1544)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-01">Regulation .05 amended effective April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 686)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-01">Regulation .06 amended effective April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 686)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-01">Regulation .10 amended effective April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 686)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2012-02-01">Regulation .14 amended effective February 1, 2012 (39:1 Md. R. 18)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2012-02-01">Regulation .16 amended effective April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 686); August 21, 2000 (27:16 Md. R. 1526); February 1, 2012 (39:1 Md. R. 18)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2012-02-01">Regulation .19 amended effective February 1, 2012 (39:1 Md. R. 18)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-01">Regulation .23 adopted effective April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 686)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
