<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Safety Standards for Trailers</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <text>The standards, requirements, and procedures set forth in this chapter are applicable to equipment originally installed by the manufacturer or required by federal or State requirement on trailers (including pole trailers, semitrailers, camping trailers, trailers so designed or manufactured for the purpose of moving modular homes, travel trailers) and any questions regarding these standards or specifications shall be referred to the Automotive Safety Enforcement Division of the Maryland State Police. Any person constructing or reconstructing a vehicle shall assure the vehicle meets or exceeds all applicable federal and State safety standards.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Hitches or Coupling Devices.</heading>
    <text>Inspect hitches, coupling devices, tongues, or drawbars on trailers and semitrailers for proper alignment, distortion, deformation, cracks, or missing parts. On vehicles equipped with a ball-type hitch, pintle hood, or drawbar means of attachment, inspect for presence, attachment, and size of safety chains or cables.</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
              <em>Procedures:</em>
            </td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
              <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>A. Inspect hitches, couplers, tongues, or drawbars on<br/> trailers and semitrailers for:</td>
            <td>A.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>(1) Proper alignment, distortion, deformation, cracks, or missing parts;</td>
            <td>(1) Hitch, coupler, tongue, or drawbar is improperly aligned, distorted, deformed, has any cracks or missing parts.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>(2) Presence and strength of safety chains or cables on vehicles equipped for a ball and hitch, pintle hook, or <br/>drawbar means of attachment.</td>
            <td>(2) Safety chains or cables on vehicles equipped for a ball and hitch, pintle hook, or drawbar means of attachment are severely worn, missing, broken, or not of sufficient strength to support the vehicle in the event the primary attachment device becomes uncoupled.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>B. On trailers or semitrailers to be coupled to a towing vehicle with a fifth wheel, inspect king pin for excessive wear.</td>
            <td>(3) Wear on king pin exceeds manufacturer's allowable tolerance.</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Suspension and Alignment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Suspension. Inspect the suspension system for missing, broken, damaged, worn, rusted, or modified wheel bearings, springs, or frame that would affect vehicle stability.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Wheel Bearings. Wheel bearings out of adjustment can cause wander, unequal brake action, and noise due to interference of parts.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Wheel Bearings: With the vehicle lifted, grasp the tire top <br/>and bottom and rock it in and out. To verity that any <br/>looseness detected is in the wheel bearing, notice the movement between the brake drum or disc and the backing plate or splash shield.</td>
                <td>Wheel bearings are loose, rough, galled, or otherwise defective.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Springs.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>With vehicle on a level surface, visually inspect the heights<br/>of the four corners of the vehicle. If necessary, use a measuring device and determine differences from side to side. Visually inspect for broken or damaged spring leaves. Inspect spring shackles, bushings, and U-bolts.</td>
                <td proof="needed">
                  <p>(a) Any spring, main, or torque leaf is broken.</p>
                  <p>(b) Any spring with more than four leaves has two or more broken leaves.</p>
                  <p>(c) Any spring with four or less leaves has a broken leaf.</p>
                  <p>(d) Any spring center bolt is broken.</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(e) Shackles or U-bolts are missing, broken, worn, loose, or extended.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(f) U-bolts are not of sufficient length to protrude at least 1/4 inch beyond nut when tightened.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(g) Any object or equipment extends below the bottom edge of wheel rim.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(h) Frame is rusted, broken, or damaged, or axle mounting points are rusted, broken, or damaged to affect suspension or axle mounting; or the frame has been repaired and not fishplated; or the body is not attached securely to the frame.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Air Suspension. Some trailers and semitrailers may be equipped with air suspension systems. Inspection of the system consists of checking for air leaks, proper height, and ride level. CAUTION: The inspector should not use a creeper under the vehicle unless the vehicle is properly jacked and supported.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) With entire system drained of air, and while observing the brake air pressure gauge of the towing vehicle, determine pressure at which air begins to lift the vehicle. Pressure regulator valve should not allow air into the suspension<br/>system until at least 55 psi is in the braking system.</td>
                <td>(a) Air begins to lift the vehicle before 55 psi is indicated on the pressure gauge.   (b) Air leakage rate is greater than 3 psi in 5 minutes.<br/>   (c) Vehicle is resting on one or both axles or the vehicle is not level (is listing to right or left).</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) With air system at normal operating pressure, inspect hoses, connection, and bellows for leaks and excessive deterioration (apply service brakes fully).</td>
                <td proof="needed"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(c) With air at normal operating pressure, observe height<br/>and level of vehicle relative to ground surface (this will indicate function of pressure regulator and height control valves).</td>
                <td proof="needed"/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Shock Absorbers (if equipped).</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Procedures:</em>
                </td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) With vehicle on level surface, push down on each<br/>corner of the vehicle and release (if possible).</td>
                <td>(a) Vehicle continues free rocking motion for two cycles after release, or shock absorbers are worn, damaged, or leaking to the extent vehicle stability is affected.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) With vehicle jacked, visually inspect for missing,<br/>broken, loose, or damaged shock absorbers, mounting brackets, bolts and bushings, and excessive leakage.</td>
                <td proof="needed">
                  <p>(b) Shock absorbers, mounting bolts, or mounts are missing, broken, or loose.</p>
                  <p>(c) Severe leakage (not slight dampness) is present.</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td proof="needed"/>
                <td>(d) Any bushing is missing any portion of the bushing or is damaged, deteriorated, or dry rotted to a point that the bushing is broken or loose.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Alignment. Inspect axles for broken, damaged, worn, rusted, bent, or modified axle beams, spindles, or mountings that affect wheel alignment, tracking, toe-in, caster, or camber enough to affect vehicle stability.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Visually inspect axles for broken, damaged, worn, rusted, <br/>bent, or modified beams, spindles, or mountings.</td>
              <td>Any axle beam, spindle, or mounting is broken, damaged, rusted, bent, or modified to the extent that wheel alignment, tracking, toe-in, caster, or camber is severe enough to affect vehicle stability.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Brakes.</heading>
    <text>Trailers and semitrailers to be registered up to 3,000 pounds GVWR are not required to be equipped with brakes.  However, if such a trailer or semitrailer is equipped with brakes, all brakes shall meet minimum standards. Trailers and semitrailers to be registered from 3,001 pounds GVWR to 10,000 pounds GVWR shall be equipped with brakes on all wheels of at least one axle. Trailers and semitrailers to be registered over 10,000 pounds GVWR shall have brakes on all wheels. At least one wheel and drum shall be removed from each axle equipped with drum brakes. On disc brakes only wheel assembly removal is necessary. On trailers and semitrailers with brakes on more than one axle, wheel assembly removal shall be on alternate sides. Always inspect a brake assembly which shows evidence of leaking fluid or grease.</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Drums and Discs.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Brake Drums:<br/>   (a) Inspect the condition of the drum friction surface <br/>for any crack extending to the open edge of the drum<br/>(short hairline heat cracks should not be considered).<br/>   (b) Inspect for any crack on the outside of the drum.<br/>   (c) Inspect for mechanical damage.<br/>   (d) Inspect for contaminated friction surface.<br/>   (e) Measure inside diameter of drum.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1)    (a) There is a crack on the friction surface extending to the open edge of the drum.<br/>   (b) There is any external crack.<br/>   (c) There is evidence of excessive mechanical damage other than wear.<br/>   (d) The friction surface is contaminated with oil, grease, or brake fluid.<br/>   (e) The inside drum diameter is greater than the manufacturer's recommended limit or the diameter stamped on the drum, or if the drum is not stamped, the manufacturer's maximum allowable remachining specification. If the drum is not stamped and no manufacturer's specification exists and the original diameter of the drum can be determined, the inside diameter may be no more than 0.090 inch greater than the original diameter.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Brake Discs (if equipped):<br/>   (a) Inspect for any crack extending to the edge of the disc. <br/>   (b) Inspect for mechanical damage.<br/>   (c) Inspect for contaminated friction surface.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2)<br/>   (a) There is any crack extending to the edge of the disc.<br/>   (b) If a crack extends into a weld or more than one-half the outside diameter of a BF Goodrich steel disc.<br/>   (c) There is evidence of excessive mechanical damage other than wear.<br/>   (d) The friction surface is contaminated with oil, grease, or brake fluid.<br/>   (e) The thickness of the disc is less than the manufacturer's recommended limit or the thickness stamped on the disc.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Brake Linings or Pads.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Condition of Linings and Pads: <br/>   (a) Bonded linings: Measure the lining thickness at the <br/>thinnest point.<br/>  (b) Riveted linings:<br/>     (i) Inspect for loose or missing rivets;<br/>     (ii) Measure lining thickness above rivet head at thinnest point.<br/>  (c) Wire backed linings: Inspect for wire showing in the friction surface. <br/>  (d) Bolted linings:<br/>     (i) Inspect for loose or missing bolts;<br/>     (ii) Measure lining thickness at center of shoe.<br/>  (e) All linings: Inspect for broken or cracked linings and<br/> parts of linings not firmly attached to shoe. Also inspect for contamination and excessively uneven lining wear.<br/>  (f) Pads (disc brakes): Inspect thickness of friction pads.</td>
              <td>(1)<br/>  (a) Thinnest point of remaining bonded lining is less than 2/32 inch.<br/>  (b) Riveted linings:<br/>     (i) Any rivet is loose or missing:<br/>     (ii) Remaining lining is less than 2/32 inch above any rivet head.<br/>  (c) Wire backing is visible in the friction surface.<br/>  (d) Bolted linings:<br/>     (i) Any fastening parts are loose or missing;<br/>     (ii) Remaining lining is less than 5/16 inch at center of shoe.<br/>  (e) <br/>    (i) Lining is broken, cracked, or not firmly and completely attached to shoe. <br/>     (ii) Friction surface is contaminated with oil, grease, or brake fluid.<br/>     (iii) Lining wear is extremely uneven.<br/>  (f)<br/>     (i) Any pad is less than 2/32 inch.<br/>     (ii) Any pad on BF Goodrich Air Actuated Disc Brakes has 1/8 inch or less lining remaining.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Mechanical Linkage.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Condition of mechanical components:<br/>  (a) Inspect for worn pins and missing or defective cotter pins. <br/>  (b) Inspect for broken, missing, or worn springs, cables, clevises, couplings, rods, and anchor pins.<br/>  (c) Inspect for frozen, rusted, or inoperative connections, missing, spring clips, and defective grease retainers. <br/>  (d) Inspect for restriction of shoe movement at backing <br/>plate and for binding between brake shoes and anchor pins.</td>
              <td>(1)<br/>  (a) Mechanical parts are missing, broken, or badly worn.<br/>  (b) Grease retainers are leaking (dampness is not cause for rejection).<br/>  (c) Conversion of a self-adjusting mechanism that is not completely converted.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Hydraulic System.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Visually inspect condition of hydraulic system:<br/>   (a) Inspect wheel cylinders for leakage and operation. <br/>Do not remove dust covers. Leakage can be determined<br/>by pushing on the outside of the boot.<br/>   (b) Inspect hydraulic hoses and brake lines for leaks, cracks, chafing, flattened or restricted sections, and improper support. <br/>   (c) Inspect master cylinder for leakage and fluid level <br/>(be sure no dirt gets into reservoir when cover is removed <br/>and that gasket is serviceable).</td>
              <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <p>(1)<br/>   (a) Any wheel cylinder leaks.<br/>   (b) Any wheel cylinder fails to operate.<br/>   (c) Brake hoses or brake lines are cracked, chafed, flattened, restricted; are rusted and pitting is visible; are not securely fastened or lines have not been repaired or replaced with copper tubing or other material not specifically designed for use as hydraulic brake lines. Hoses or brake lines are mounted to contact wheels or body during suspension movement.<br/>   (d) Master cylinder leaks.</p>
                <p>(e) Master cylinder fluid level is less than 1/2 full in any section.<br/>   (f) Master cylinder gasket does not properly seal.</p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) If the vehicle is equipped with hydraulic surge brakes, <br/>test for functions of brakes by causing brakes to be applied.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2)<br/>   (a) Brakes fail to function.<br/>   (b) Brakes do not remain applied until released.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Air Brake Leakage. Before conducting these inspections, it may be desirable to install in the system an air gauge (0-150 psi) which has 5 or 10 psi increments, so that small changes in pressure can be more easily observed. Also, to eliminate the possibility of leakage being in the system of the towing vehicle, conduct air leakage tests on the uncoupled towing vehicle before inspecting the system of the trailer or semitrailer.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Air leakage in system: Connect trailer or semitrailer air <br/>brake system to towing vehicle or independent air supply and inspect for air leakage in two ways: <br/>   (a) With a fully charged system or independent air supply and record the pressure drop in psi per minute with brakes fully applied;<br/>   (b) With a fully charged system or independent air supply and record pressure drop in psi per minute with brakes released.</td>
              <td>(1) Leakage exceeds the following limits:<br/>   (a) Brakes fully applied—4 psi per minute<br/>   (b) Brakes released—3 psi per minute.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) General condition: <br/>   (a) Inspect all air hoses, tubes and connections. Check attachment of all connecting lines and look for proper supporting parts. Be sure lines are free from contact with frame, axles, wheels, or other lines.<br/>   (b) Inspect for leaks that may be heard from valves, diaphragms, piston cups, and connections.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2)<br/>   (a) There are leaks, breaks, crimps, or cracks in the air hoses, tubes, or connections.<br/>   (b) Lines are being chafed by moving parts, frame, or other lines.<br/>   (c) Leaks in valves, diaphragms, piston cups, or connections can be heard.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Vacuum System.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Condition of vacuum system: Visually inspect system <br/>for collapsed, broken, badly chafed, and improperly supported hoses and tubing, and loose or broken hose clamps.</td>
              <td>(1)<br/>   (a) Hoses and tubing are leaking, collapsed, broken, badly chafed, improperly supported, or loose because of broken clamps.<br/>   (b) Hose or tubing is in good condition but exposed to danger from flying debris or rubbing.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Operation of vacuum system: Couple trailer or semitrailer to a vacuum supply and open shutoff valves. Then: <br/>   (a) If motor vehicle is used, start engine and allow about 1 minute to build vacuum;<br/>   (b) Apply and release brake pedal a number of times and observe action of brake chamber rods.</td>
              <td>(2)<br/>   (a) Brake chamber rod does not move when brakes are applied or released.<br/>   (b) Rods do not reach full released position.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Actuator Reserve.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Actuator reserve test:<br/>   (a) On air or vacuum mechanical brakes, measure the stroke <br/>of the air or vacuum chambers from fully released to fully applied position. <br/>   (b) On air-over-hydraulic brake systems, measure air chamber travel from fully released to fully applied position (some <br/>systems include a rod gauge for visual checking).</td>
              <td>(1)<br/>   (a) The push rod travel on S-Cam Brakes exceeds the maximum stroke listed in S-Cam Brakes—Push Travel Limits Chart.<br/>   (b) Push rod travel on BF Goodrich Air Actuated Disc Brakes exceeds manufacturer's specification.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Push rod/slack adjuster angle: Measure push rod/slack adjuster angle with brakes applied.</td>
              <td>(2) Push rod/slack adjuster angle is less than 90° with brakes applied.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Wedge brake shoe movement: Measure total shoe <br/>movement from released to applied positions.</td>
              <td>(3) Brake shoe movement on wedge brakes exceeds 1/16 inch.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <text>Figure 1, chart and diagram.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Electric Brakes. Electric brakes are generally used on small and occasionally on large commercial trailers and semitrailers.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Electric brakes—function: <br/>   (a) Insert a low range DC ammeter into the circuit <br/>between the controller and brakes. Ammeter should read <br/>"zero" with controller in off position. Gradually apply controller to full "On" position and take maximum ammeter reading. <br/>   (b) Gradually return controller to full "Off" position. <br/>Ammeter should return to "zero". Divide the maximum <br/>ammeter reading by the number of brakes.<br/>   (c) Inspect for loose or corroded terminal connections <br/>and broken, frayed, or unsupported wires.</td>
              <td>(1)<br/>   (a) The maximum amperage per brake is: <br/>      (i) More than 20 percent above; or<br/>      (ii) More than 30 percent below brake manufacturer's maximum current rating.<br/>   (b) Electric terminals are loose or excessively corroded.<br/>   (c) Wires or connectors are broken, frayed, or not properly supported.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Emergency Brake. Every trailer, semitrailer, and pole trailer equipped with air or vacuum actuated brakes and every trailer, semitrailer, and pole trailer with a registered gross weight in excess of 3,000 pounds, manufactured or assembled after June 1, 1970, shall be equipped with brakes of a character to be applied automatically and promptly and remain applied for at least 15 minutes on breakaway from the towing vehicle.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Air or vacuum emergency brakes: <br/>   (a) Couple trailer or semitrailer to fully charged air or vacuum system. Then: <br/>      (i) Disconnect couplings and observe for automatic application of trailer or semitrailer brakes; <br/>      (ii) Observe operating mechanism for "bottoming" before brakes are fully applied; <br/>      (iii) Record length of time brakes remain applied. <br/>   (b) If manual control for trailer or semitrailer emergency brake system is installed: <br/>      (i) Connect trailer or semitrailer couplings and build up the system to governor cut-out point;<br/>      (ii) Stop engine and operate control—observe emergency brake application and release;<br/>      (iii) Make a series of brake applications and observe automatic trailer or semitrailer brake application.</td>
              <td>(1)<br/>   (a) Emergency brakes do not automatically apply.<br/>   (b) Operating mechanism "bottoms" before brakes are fully applied.<br/>   (c) Brakes do not remain applied for at least 15 minutes.<br/>   (d) With manual control, brakes do not apply and release by operating manual control. <br/>   (e) Air only: Brakes apply automatically when reservoir pressure is above 45 psi or fail to apply automatically when pressure is reduced within range of 45-20 psi.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Electric emergency brakes: Place a DC ammeter in the emergency brake power supply lines. Disconnect all electrical connections between the towing vehicle and the trailer or semitrailer. Then:<br/>   (a) Operate breakaway switch and observe application of trailer or semitrailer brakes;<br/>   (b) Operate ammeter reading and divide by the number of brakes; <br/>   (c) Connect electric cables, return safety switch to normal position, and observe release of trailer or semitrailer brakes.</td>
              <td>(2)<br/>   (a) Brakes do not apply automatically when breakaway safety switch is operated.<br/>   (b) Brakes do not release when switch is returned to normal position.<br/>   (c) Brakes do not receive at least 50 percent of manufacturer's maximum current (amperes) rating per brake.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Hydraulic surge emergency brakes. Inspection for operation of breakaway device, if equipped, application of trailer or semitrailer brakes and record length of time brakes remain applied.</td>
              <td>(3)<br/>   (a) Breakaway device, if equipped, fails to operate.<br/>   (b) Brakes would not apply upon breakaway.<br/>   (c) Brakes do not remain applied for at least 15 minutes.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Tires and Wheels.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Tires.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Reference is made to Figures 2 and 3 for visual aid in determining tire wear. This inspection is visual. <br/>   (a) Inspect for tire wear:<br/>      (i) Tires without tread wear indicators.<br/>      (ii) Tires with tread wear indicators. <br/>      (iii) For cord exposure. <br/>   (b) Inspect for tread cuts, snags, or sidewall cracks.<br/>   (c) Inspect for lumps, bulges, or knots. <br/>   (d) Inspect for fabric breaks and exposed or damaged body cords.<br/>   (e) Inspect for regrooved or recut tires.<br/>   (f) Inspect for mismatching of tire types.<br/>   (g) Inspect for mismatching of tire sizes (dual wheels).<br/>   (h) Inspect for tire size. <br/>   (i) Visually inspect for restricted usage marking on tire such as reclassified tires.<br/>   (j) Inspect valve stems for leaks, damage, or cracks.</td>
              <td>(1)(a)<br/>      (i) Tire is worn so that less than 2/32 inch tread remains when a measurement is made in any motor groove at three locations spaced approximately equally around outside of tire.<br/>      (ii) Tire is worn so that the tread wear indicators contact the road in any two adjacent grooves at three locations spaced approximately equally around outside of tire.<br/>     (iii) Tire has a worn spot that exposes the cord through the tread.<br/>  (b) Tire has tread cuts, snags, or sidewall cracks in any direction and deep enough to expose cords.<br/>  (c) Tire has visible bumps, bulges, or knots indicating partial failure or separation of the tire structure.<br/>  (d) Tire has an unrepaired fabric break or sidewall has damaged body cords.<br/>  (e) Tire has been regrooved, or recut below original groove depth, except those that are designed to be readily identified as regroovable.<br/>  (f) Tires are not the same size on the same axle.<br/>  (g) The diameter of one of the duals is not within 1/2 inch of the other, or if the gauge block can be inserted between the tire and the caliper.<br/>  (h) Tires are smaller than manufacturer's specified minimum or of a larger size so that tire and body contact during different vehicle attitudes.<br/>  (i) Tire is:<br/>     (i) Marked "For Farm Use Only";<br/>     (ii) Marked "Off Highway Use Only";<br/>     (iii) Marked "For Racing Use Only";<br/>     (iv) A metal studded snow tire during period when prohibited (April 1st through October 31st in Allegany, Carroll, Frederick, Garrett, and Washington counties.) Reject in other areas at any time.<br/>  (j) Valve stem is leaking, cracked, or damaged or shows evidence of wear.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <text>Figures 2-4.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Wheels.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect wheel bolts, nuts, or lugs.</td>
              <td>(1) Wheel bolts, nuts, studs, or lugs are loose, missing, or damaged.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Inspect for wheel damage.</td>
              <td>(2) Any part of a wheel is bent, cracked, rewelded, or damaged to affect safe operation of the vehicle; loose or missing spokes on spoke-type wheels; or any wheel not the original, equivalent, or one designated by the wheel manufacturer for use on that particular vehicle. (Specialty Equipment Market Association, SEMA, or U.S./D.O.T. approved wheels and adapters are acceptable.)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Inspect rims and lock rings for matching, condition, <br/>tightness of nuts and clamps, and evidence of slippage.</td>
              <td>(3) Rims and lock rings are obviously mismatched, nuts and clamps are loose, or there is evidence of slippage.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Rear Metal Frame.</heading>
    <text>Every trailer or semitrailer of a gross weight of 3,000 pounds or more when operated upon a highway shall be equipped with a permanent metal frame attached to the underside of the rear of the vehicle. The frame may not be any wider than the width of the vehicle and may not be more than 30 inches above the highway when moving and shall be constructed of heavy gauge steel. The maximum transverse distance from the widest part of the vehicle at the rear to the frame may not exceed 18 inches. The frame shall be constructed so as not to interfere with lights or other warning devices. Any trailer or semitrailer so constructed and maintained so that the body, chassis, or other parts thereof afford protection required by this section, shall be deemed to be in compliance. The provisions of this section do not apply to pole trailers or to vehicles where the installation of the required frame would prevent operation of the vehicle to secure its designed use.</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
              <em>Procedures:</em>
            </td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
              <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>A. Rear Metal Frame. Inspect frame for proper size, <br/>mounting, interference with lights or warning devices, <br/>and type of construction.</td>
            <td>A.<br/>   (1) Rear protector frame does not conform to requirements.<br/>   (2) Rear protector frame is missing when required.</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Rear Wheel Protector Flaps.</heading>
    <text>Every trailer or semitrailer when operated upon a highway shall be equipped with suitable metal protectors or substantial flexible flaps behind the rearmost wheels of the vehicle to prevent the projection of rocks, dirt, water, or other substances to the rear and to minimize side spray. This section does not apply to pole trailers or other vehicles if the construction is such that complete freedom around the wheel area is necessary to secure the designed use of the vehicle.</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
              <em>Procedures:</em>
            </td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
              <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>A. The protectors or flaps shall have a ground clearance of <br/>not more than one-third of the horizontal distance from the bottom edge of the protector or flap to the centerline of the <br/>axle, provided, however, that no protector or flap need be <br/>closer to the ground than 6 inches under any condition of loading. The protector or flap shall extend laterally at least <br/>the width of the tire or tires being protected.</td>
            <td>A. Measurement A is longer than 1/3 the length of Measurement B (Figure 5) and the vehicle is not equipped with flaps or protectors or flaps are not of required length.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>B. If any trailer or semitrailer is so designed or constructed <br/>that the objectives of this section are accomplished by reason <br/>of fender or body construction or other means of enclosure, either permanent or temporary, then the requirements of this section have been satisfied.</td>
            <td>B. Protector or flap does not extend laterally at least the width of the tire or tires being protected.<br/>C. Protectors or flaps are not securely attached to the vehicle.</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>Figure 5—REAR WHEEL PROTECTOR FLAP REQUIREMENTS.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Fenders.</heading>
    <text>Fender inspection shall include condition, mounting, and coverage of wheels and tires. If the body or fenders of the vehicle do not provide coverage, the vehicle shall then be equipped with suitable metal protectors or substantial flexible flaps behind the rearmost wheels of the vehicle. This section does not apply to pole trailers or other vehicles where the construction is such that complete freedom around the wheel area is necessary to secure the designed use of the vehicle.</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
              <em>Procedures:</em>
            </td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
              <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>A. Fenders shall be securely attached to the vehicle and inspected for tears, sharp or jagged edges, sufficient coverage <br/>of the wheel and tire to the side and to the front and rear of tires and wheels. Fenders may be extended outward to compensate for tire or wheel changes provided the extensions:</p>
              <p>(1) Provide required coverage of wheels and tires;</p>
              <p>(2) Are constructed of substantial materials;</p>
              <p>(3) Are securely attached to the fenders;</p>
              <p>(4) Have all edges rolled to eliminate sharp or jagged edges;</p>
              <p>(5) Do not contact tires during different vehicle attitudes.</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>A.<br/>  (1) Fender has tears, sharp or jagged edges.</p>
              <p>(2) Fender is not securely attached to vehicle.</p>
              <p>(3) Fender does not extend outward enough to cover the top of the wheel band tire.</p>
              <p>(4) The rear of the rearmost fenders do not extend downward to the horizontal centerline of the wheel.</p>
              <p>(5) Front of all fenders do not extend forward from the vertical centerline of the wheel to at least a 45-degree angle of the horizontal centerline.</p>
              <p>(6) Fender is missing.</p>
              <p>(7) The vehicle is not equipped with flaps behind the rearmost wheels when required.</p>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Lighting.</heading>
    <text>General Lamp and Reflector Inspection. This includes all original equipment, exterior lighting plus whatever lights are authorized. (For definitions of lighting terms, refer to <cite path="11.14.04.12|E.">COMAR 11.14.04.12E</cite> and F.) Pole trailers and modular home trailers may have portable lamp devices which attach to the load when in use to comply with applicable regulations.</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
              <em>Procedures:</em>
            </td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
              <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>A. Visual Inspection of Lamp Function. Connect trailer or semitrailer to power source of towing vehicle. Turn on night driving lights of towing vehicle and visually inspect the following:</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle">
              <p>A.<br/>  (1) A required lamp is missing or fails to function.</p>
              <p>(2) Turn signals do not properly indicate right or left when so activated.</p>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>(1) Actuate the turn signal lever of the towing vehicle to right and left; and observe function of turn signal lights of trailer or semitrailer (1962 or newer trailers, semitrailers, and pole trailers shall be so equipped). Turn signals shall emit red or amber light.</td>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>(3) Any lamp shows color contrary to law (red or blue light to the front; white light to the rear, except license plate lamp).</p>
              <p>(4) A required lamp, lens, or reflector is obscured by any object or shielded by a nontransparent material.</p>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>(2) Depress the brake pedal of the towing vehicle and <br/>observe the function of the stop lamps of the trailer or<br/>semitrailer (1972 or newer trailers, semitrailers, and  pole<br/>trailers shall have two red or amber stop lamps, all others one).</td>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>(5) A lamp or reflector is not mounted to properly direct or reflect light.</p>
              <p>(6) A lamp assembly or reflector is loose or improperly mounted.</p>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>(3) Observe function of tail lamps of trailer or semitrailer <br/>(Red: two on 1972 or newer vehicles; all others, one).</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle">
              <p>(7) A tail lamp, stop lamp, or turn signal has a cracked or broken lens which emits a white light to the rear.</p>
              <p>(8) A lamp, lens, or reflector is not an approved type.</p>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>(4) Observe function of license plate lamp of trailer or semitrailer (White: May be incorporated in tail lamp).</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>(5) 1972 and newer model trailers and semitrailers shall be equipped with two red reflectors on the rear. All others, one. (Reflectors may be incorporated in tail lamps.) In addition, <br/>every trailer or semitrailer 80 inches or more in overall width shall be, and all other trailers or semitrailers may be, equipped as required in §A(6),(7), (8), and (9).</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>(6) Side marker lamps: One amber, front, and one red, rear, on each side. Vehicles over 30 feet in overall length, one amber, centrally located with respect to length of the vehicle.</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>(7) Reflectors: One amber, front, and one red, rear, on each side. Vehicles over 30 feet in overall length, one amber, centrally located with respect to the length of the vehicle. (Reflectors may be incorporated in side marker lamps.)</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>(8) Clearance Lamps: Two amber, front, and two red, rear, to indicate the overall width of the vehicle. One on each side of the vertical centerline of the vehicle at the same height and as near the top of the vehicle as possible. If the vehicle is equipped with three red identification lamps on the top rear, the rear clearance lamps may be mounted at the top or bottom of the vehicle.</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>(9) Identification Lamps: (Required on 1972 or newer trailers and semitrailers). Three red, rear, grouped in a horizontal row with lamp centers spaced not less than 6 inches or more than 12 inches apart and mounted on a permanent structure of the vehicle as close as possible to the vertical centerline of the vehicle. Pole trailers may be equipped with three red identification lamps visible to the rear, mounted on the rear of the cab of the towing vehicle, the bolster, or on the rear of the load provided they are visible.</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>(10) Modular home trailers may be equipped with a bar light assembly provided it is bolted securely to the rear frame of the trailer.</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-vertical-align="middle"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>Figures 6—COMMERCIAL SEMI TRAILER LIGHTING REQUIREMENTS.</text>
    <text>Figures 7—SMALL TRAILER LIGHTING REQUIREMENTS.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Electrical System.</heading>
    <text>To save time, the inspector should develop his own plan or sequence for inspecting miscellaneous electrical items, many of which can be inspected while inspecting other items.</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
              <em>Procedures:</em>
            </td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
              <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>A. Inspect Electrical System:<br/>  (1) Wiring shall be well insulated.</td>
            <td>A.<br/>  (1) Wiring:<br/>     (a) Insulation is bare, cracked, or broken.<br/>     (b) Shows evidence of burning or short-circuiting.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>(2) Connections shall be tight and secure.</td>
            <td>(2) Connections are loose or show signs of excessive corrosion.</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Load Covers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not apply to a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Class G (trailer) vehicle registered or capable of being registered under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-927">Transportation Article, §13-927, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, provided no part of the load is within 6 inches of the top of any of the enclosures the load touches;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Construction vehicle working within the confines of a public works construction work project site as outlined in the construction project's plans and specifications, provided the distance traveled does not exceed 1 mile or the distance specified in an extension granted by the Maryland Department of Transportation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Construction vehicle or mining equipment while crossing a highway between construction or mining sites; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Vehicle, within the Port of Baltimore for a distance not to exceed 1 mile, carrying a load of loose material between a stockpile or storage facility and a vessel docked at the Port.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A vehicle carrying loose material which is within 6 inches of the top of any of the enclosures the loose material touches, shall have the loose material covered by a firmly attached canvas or similar type covering.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The requirements of this regulation apply only to the issuance and certification of a safety equipment repair order and do not apply to a complete inspection required upon sale or transfer of ownership of a used vehicle. A safety equipment repair order may be certified only if the cover is present, fully covers the top of the bed, and meets the requirements of this regulation.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Procedures:</em>
              </td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Reject Vehicle If:</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect cover for presence and size.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Cover is not present or does not fully cover the top of the vehicle bed.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Inspect cover for holes, rips, tears, or broken mesh.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Cover contains holes, rips, tears, or broken mesh which would permit any part of the load to blow, fall, or spill from the bed.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Inspect cover for proper mounting.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(3) Cover is not securely attached to the bed.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(4) Inspect securement hardware for presence and condition.</td>
              <td>(4) Securement hardware is missing, broken, or damaged.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|23-101">23-101</cite>-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|23-105">23-105</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|24-106">24-106</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container"><cite path="|11.14.05">COMAR 11.14.05</cite> Noise Abatement Program recodified <cite path="|11.14.07">COMAR 11.14.07</cite></annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" discontinuity="true">Regulations .01—.10 Safety Standards for Trailers adopted effective</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-10-31">October 31, 1988 (15:22 Md. R. 2557)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-01">Regulation .08 amended effective April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 687)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-01">Regulation .11 adopted effective April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 687)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
