<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Incentive Program for Certification by the National Board for Professional Teaching Standards</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes the criteria for the selection of public school candidates who are eligible to receive financial aid, subject to annual appropriation by the Maryland General Assembly, to pursue initial certification or renewal by the National Board for Professional Teaching Standards.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Completion of the National Board Assessment process" means the candidate submits the requisite number of scoreable entries, as defined by National Board for Professional Teaching Standards (NBPTS), for initial certification or renewal within one assessment cycle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"National Board certificate" means a credential issued by the NBPTS which attests that a candidate has been judged by peers as one who is accomplished, makes sound professional judgments about student learning, and acts effectively on those judgments.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"National Board certification fee" means the assessment fee charged by the NBPTS.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"National Board certification process for initial certification" means the process which involves compiling a portfolio and completing assessment center activities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"National Board certification process for renewal" means the process that requires the candidate for renewal to complete one portfolio entry that contains evidence of connections between the candidate's continued professional growth and student learning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"National Board for Professional Teaching Standards (NBPTS)" means a private, nonprofit organization whose primary purpose is to advance the teaching profession and to improve student learning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Retake" means the process offered by the NBPTS, which allows candidates, during their initial attempt, to resubmit any combination of portfolio entries, assessment center exercises, or both, for which they did not achieve a passing score.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Eligibility Criteria.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In order to be eligible to receive financial aid to pursue initial NBPTS certification, a candidate shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have completed 3 years of successful teaching on a Maryland professional certificate at one or more early childhood, elementary, middle, or secondary public schools;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Hold a valid Maryland professional certificate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Affirm voluntary participation in the NBPTS certification process;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Comply with the deadlines as specified by the Department and NBPTS; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Demonstrate teaching practice in designated fields as identified by the NBPTS.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In order to be eligible to receive financial aid to pursue renewal of the NBPTS certificate, a candidate shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Hold a valid Maryland professional certificate; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Comply with the deadlines as specified by the Department and NBPTS.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In order to be eligible to receive financial aid to pursue one retake, a candidate shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Hold a valid Maryland professional certificate; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pursue the NBPTS certificate within the next assessment cycle immediately following the cycle in which the candidate does not achieve National Board certification.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A local school system may establish additional criteria for eligibility.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Selection Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each participating local school system shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Establish a diverse selection committee representative of the educational community to include, but not be limited to, classroom teachers, National Board certified teachers, school administrators, and local teacher association members who are classroom teachers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Establish and publicize written criteria, including the criteria identified in Regulation .03 of this chapter for the selection of candidates;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Forward names of initial candidates for the financial incentive program to the Department in accordance with the timelines established by the Department, with the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Candidate code;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Signed, notarized memorandum of understanding that specifies the candidate's financial responsibility if the candidate does not complete the assessment process;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Confirmation of verification of eligibility as identified in Regulation .03 of this chapter; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Verification that the selection procedures specified in this regulation were followed; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Forward names of renewal and retake candidates for the financial incentive program to the Department in accordance with the timelines established by the Department, with the information required under Regulation .04A(3)(a)—(c) of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The State Board of Education shall select initial, renewal, and retake candidates for National Board certification and promptly notify the respective school system and candidates in writing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Funding for the National Board Incentive Program is contingent upon appropriations by the General Assembly, and individual participation is not guaranteed.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Credits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A candidate who receives a National Board certificate shall earn six credits toward the renewal of the Maryland professional certificate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A candidate who completes the National Board certification process, but who does not receive a National Board certificate, shall earn three credits toward the renewal of the Maryland professional certificate.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Costs.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Costs for the fee charged by NBPTS shall be shared in the following manner:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The State Board of Education shall pay 2/3 of the National Board certification fee, and the local school system shall pay 1/3 of the National Board certification fee for an initial or renewal candidate; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Subject to the annual appropriation by the Maryland General Assembly, the State Board of Education may pay 2/3 of the National Board certification fee, and the local school system may pay 1/3 of the National Board certification fee, for a candidate to pursue one retake for National Board certification.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Reimbursement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A candidate who does not complete the National Board certification process shall reimburse the State Board of Education the full amount of the aid, and the State Board of Education shall reimburse the local school system its share.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A candidate who completes the certification process but does not achieve National Board Certification, is not required to reimburse the amount of the aid.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Staff Development Plan.</heading>
    <text>The Department shall establish a Statewide staff development plan that uses the skills and knowledge of teachers who have obtained National Board certification.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Advanced Professional Certificate.</heading>
    <text>A candidate who receives a National Board certificate shall be eligible to receive the Advanced Professional certificate if the course work and experience requirements are satisfied in accordance with COMAR 13A.12.01.06E.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|6-112">6-112</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-01">Effective date: June 1, 1998 (25:11 Md. R. 821)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-09-22">Regulation .01 amended effective September 22, 2008 (35:19 Md. R. 1717)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-09">Regulation .02B amended effective September 22, 2008 (35:19 Md. R. 1717); April 9, 2018 (45:7 Md. R. 346)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-09-22">Regulation .03 amended effective September 22, 2008 (35:19 Md. R. 1717)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-09">Regulation .03C amended effective April 9, 2018 (45:7 Md. R. 346)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-09">Regulation .04 amended effective January 20, 2003 (30:1 Md. R. 26); September 22, 2008 (35:19 Md. R. 1717); April 9, 2018 (45:7 Md. R. 346)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-09-22">Regulation .05 amended effective September 22, 2008 (35:19 Md. R. 1717)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-09">Regulation .06 amended effective September 22, 2008 (35:19 Md. R. 1717); April 9, 2018 (45:7 Md. R. 346)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-09-22">Regulation .07 amended effective September 22, 2008 (35:19 Md. R. 1717)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2008-09-22">Regulation .08 adopted effective January 20, 2003 (30:1 Md. R. 26); September 22, 2008 (35:19 Md. R. 1717)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
