<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Use of Trade-Marks for Maryland Fresh and Maryland Fancy Eggs</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>"Department" means Maryland Department of Agriculture.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>"Secretary" means the Secretary of Agriculture or the Secretary's designee.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Eligibility to Use Insignia.</heading>
    <text>Persons approved by the Secretary or his authorized representative to pack and sell eggs as Maryland Fresh or Maryland Fancy eggs as provided in the Maryland Egg Law and subject regulations shall be eligible to apply to the Department to use the appropriate insignia.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Applications.</heading>
    <text>Application to use the insignia shall be made, on an annual basis, on forms provided by the Department.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Submitting of Designs for Cartons.</heading>
    <text>Applicants shall submit the designs or art work for all cartons on which the insignia is to appear to the Department or its authorized representative before its use.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Minimum Width of Insignia.</heading>
    <text>The minimum width of the insignia on any egg carton shall be 1-1/2 inches.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Required Colors.</heading>
    <text>The insignia is to be reproduced on egg cartons in black printing on a gold background, except that other colors may be permitted if, in the opinion of the Secretary or his authorized representative, those colors are compatible with the design of the carton.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Reports.</heading>
    <text>Authorized users of the insignia will be required, from time to time, to make reports, on forms furnished by the Department, showing the volume of eggs packed and sold in cartons bearing the insignia and other related information. Any information obtained from these reports shall be kept confidential as to individual source but this may not prohibit the compilation and issuance of reports from the information required from a number of sources that does not disclose the identity of any single source.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Suspension or Revocation.</heading>
    <text>Authorization to use the insignia may be revoked or suspended by the Secretary or his authorized representative upon satisfactory proof that the user has violated any provision of the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag">Agriculture Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, Subtitle "Maryland Egg Law".</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Restriction.</heading>
    <text>A person, corporation, partnership, or other business entity may not use the term "Maryland Fresh" or "Maryland Fancy" in the business or firm name, corporate title, trademark, trade name, or other nomenclature.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Form of Insignia.</heading>
    <text>Authorized insignia users may use the old or new insignia until January 1, 1976, unless otherwise suspended or revoked. After January, 1976, only the new insignia as reproduced below shall be used:</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">
      <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|4-306">Agriculture Article, §4-306, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>
    </annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1973-07-01">Effective date: July 1, 1973</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-12-02">Regulation .10 adopted effective December 2, 1977 (4:25 Md. R. 1915)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
