<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Maryland Register Information" name="information">
  <heading>Information About the Maryland Register and COMAR</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>0001-01-01</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="reg">Information</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <container name="register">
    <heading>MARYLAND REGISTER</heading>
    <text>The Maryland Register is an official State publication published every other week throughout the year. A cumulative index is published quarterly.</text>
    <text>The Maryland Register is the temporary supplement to the Code of Maryland Regulations. Any change to the text of regulations published  in COMAR, whether by adoption, amendment, repeal, or emergency action, must first be published in the Register.</text>
    <text>The following information is also published regularly in the Register:</text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>Governors Executive Orders</li>
        <li>Attorney Generals Opinions in full text</li>
        <li>Open Meetings Compliance Board Opinions in full text</li>
        <li>State Ethics Commission Opinions in full text</li>
        <li>Court Rules</li>
        <li>District Court Administrative Memoranda</li>
        <li>Courts of Appeal Hearing Calendars</li>
        <li>Agency Hearing and Meeting Notices</li>
        <li>Synopses of Bills Introduced and Enacted by the General Assembly</li>
        <li>Other documents considered to be in the public interest</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
  </container>
  <container name="citation">
    <heading>CITATION TO THE MARYLAND REGISTER</heading>
    <text>The Maryland Register is cited by volume, issue, page number, and date. Example:</text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>19:8 Md. R. 815—817 (April 17, 1992) refers to Volume 19, Issue 8, pages 815—817 of the Maryland Register issued on April 17, 1992.</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
  </container>
  <container name="code">
    <heading>CODE OF MARYLAND REGULATIONS (COMAR)</heading>
    <text>COMAR is the official compilation of all regulations issued by agencies of the State of Maryland. The Maryland Register is COMARs temporary supplement, printing all changes to regulations as soon as they occur. At least once annually, the changes to regulations printed in the Maryland Register are incorporated into COMAR by means of permanent supplements.</text>
  </container>
  <container name="code-citation">
    <heading>CITATION TO COMAR REGULATIONS</heading>
    <text>COMAR regulations are cited by title number, subtitle number, chapter number, and regulation number. Example: COMAR 10.08.01.03 refers to Title 10, Subtitle 08, Chapter 01, Regulation 03.</text>
  </container>
  <container name="dibr">
    <heading>DOCUMENTS INCORPORATED BY REFERENCE</heading>
    <text>Incorporation by reference is a legal device by which a document is made part of COMAR simply by referring to it. While the text of an incorporated document does not appear in COMAR, the provisions of the incorporated document are as fully enforceable as any other COMAR regulation. Each regulation that proposes to incorporate a document is identified in the Maryland Register by an Editors Note. The Cumulative Table of COMAR Regulations Adopted, Amended or Repealed, found online, also identifies each regulation incorporating a document. Documents incorporated by reference are available for inspection in various depository libraries located throughout the State and at the Division of State Documents. These depositories are listed in the first issue of the Maryland Register published each year. For further information, call 410-974-2486.</text>
  </container>
  <container name="research">
    <heading>HOW TO RESEARCH REGULATIONS</heading>
    <text>An Administrative History at the end of every COMAR chapter gives information about past changes to regulations. To determine if there have been any subsequent changes, check the "Cumulative Table of COMAR Regulations Adopted, Amended, or Repealed" which is found online at http://www.dsd.state.md.us/PDF/CumulativeTable.pdf. This table lists the regulations in numerical order, by their COMAR number, followed by the citation to the Maryland Register in which the change occurred. The Maryland Register serves as a temporary supplement to COMAR, and the two publications must always be used together. A Research Guide for Maryland Regulations is available. For further information, call 410-260-3876.</text>
  </container>
  <container name="subscription">
    <heading>SUBSCRIPTION INFORMATION</heading>
    <text>For subscription forms for the Maryland Register and COMAR, see the back pages of the Maryland Register. Single issues of the Maryland Register are $15.00 per issue.</text>
  </container>
  <container name="participation">
    <heading>CITIZEN PARTICIPATION IN THE REGULATION-MAKING PROCESS</heading>
    <text>Maryland citizens and other interested persons may participate in the process by which administrative regulations are adopted, amended, or repealed, and may also initiate the process by which the validity and applicability of regulations is determined. Listed below are some of the ways in which citizens may participate (references are to State Government Article (SG), Annotated Code of Maryland):</text>
    <text>
      <ul>
        <li>By submitting data or views on proposed regulations either orally or in writing, to the proposing agency (see "Opportunity for Public Comment" at the beginning of all regulations appearing in the Proposed Action on Regulations section of the Maryland Register). (See SG, §10-112)</li>
        <li>By petitioning an agency to adopt, amend, or repeal regulations. The agency must respond to the petition. (See SG §10-123)</li>
        <li>By petitioning an agency to issue a declaratory ruling with respect to how any regulation, order, or statute enforced by the agency applies. (SG, Title 10, Subtitle 3)</li>
        <li>By petitioning the circuit court for a declaratory judgment on the validity of a regulation when it appears that the regulation interferes with or impairs the legal rights or privileges of the petitioner. (SG, §10-125)</li>
        <li>By inspecting a certified copy of any document filed with the Division of State Documents for publication in the Maryland Register. (See SG, §7-213)</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
  </container>
  <container name="other">
    <heading>OTHER INFORMATION</heading>
    <text><strong>Maryland Register (ISSN 0360-2834)</strong>. Postmaster: Send address changes and other mail to: Maryland Register, State House, Annapolis, Maryland 21401. Tel. 410-260-3876. Published biweekly, with cumulative indexes published quarterly, by the State of Maryland, Division of State Documents, State House, Annapolis, Maryland 21401. The subscription rate for the Maryland Register is $225 per year (first class mail). All subscriptions post-paid to points in the U.S. periodicals postage paid at Annapolis, Maryland, and additional mailing offices</text>
    <text><strong>Wes Moore</strong>, Governor; <strong>Susan C. Lee</strong>, Secretary of State; <strong>Gail S. Klakring</strong>, Administrator; <strong>Mary D. MacDonald</strong>, Senior Editor, Maryland Register and COMAR; <strong>Elizabeth Ramsey</strong>, Editor, COMAR Online, and Subscription Manager; <strong>Tami Cathell</strong>, Help Desk, COMAR and Maryland Register Online.</text>
  </container>
</document>
