<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Regulation of Invasive Plants</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>These regulations establish a science-based risk assessment protocol to determine the harm and impact caused by invasive plants, including an approval procedure for activities involving invasive plant species that cause or are likely to cause severe harm and administrative orders that the Secretary may issue to enforce these regulations.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Commercial entity" means an entity that engages in a plant removal activity for profit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Invasive plant" means a terrestrial plant species that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Did not evolve in the State; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If introduced within the State, will cause or is likely to cause, as determined by the Secretary:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Economic harm;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Ecological harm;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Environmental harm; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Harm to human health.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Off-site" means property other than where the Tier 1 invasive plant exists, including property under the control of the person removing the Tier 1 plant but not contiguous, for example, separated by a road or property owned by another person.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Tier 1 invasive plant" includes invasive plant species that cause or are likely to cause severe harm within the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Tier 2 invasive plant" includes invasive plant species that cause or are likely to cause substantial negative impact within the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Transport" means when a person moves a Tier 1 invasive plant anywhere within the State, including for transportation or shipment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Risk Assessment Protocol for Invasive Plants.</heading>
    <text>The Secretary shall determine whether an invasive plant qualifies as a Tier 1 or a Tier 2 plant based on the following protocols:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Plant risk assessment protocol established by the United States Department of Agriculture, Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service, Plant Protection Quarantine pursuant to A. Koop, L. Fowler, L. Newton, and B. Caton, Development and Validation of a Weed Screening Tool for the United States, Biological Invasions (2012) 14:273-294, which is incorporated by reference; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Factors relating to special Maryland circumstances (e.g. potential distribution, current distribution, threatened and endangered species or ecosystems, feasibility of control, and special agricultural conditions).</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="15|06|04|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Tier 1 Prohibitions and Approvals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as approved by the Secretary under this regulation, a person may not propagate, import, transfer, sell, purchase, transport, or introduce any living part of a Tier 1 invasive plant in the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person may conduct an activity prohibited under <cite path="15|06|04|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The person receives approval from the Secretary before conducting the activity; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The activity is for the purpose of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Disposing of the invasive plant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Controlling the invasive plant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Using the invasive plant for research or educational purposes; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Exporting the invasive plant out of the State</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A person has the Secretary's approval and may engage in any activity prohibited by <cite path="15|06|04|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> for the limited purpose of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Controlling a Tier 1 invasive plant, provided:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The person is not a commercial entity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The plant is not taken off-site; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The plant is not placed at a location in the proximate vicinity of a roadway or waterway that could facilitate the movement of the invasive plant off-site; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Transporting a Tier 1 invasive plant off-site for the purpose of identification or disposal, provided:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The person is not a commercial entity; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The plant is removed according to the provisions of Regulation .06G of this chapter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>For approvals not granted under <cite path="15|06|04|.04|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, a person may submit a written request to the Secretary for approval of any activity allowed under <cite path="15|06|04|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> with the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Name;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Business, nursery, or plant dealer license number if applicable;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Phone;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Email address;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Tier 1 plant for which approval is being requested (full botanical name);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Specific location of the Tier 1 plant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Proposed activity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Method of safeguarding from propagule dispersal;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Time frame of the proposed activity; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Any other information required by the Secretary.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Upon notice and an opportunity to be heard, the Secretary may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Withdraw or revoke any approval for any person who violates any condition of any approval by the Secretary; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Revise any approval as a condition of any permit, based on new information obtained after an approval is granted.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Administrative Orders By The Secretary.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Secretary may issue administrative orders to enforce the provisions of this chapter and Agriculture Article, Title 9.5 (Invasive Plants Prevention and Control), Annotated Code of Maryland, as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Order any person to cease propagating, importing, transferring, selling, purchasing, transporting, or introducing any living part of a Tier 1 invasive plant in the State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Order the condemnation and seizure of any Tier 1 plant owned or possessed by any person who violates <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|9">§9.5-302(a)(2) of the Agriculture Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Order the marking or tagging in a conspicuous manner of a Tier 1 plant owned or controlled by any person subject to an order of the Secretary under this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Order any person, on notice from the Secretary, to dispose of any Tier 1 plant that is held in violation of this Chapter or in violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag">Agriculture Article, Title 9.5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, in a manner that renders all plant parts nonviable, or allow a person to return a Tier 1 plant to the out-of-State supplier of the plant, as approved in advance by the Secretary;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Order a person to make any Tier 1 plant available to the Secretary for destruction if the person has failed to dispose of the Tier 1 plant as ordered by the Secretary and require that person to pay any destruction cost;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Order any person to cease selling or offering for sale at any retail outlet a Tier 2 invasive plant until the retail outlet posts in a conspicuous manner in proximity to all Tier 2 plant displays a sign identifying the plants as Tier 2 plants;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Order any person to cease providing landscaping services to plant or supply for planting a Tier 2 invasive plant, if the person fails to provide the customer with a list of Tier 2 invasive plants; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Order a person to take any action that the Secretary considers necessary to enforce the requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag">Agriculture Article, Title 9.5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person who violates any order issued by the Secretary is subject to a civil penalty not to exceed $500 for each violation.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Tier 1 and Tier 2 Invasive Plants.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following plants are classified as Tier 1 invasive plants upon adoption of this regulation (see Department's website for adoption date http://mda.maryland.gov/plantspests/Pages/maryland invasive plants prevention and control.aspx):</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ficaria verna (fig buttercup);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Geranium lucidum (shining cranesbill);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Iris pseudacorus (yellow flag iris);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Euonymus fortune (wintercreeper);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Lonicera maackii (Amur honeysuckle); and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Corydalis incisa (incised fumewort).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Phase-out periods for Tier 1 Plants.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person in possession of a Tier 1 plant, except a person who is growing a woody plant in ground, shall comply with the Tier 1 provisions of this chapter within 1 year of that plant's effective date on the Tier 1 list.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person who is growing a Tier 1 woody plant in ground shall comply with the provisions of this chapter within 2 years from that plant's effective date on the Tier 1 list.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not acquire a new Tier 1 plant after that plant's effective date on the Tier 1 list.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The following plants are classified as Tier 2 invasive plants upon adoption of this regulation (see Department's  website for adoption date http://mda.maryland.gov/plants-pests/Pages/maryland invasive plants prevention and control.aspx):</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Euonymus alatus (burning bush);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ligustrum obtusifolium (blunt-leaved or border privet);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Wisteria sinensis (Chinese wisteria);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Wisteria floribunda (Japanese wisteria);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Wisteria xormosa (floribunda x sinensis hybrids);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Cytisus scopoarius, (Scotch broom);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Nandina domestica (heavenly bamboo), except for the cultivar Firepower;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Phyllostachys aurea (golden bamboo);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Phyllostachys aureosulcata (yellow groove bamboo);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Pyrus calleryana (Callery pear);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Tetradium daniellii (bee bee tree);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Aralia elata  (Japanese angelica-tree); and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Berberis thunbergii (Japanese barberry).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A person shall comply with the Tier 2 provisions of this chapter within 3 months of a plant's effective date on the Tier 2 list.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Procedures for Classification or Declassification of an Invasive Plant as a Tier 1 Invasive Plant or Tier 2 Invasive Plant.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person who requests the classification or declassification of a plant as a Tier 1 or Tier 2 invasive plant, shall submit a written request to the Secretary that includes the name of the requestor, contact information, scientific name of the plant, and a justification for the request.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of the request the Secretary, in consultation with the Invasive Plant Advisory Committee, shall make a determination, considering:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Whether the plant is or could potentially be sold or marketed in the State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the plant has already been assessed pursuant to Regulation .03 of this chapter, whether new, science-based information is available that could change the species' tier ranking; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the plant has not been assessed pursuant to Regulation .03 of this chapter, whether the justification for the request, including documented scientific evidence of economic, ecological, or environmental harm, or harm to human health, necessitates formal weed risk assessment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Secretary shall notify the requestor of the final decision regarding the request.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Distribution of the List of Tier 2 Invasive Plants.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Secretary shall send a list of Tier 2 invasive plants with annual renewal letters and with each new application for a nursery, plant dealer, or plant broker license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Secretary shall post the current list of Tier 2 invasive plants on the Department's website.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person in the business of providing landscaping services who plants or supplies for planting a Tier 2 invasive plant shall provide to the customer requesting the service the list of Tier 2 invasive plants.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Disposal of Tier 1 Plants. Any person who removes a Tier 1 plant off-site shall ensure that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The plant is completely contained (for example, covered or securely tarped in a solid conveyance, or bagged) to prevent the escape of plant parts into the environment; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the plant is being removed for disposal, it is removed to a Maryland Department of Environment approved landfill or compost facility for burial or composting.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Required Retail Signage for Tier 2 Plants.</heading>
    <text>A person shall post in a conspicuous place, in proximity to all Tier 2 invasive plant displays, a sign imprinted with the insignia required by this regulation, identifying the plants as Tier 2 invasive plants, consistent with the following:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The insignia imprinted on any sign shall be a minimum of 5" tall x 7" wide;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The insignia shall be reproduced in black on a bright yellow background; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The insignia as provided below shall be used:</text>
      <text>(picture next page)</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Agriculture Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-103">2-103</cite>(b) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|9">9</cite>.5-301, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-01-21">Effective date: January 21, 2013 (40:1 Md. R. 21)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" discontinuity="true" effective="2016-04-11">Chapter revised effective April 11, 2016 (43:7 Md. R. 452)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2017-02-13">Regulation .06 amended effective February 13, 2017 (44:3 Md. R. 189)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23">Regulation .06A, C amended effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 422)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-03-23">Regulation .06C amended effective March 23, 2020 (47:6 Md. R. 342)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
