<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General Administrative Provisions</heading>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Authority: Environment Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|1-101">1-101</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|1-404">1-404</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|2-101">2-101</cite>-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|2-103">2-103</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|2-301">2-301</cite>-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|2-303">2-303</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|10-102">10-102</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|10-103">10-103</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
  </annotations>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|11|01|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Actual Emissions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Actual emissions" means the average rate, in tons per year, at which a source discharged a pollutant during a 2-year period which precedes the date of a completed application for an NSR source or other specified date, and which is representative of normal source operation. The Department may allow the use of a different time period upon a determination that it is more representative of normal source operation. Actual emissions shall be calculated using the source's operating hours, production rates, and types of materials processed, stored, or combusted during the selected time period.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For the purpose of submitting emissions statements under Regulation .05-1 of this chapter, "actual emissions" means the emissions, in tons per year, which a source discharged during a calendar year or other specified period of time.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Air pollution" as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|2-101">Environment Article, §2-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, means the presence in the outdoor atmosphere of substances in quantities, having characteristics, and being of a duration which, from any single source or in combination with other sources, are, or may be predicted with reasonable certainty to be, injurious to human, plant, or animal life or to property, or which unreasonably interfere with the proper enjoyment of the property of others by reason of the emission of odors, solids, vapors, liquids, or gases, throughout the State and in such areas of the State that are affected by them.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Air pollution control equipment" means equipment whose primary purpose is to reduce the discharge of emissions into the atmosphere in order to comply with air pollution control requirements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Allowable emissions" means the maximum emissions a source or installation is capable of discharging after consideration of any physical, operational, or emissions limitations required by this subtitle or by federally enforceable conditions which restrict operations and which are included in an applicable air quality permit to construct, permit to operate, secretarial order, plan for compliance, consent agreement, court order, or applicable federal requirement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Capture efficiency" means the weight per unit time of a pollutant entering a capture system and delivered to a control device, divided by the weight per unit time of the total pollutant generated by a source of the pollutant, expressed as a percentage. The capture efficiency reflects how much of the pollutant is captured and routed to the control device.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Certifying individual" means the person responsible for the completion and certification of the emissions statement required in Regulation .05-1 of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6-1)</num>
        <text>CO<sub>2</sub> Equivalent Emissions (CO<sub>2</sub>e).</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"CO<sub>2</sub> equivalent emissions (CO<sub>2</sub>e)" means the amount of GHGs emitted.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"CO<sub>2</sub> equivalent emissions (CO<sub>2</sub>e)"shall be computed as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Except as stated in <cite path="26|11|01|.01|B.|(6-1)|(b)|(iii)">§B(6-1)(b)(iii) of this regulation</cite>, multiply the mass amount of emissions (tpy), for each of the six greenhouse gases in the pollutant GHGs, by the gas's associated global warming potential published at Table A–1 to Subpart A of 40 CFR Part 98 — Global Warming Potentials (74 FR 56395);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Sum the resultant values from <cite path="26|11|01|.01|B.|(6-1)|(b)|(i)">§B(6-1)(b)(i) of this regulation</cite> for each gas to compute a tpy CO<sub>2</sub>e; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Prior to July 21, 2014, the mass of the greenhouse gas carbon dioxide shall not include carbon dioxide emissions resulting from the combustion or decomposition of nonfossilized and biodegradable organic material originating from plants, animals, or micro-organisms (including products, by-products, residues and waste from agriculture, forestry and related industries as well as the nonfossilized and biodegradable organic fractions of industrial and municipal wastes, including gases and liquids recovered from the decomposition of nonfossilized and biodegradable organic material).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6-2)</num>
        <text>"Commercial bakery oven" (bakery oven) means an oven with a rated heat input capacity of 2,000,000 Btu per hour or greater, that is used to bake bread, rolls, or other yeast-raised products.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Confined emissions" means emissions which are discharged into the outdoor atmosphere through a stack, duct, hood, flue, or other conduit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Confined source" means an installation that discharges into the atmosphere through a stack, duct, hood, flue, or other conduit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Continuous emission monitor (CEM)" means a system of instruments installed, operated, and calibrated in accordance with the procedures in this subtitle to continuously measure and record the emission rate or concentration of a substance in a gas stream.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9-1)</num>
        <text>"Continuous opacity monitor (COM)" means a system of instruments installed, operated, and calibrated in accordance with the procedures in this subtitle to continuously measure and record the opacity of emissions as six-minute averages of not greater than 15 second increments.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Control efficiency" means the ratio of the emissions released by a control device and the emissions introduced to the control device, expressed as a percentage.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Control equipment" means any device or contrivance which prevents or reduces emissions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Control officer" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The health officer of Allegany, Anne Arundel, Calvert, Caroline, Carroll, Cecil, Charles, Dorchester, Frederick, Garrett, Harford, Howard, Kent, Prince George's, Queen Anne's, St. Mary's, Somerset, Talbot, Washington, or Wicomico County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Commissioner of Health of the City of Baltimore, the Director of the Baltimore County Department of Environmental Protection and Resource Management, the Director of the Montgomery County Department of Environmental Protection, or the Chief of the Environmental Programs Section of Worcester County Department of Planning, Permits, and Inspections; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any employee of the Department designated by the Secretary.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Reserved.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Department of the Environment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"Distillate fuel oil" means all American Society for Testing and Materials numbered fuel oils other than residual fuel oil.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"Emissions" means any substance, other than water in an uncombined form, discharged directly or indirectly into the atmosphere including, but not limited to, odors, particulate matter, vapors, gases, or any combination of these substances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>"Fuel-burning equipment" means any:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Boiler that has the primary function of heating air, water, or any other medium through indirect heat transfer from the burning of fuels; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Stationary internal combustion engine or stationary combustion turbine used to produce mechanical or electrical energy.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>"Fugitive emissions" means emissions which escape into the outdoor atmosphere through openings such as windows, doors, vents, roof monitors, poorly fitting closures, or poorly maintained equipment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18-1)</num>
        <text>"Greenhouse gases (GHGs)"means the aggregate group of six greenhouse gases:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>methane (CH<sub>4</sub>);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>nitrous oxide (N<sub>2</sub>O);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>sulfur hexafluoride (SF<sub>6</sub>);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>hydrofluorocarbons (HFCs); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>perfluorocarbons (PFCs).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>"Installation" means any article, machine, equipment, or other contrivance, including, but not limited to, emission control equipment, processing equipment, manufacturing equipment, fuel-burning equipment, incinerators, or any equipment or construction, capable of generating, causing, or reducing emissions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>Modification.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Modification" means any physical change in, or change in the operation of, a source or installation which causes a change in the quantity, nature or characteristics of emissions from the source or installation. However, this term excludes routine maintenance and routine repair, and increases in the hours of operation or in the production rate, unless these increases would be prohibited under any permit or approval conditions adopted by the Department.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In the context of New Source Performance Standards and National Emission Standards for Hazardous Air Pollutants adopted or enforced by the Department, the federal definition of the term "modification" is controlling.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Modify" means to make a modification.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>In the context of Prevention of Significant Deterioration regulations adopted or enforced by the Department, the federal definitions of the terms "modification" and "major modification" are controlling.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20-1)</num>
        <text>"Motor vehicle" means a vehicle registered with the Maryland Motor Vehicle Administration or the equivalent agency of another state.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>"National Emission Standards for Hazardous Air Pollutants source (NESHAP source)" means any:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Source of asbestos, beryllium, mercury, vinyl chloride, benzene, or inorganic arsenic which is subject to the provisions of 40 CFR Part 61 (excluding Subparts B, H, I, K, Q, R, T, and W), as amended; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Source which is subject to the provisions of 40 CFR Part 63, as amended.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>Reserved.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>"New Source Performance Standard source (NSPS source)" means any source which is subject to 40 CFR Part 60, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>"New Source Review source (NSR source)" means any major stationary source or major modification subject to the requirements of <cite path="|26.11.17">COMAR 26.11.17</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>"Odor" means that property of an emission which stimulates the sense of smell.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>"Opacity" means the degree to which emissions reduce the transmission of light and obscure the view of an object in the background.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>"Operating day" means a 24-hour period beginning midnight of one day and ending the following midnight, or an alternative 24-hour period approved by the Department, during which time an installation being monitored is operating, consuming fuel, processing or producing a material, or causing emissions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>"Oxides of nitrogen (NO<sub>x</sub>)" means compounds of nitrogen comprised of nitric oxide (NO) and nitrogen dioxide (NO<sub>2</sub>), expressed as equivalent molecular weight of NO<sub>2</sub>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(29)</num>
        <text>"Particulate matter (PM)" means any material, except water in uncombined form, that is or has been airborne, and exists as a liquid or a solid at standard conditions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30)</num>
        <text>"Particulate matter emissions" means all finely divided solid or liquid material, other than uncombined water, discharged into the ambient air.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30-1)</num>
        <text>"PM<sub>2.5</sub>" means particulate matter with an aerodynamic diameter less than or equal to a nominal 2.5 micrometers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30-2)</num>
        <text>"PM<sub>2.5</sub> emissions" means finely divided solid or liquid materials with an aerodynamic diameter less than or equal to a nominal 2.5 micrometers, discharged into the ambient air.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(31)</num>
        <text>"PM<sub>10</sub>" means particulate matter with an aerodynamic diameter less than or equal to a nominal 10 micrometers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(32)</num>
        <text>"PM<sub>10</sub> emissions" means finely divided solid or liquid materials with an aerodynamic diameter less than or equal to a nominal 10 micrometers, discharged into the ambient air.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(33)</num>
        <text>"Percent seasonal throughput" means percent of annual throughput conducted during each of the 4 seasonal periods (December—February, March—May, June—August, September—November).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(34)</num>
        <text>"Person" means any individual, group of individuals, firm, partnership, voluntary association, or private, public or municipal corporation, or agency, bureau, department or an instrumentality of federal, State, or local government responsible for the use of property.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(35)</num>
        <text>"Potential to emit" means the maximum capacity of a stationary source to discharge a pollutant under its physical and operational design. Any physical or operational limitation on the capacity of the source to emit a pollutant, including air pollution control equipment and restrictions on hours of operation or on the type or amount of material combusted, stored, or processed, shall be treated as part of its design if the limitation or the effect it would have on emissions is federally enforceable through a permit condition, compliance plan, or administrative or court order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(36)</num>
        <text>"Premises" means all the installations or other sources that are located on contiguous or adjacent properties and that are under the control of one person or under common control of a group of persons.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(37)</num>
        <text>"Prevention of Significant Deterioration (PSD) source" means any new or modified source subject to the provisions of 40 CFR §52.21, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(38)</num>
        <text>"Process weight" means the total weight of all materials introduced into any specific process which may cause emissions. Solid fuels charged will be considered as part of the process weight, but liquid and gaseous fuels and combustion air will not.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(39)</num>
        <text>"Process weight per hour" means the rate established as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For continuous or long-run steady-state operations, the total process weight for the entire period of continuous operation or for a typical portion of operation, divided by the number of hours of the period or portions of operation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For cyclical or batch operations, the total process weight for a period that covers a complete operation or an integral number of cycles, divided by the hours of actual process operation during the period; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>When the nature of any process or operation or the design of any equipment permits more than one interpretation of this definition, the interpretation that results in the minimum value for allowable emission shall apply.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(40)</num>
        <text>"Reasonably Available Control Technology (RACT)" means the lowest emissions limit that a particular source is capable of meeting by the application of control technology that is reasonably available considering technological and economic feasibility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(41)</num>
        <text>"Residual fuel oil" means that fuel oil that meets the specifications of the American Society for Testing and Materials for Numbers 4, 5, or 6 (bunker C) oils or crude oils when used as a fuel.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(42)</num>
        <text>"Secretary" means the Secretary of the Environment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(43)</num>
        <text>"Source" as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|2-101">Environment Article, §2-101(i), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, means any property, real or personal, or person contributing to air pollution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(44)</num>
        <text>"Stack or chimney" means any flue, conduit, or duct arranged to conduct emissions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(45)</num>
        <text>"Stack height" means the height of a stack measured from the ground elevation to the top of the stack, not including caps, nozzles, or other encumbrances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(46)</num>
        <text>"Standard conditions" means at a temperature of 77°F (25°C) and a pressure of <cite path="|29.92">29.92</cite> inches (760 mm) of mercury.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(47)</num>
        <text>"Standard industrial classification (SIC) code" means a series of codes devised by the federal Office of Management and Budget (OMB) to classify establishments according to the type of economic activity in which they are engaged.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(48)</num>
        <text>"True vapor pressure (TVP)" means the vapor pressure of a material at storage temperature, where storage temperature is the maximum monthly average temperature of the material or 77°F (25°C), whichever is the higher.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(49)</num>
        <text>"Typical ozone season day (TOSD)" means a day typical of that period of the year during which conditions for photochemical ozone formation are most favorable, which is generally during sustained periods of direct sunlight (that is, long days, little cloud cover) and warm temperatures.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(50)</num>
        <text>"Unconfined source" means an installation that causes emissions which are not enclosed in a stack, duct, hood, flue, or other conduit but which escape into the atmosphere through openings such as windows, vents or doors, ill fitting closures, or poorly maintained equipment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(51)</num>
        <text>"Vapor balance line" means any connection closed to the atmosphere between the vapor space of two storage containers that will allow the vapors to be displaced as the liquid is transferred from one tank to the other.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(52)</num>
        <text>"Vapor pressure" means the total equilibrium partial pressure or pressures for any given chemical or mixture at a given temperature.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(53)</num>
        <text>"Volatile organic compound (VOC)" means any organic compound which participates in atmospheric photochemical reactions, excluding those compounds which have been determined to have negligible photochemical reactivity by the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency and which are listed in 40 CFR §51.100(s), as amended.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Relationship of Provisions in this Subtitle.</heading>
    <text>Unless otherwise expressly provided in this subtitle, the provisions of this subtitle are cumulative and each provision applies to each applicable source or installation and to each person in control of the source or installation.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Delineation of Areas.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Area I means the western area of the State comprising the counties of Allegany, Garrett, and Washington.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Area II means the central area of the State composed of Frederick County.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Area III means the Baltimore metropolitan area of the State comprising Baltimore City and the counties of Anne Arundel, Baltimore, Carroll, Harford, and Howard.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Area IV means the Washington metropolitan area of the State comprising the counties of Montgomery and Prince George's.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Area V means the southern area of the State comprising the counties of Calvert, Charles, and St. Mary's.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Area VI means the eastern shore area of the State comprising the counties of Caroline, Cecil, Dorchester, Kent, Queen Anne's, Somerset, Talbot, Wicomico, and Worcester.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|11|01|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Testing and Monitoring.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Requirements for Testing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department may require any person to conduct or have conducted testing to determine compliance with this subtitle. The Department, at its option, may witness or conduct these tests. This testing will be done at a reasonable time, and all information gathered during a testing operation will be provided to both parties.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Compliance with this subtitle shall be determined by the test methods designated and described in <cite path="26|11|01|.04|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> and shall be applicable to both new and existing stationary emission sources. These test methods may be modified or adjusted by the Department to meet the requirements at certain types of sources, specific sampling conditions, and the need to incorporate advances and other new information relating to testing technology.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When the Department conducts or has these tests conducted, the person shall provide the sampling facilities, exclusive of instruments and sensing devices, that are necessary to determine the quantity of emissions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any registerable installation constructed after January 4, 1971, shall be provided with openings in the exhaust gas ductwork or in the stack or chimney as required by the test methods specified in <cite path="26|11|01|.04|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite> to enable the collection of samples of the effluent to the atmosphere from this installation. Upon request of the Department, the owner or operator of this installation shall provide appropriate scaffolding which meets OSHA standards as set forth in 29 CFR Chapter XVII Part 1910.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Requirements for Monitoring.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department or the control officer may require a person responsible for any installation to install, use, and maintain monitoring equipment or employ other methods as specified by the Department or the control officer to determine the quantity or quality, or both, of emissions discharged into the atmosphere and to maintain records and make reports on these emissions to the Department or the control officer in a manner and on a schedule approved by the Department or the control officer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department or the control officer, at reasonable times, shall have access to and be permitted to copy any records, inspect any monitoring equipment or methods required under this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Except when otherwise specified by the Department or the control officer, records required under this regulation shall be available for inspection by the Department and the control officer for a period of not less than 90 days.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>All records and reports submitted to the Department or the control officer required under this regulation shall be available for public inspection.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Emission Test Methods. The following test methods are incorporated by reference:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>40 CFR Part 60, Appendix A, as amended;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department's Technical Memorandum 91-01, "Test Methods and Equipment Specifications for Stationary Sources", January, 1991, as amended through Supplement 3 (October 1, 1997); and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For PM10 stack tests, the following EPA approved test methods shall be used:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Test Methods 201 A and 202 in 40 CFR Part 51, Appendix M, as amended;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Test Method 5 (40 CFR Part 60, Appendix A, as amended) and Test Method 202 in 40 CFR Part 51, Appendix M, as amended;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Test Method 5 (40 CFR Part 60, Appendix A, as amended) using front half and back half procedure;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>EPA Conditional Test Method 39 may be substituted for Test Method 202 in 40 CFR Part 51, Appendix M, as amended; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Alternative test methods may be used for PM10 if they are approved by the Department and the EPA.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|11|01|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Records and Information.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department may require a person who owns or operates an installation or source to establish and maintain records sufficient to provide the information necessary to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Assist the Department in the development of an implementation plan, air emissions standard, equipment performance standard, or material formulation standard;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Determine compliance with an air emissions standard, equipment performance standard, material formulation standard, or permit condition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Verify or update registration information; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Update Maryland's air emissions inventory.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person who is required pursuant to <cite path="26|11|01|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> to establish and maintain records shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maintain the necessary information in a format approved by the Department; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit written reports, when requested by the Department, summarizing the information in a format approved by the Department and on a schedule specified by the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Whenever a provision in this subtitle requires submission or reporting of test results, reports, or other information to the Department, unless otherwise specified, the information shall be submitted to:</text>
      <text class="center">Program Manager</text>
      <text class="center">Air Quality Compliance Program</text>
      <text class="center">Maryland Department of the Environment</text>
      <text class="center">1800 Washington Boulevard, Suite 715</text>
      <text class="center">Baltimore, Maryland 21230</text>
      <text class="center">410-537-4225</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Unless otherwise specified, all records, documentation or other information required by this subtitle, shall be maintained on-site and made available to the Department upon request.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|11|01|.05-1">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05-1</num>
    <heading>Emissions Statements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applicability. This regulation applies to a person who owns or operates any installation, source, or premises that is located in:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Baltimore City, or in Anne Arundel, Baltimore, Calvert, Carroll, Cecil, Charles, Frederick, Harford, Howard, Kent, Montgomery, Prince George's or Queen Anne's counties, and has total actual emissions of either VOC or NO<sub>x</sub> from all installations and sources on a premises of 25 tons or more during a calendar year;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Allegany, Caroline, Dorchester, Garrett, St. Mary's, Somerset, Talbot, Washington, Wicomico, or Worcester counties, and has total actual emissions of either VOC or NO<sub>x</sub> from all installations and sources on a premises of 50 tons or more of VOC or 100 tons or more of NOx during a calendar year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>General Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>By April 1 of each year, beginning with April 1, 1993, a person subject to this regulation shall submit to the Department an emissions statement for the previous calendar year that meets the requirements of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person submitting an emissions statement shall certify that the information in the emissions statement is accurate to the person's best knowledge. The certifying individual shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Familiar with each installation and source for which the statement is submitted; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Responsible for the accuracy of the statement.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If actual emissions from a source or premises for any year after calendar year 1992 equal or exceed the applicable emission levels prescribed in §A(1) or (2) of this regulation, an emissions statement is required for that year and each following year unless the source demonstrates, to the satisfaction of the Department, that emissions have been permanently reduced and the source no longer has the potential to emit emissions that exceed the applicable levels.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Emissions Statement Content. Emissions statements required by <cite path="26|11|01|.05-1|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> shall be organized by premises, submitted on a form obtained from the Department, and include the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Identification of each installation or source at the premises that discharges VOC or NO<sub>x</sub>, and the actual daily and annual emissions from each installation or source;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An explanation of the method used to determine emissions from each installation or source and operating schedules and production data that were used to determine emissions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Beginning with the emissions statement for calendar year 1993, an explanation for any increases or decreases in emissions for each installation or source if reported emissions differ from the emissions reported in the previous year's emissions statement; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Other relevant information as required by the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Circumvention.</heading>
    <text>A person may not install or use any article, machine, equipment or other contrivance, the use of which, without resulting in a reduction in the total weight of emissions, conceals or dilutes an emission which would otherwise constitute a violation of any applicable air pollution control regulation.</text>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|11|01|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Malfunctions and Other Temporary Increases of Emissions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Excess emissions" means an emission rate which exceeds any applicable emission standard set forth in this subtitle unless the emission rate is in compliance with an approved plan for compliance, departmental order, consent order, or condition of a permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Malfunction" means sudden and unavoidable failure of an installation to operate in a normal and usual manner. Failures that are caused entirely or in part by inadequate design, poor maintenance, careless operation, preventable upset conditions, or preventable equipment breakdown may not be considered malfunctions.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Unless otherwise required by law, the Department will consider any period of excess emissions to be a violation of law, regardless of the cause. Information submitted pursuant to §§C and D of this regulation will be considered, however, in determining whether the excess emissions are the result of a malfunction and whether to commence an administrative or judicial proceeding authorized by State and federal law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Report of Excess Emissions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In the case of any occurrence of excess emissions, expected to last or actually lasting for 1 hour or more, from any installation required by <cite path="26.11.02.13">COMAR 26.11.02.13</cite> to obtain a State permit to operate, the owner or operator shall report the onset and shall report the termination of the occurrence to the Department by telephone.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Telephone reports of excess emissions shall include the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The identity of the installation and the person reporting;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The nature or characteristics of the emissions (for example, hydrocarbons, fluorides);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The time of occurrence of the onset of the excess emissions and the actual or expected duration of the occurrence; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The actual or probable cause of the excess emissions.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Written Report of Excess Emissions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When requested by the Department, the owner or operator of any installation from which excess emissions have occurred shall submit a written report to the Department within 10 days of receiving the request.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The report shall set forth the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The identity of the installation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The nature or characteristics of the emissions (for example, hydrocarbon, fluorides);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The time of occurrence of the onset of the excess emissions and the duration of the occurrence;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The actual or estimated quantity of excess emissions during the occurrence, and operating data and calculations used in determining the quantity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The actual or probable cause of the occurrence and whether the owner or operator contends that the cause is a malfunction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The method of correcting the cause of the excess emissions and minimizing the duration and magnitude of the occurrence, including, if applicable, the use of overtime or contractual assistance to make repairs as expeditiously as possible;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>A listing of all occurrences of excess emissions from the installation, the duration of each occurrence, and the cause of each occurrence for the last 1-year period or since the effective date of this regulation, whichever is less;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>A copy of the maintenance plan for the installation and documentation that the plan is appropriate for the installation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Documentation that the maintenance plan was being carried out before the occurrence of excess emissions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>The steps taken or planned to prevent the reoccurrence of the excess emissions; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Any other information requested by the Department which is relevant to the occurrence of excess emissions or a claim by the owner or operator that the excess emissions were the result of a malfunction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding any provisions to §§A—D, of this regulation, a decision by the Department not to commence enforcement proceedings for an occurrence of excess emissions is not intended to preclude the Department from considering all past periods of excess emissions in determining whether to revoke or suspend a current operating permit or not to issue an operating permit for a future period of time.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Department may exempt the owner or operator of any installation from the reporting requirements of §C, of this regulation, if it determines that other information submitted to the Department meets the requirements of <cite path="26|11|01|.07|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, or the information is of insignificant use to the Department.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Determination of Ground Level Concentrations — Acceptable Techniques.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Major modification" means any modification as defined in 40 CFR Parts 51 and 52, 1985 edition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"State Implementation Plan" means the plan required by the Federal Clean Air Act, 42 U.S.C §7410, which the State adopts and submits to the United States Environmental Protection Agency showing attainment and maintenance of National Ambient Air Quality Standards.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Unacceptable dispersion technique" means any dispersion technique as defined in 40 CFR Part 51, 1985 edition, as amended, 50 FR 27906-27907 (July 8, 1985: Stack Height Regulation).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Exemptions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>This regulation does not apply to any stack height in existence or dispersion technique implemented on or before December 31, 1970, except when a source using a stack or dispersion technique undergoes a major modification after December 31, 1970.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>This regulation does not apply to the calculation of ground level concentrations of toxic air pollutants for the purpose of demonstrating compliance with <cite path="26.11.15.06">COMAR 26.11.15.06</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Dispersion Technique. A person may not use an unacceptable dispersion technique to determine the ground level concentrations of air pollutants discharged from a source in order to obtain:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An approval or permit under this subtitle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A revision to the State Implementation Plan; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A Certificate of Public Convenience and Necessity under Article 78, §§54A and B, or H, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Vapor Pressure of Gasoline.</heading>
    <text>See Figure 1.</text>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|11|01|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Continuous Opacity Monitoring Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applicability and Exceptions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The provisions of this regulation apply to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Fuel burning equipment burning coal, fuel oil, tars, or waste combustible fluid at any time and that has a rated heat input capacity of 250 million Btu per hour or greater;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Fuel burning equipment burning coal with a rated heat input capacity of 100 million Btu per hour or greater but less than 250 million Btu per hour and was constructed on or before June 19, 1984;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A cement kiln;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A fluidized bed combustor of any size; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A municipal waste combustor with a burning capacity of 35 tons or greater per day.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The owner or operator of an installation subject to this regulation may also be subject to the requirements of 40 CFR Parts 60 and 75, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>This regulation does not apply to fuel burning equipment that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Burns only distillate fuel oil or a mixture of gas and distillate fuel oil;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is able to comply with the applicable particulate matter and opacity emission limitations without using particulate matter control equipment; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has never been found in a final order to be in violation of any visible emissions standard.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The owner or operator of fuel burning equipment subject to this regulation may, with approval by the Department, discontinue use of a COM only in accordance with the provisions in <cite path="26.11.09.05|C.">COMAR 26.11.09.05C</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The owner or operator of a cement manufacturing installation may discontinue use of a COM when a PM CPMS is installed and operated in accordance with the requirements of <cite path="|26.11.30">COMAR 26.11.30</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Sources may request for approval by the Department and EPA an alternate limit for specific operating conditions in which the technological limitations of the control equipment adversely affects the ability of the source to comply with visible emissions limits by following the recommendations at 80 FR 33980. The alternate limit shall be submitted to EPA as a SIP revision and included in 40 CFR Part 52 Subpart V 52.1070(d) for Maryland Source Specific SIP revisions.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>General Requirements for COMs.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The owner or operator of an installation subject to this regulation shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Install and continuously operate a COM that complies with a plan approved by the Department and EPA in accordance with <cite path="26|11|01|.10|B.|(1)|(b)">§B(1)(b) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Before installing a COM, submit to the Department for approval, a plan containing the COM design specifications, proposed location, and a description of a proposed alternative measurement method consisting of a schedule for utilizing the EPA Reference Method 9 observational procedures.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department shall submit the plan to EPA for review and approval.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A COM shall comply with the applicable requirements in 40 CFR Part 51, Appendix P, as amended, which is incorporated by reference.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The owner or operator of fuel burning equipment that is required by this regulation to install and operate a COM is subject to the provisions in <cite path="26.11.09.05">COMAR 26.11.09.05</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The owner or operator of a cement kiln or clinker cooler that is operating a COM is subject to the following requirements.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The owner or operator of a cement kiln or clinker cooler may not cause or permit the discharge of emissions which exceed the visibility standards in <cite path="26.11.30.05|B.">COMAR 26.11.30.05B</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The visibility standards in <cite path="26.11.30.05|B.|(1)">COMAR 26.11.30.05B(1)</cite> and (2) do not apply to emissions as specified in <cite path="26.11.06.02|A.|(2)">COMAR 26.11.06.02A(2)</cite> during EPA reference Method 9 observations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For the purpose of demonstrating compliance with <cite path="26.11.30.05|B.|(2)">COMAR 26.11.30.05B(2)</cite> when using a COM, emissions that are visible to a human observer are those that are equal to or greater than 10 percent opacity.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>For the owner or operator of a cement kiln or clinker cooler that is operating a COM, compliance with visible emission standards is achieved if visible emissions do not exceed the applicable visible emission limitations in <cite path="26.11.30.05|B.|(1)">26.11.30.05B(1)</cite> or (2) as applicable.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Notwithstanding the requirements in §B(5)(a)—(d) of this regulation, the Department may determine compliance and non-compliance with the visible emission limitations by performing EPA reference Method 9 observations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The owner or operator of a cement kiln or clinker cooler that is operating a COM shall meet the quality assurance requirements under <cite path="|26.11.31">COMAR 26.11.31</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The owner or operator of a municipal waste combustor that is required to install and operate a COM is subject to the following requirements.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The owner or operator of a municipal waste combustor may not cause or permit the discharge of emissions which exceed the visibility standards in <cite path="26.11.08.04">COMAR 26.11.08.04</cite> as determined by EPA reference Method 9 observations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For the purpose of demonstrating compliance with <cite path="26.11.08.04">COMAR 26.11.08.04</cite> when using a COM, emissions that are visible to a human observer are those that are equal to or greater than 10 percent opacity.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For the owner or operator of a municipal waste combustor that is required to install and operate a COM, compliance with visible emission standards is achieved if visible emissions do not exceed 10 percent opacity for a 6-minute block average during the unit's operating time.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Notwithstanding the requirements in §B(6)(a)—(c) of this regulation, the Department may determine compliance and non-compliance with the visible emission limitations by performing EPA reference Method 9 observations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The owner or operator of a municipal waste combustor that is operating a COM shall meet the quality assurance requirements under <cite path="|26.11.31">COMAR 26.11.31</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Certification and Quality Assurance Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All certification testing, including certification performance tests and audits, shall be performed in accordance with 40 CFR Part 60, Appendix B, as amended, which is incorporated by reference.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For fuel burning equipment subject to the federal Acid Rain Program, all certification testing, including certification performance tests and audits, shall be performed in accordance with 40 CFR Part 75, Appendix A, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Certification testing shall be repeated when the Department determines that the data are invalid because of component replacement or other conditions that affect the accuracy of generated data.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The owner or operator that is required to perform a certification performance test shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least 60 days before the test, submit a test protocol to the Department for review and approval;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Schedule the test at a reasonable time and notify the Department at least 10 days before the test is to be conducted; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Submit the test results to the Department not later than 45 days after the completion of the test.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The owner or operator of fuel-burning equipment required to install and operate a COM shall meet the quality assurance procedures contained in <cite path="|26.11.31">COMAR 26.11.31</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Record Keeping and Reporting Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>System Downtime Reporting Requirements.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All COM downtime that lasts or is expected to last more than 24 hours shall be reported to the Department by telephone before 10 a.m. of the first regular business day following the first day on which downtime occurs.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The COM downtime report shall include the reason, if known, for the breakdown and the estimated period of time that the COM will be down. The owner or operator shall notify the Department by telephone when the COM has met performance specifications for accuracy, reliability, and durability of acceptable monitoring systems, as provided in 40 CFR Part 51 Appendix P, and is producing data.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Except as otherwise approved by the Department and the EPA, a COM shall operate in compliance with the requirements of <cite path="26|11|01|.10|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite> and collect data for at least 95 percent of the source's operating time during any calendar quarter. The alternative measurement plan required in <cite path="26|11|01|.10|B.|(1)|(b)">§B(1)(b) of this regulation</cite> shall be used at all times when the COM fails to conform to performance standards required by <cite path="26|11|01|.10|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite> during data collection.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Data Reporting Requirements.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A COM shall automatically reduce all data to six-minute block averages calculated from 24 or more equally spaced data points.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All COM data shall be reported in a format approved by the Department.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A quarterly summary report shall be submitted to the Department not later than 30 days following each calendar quarter. The report shall be in a format approved by the Department, and shall include the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The cause, time periods, and the opacity of all emissions which exceed the applicable quarterly, daily and hourly emission standards as provided in <cite path="26.11.09.05|A.|(4)">COMAR 26.11.09.05A(4)</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The COM and installation downtimes, including the time and date of the beginning and end of each downtime period, and whether the downtime was scheduled;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The cause of all COM downtime;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The total operating time for the quarter, and the total time and percent of the operating time during the quarter that excess emissions occurred, and the percentage of COM downtime, during the calendar quarter;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Quarterly quality assurance activities;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Daily calibration activities that include reference values, actual values, absolute or percent of span differences, and drift status;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Other information that the Department determines is necessary to evaluate the data or to ensure that compliance is achieved.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>All information required by this regulation to be maintained or reported to the Department shall be retained and made available for review by the Department for a minimum of 5 years from the time the report is submitted.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|11|01|.11">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Continuous Emission Monitoring Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applicability and Exemptions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The provisions of this regulation apply to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Fuel-burning equipment burning coal that has a rated heat input capacity of 100 million Btu per hour or greater;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Municipal waste combustors with a burning capacity of 35 tons or greater per day;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Fluidized bed combustors; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Kraft pulp mills.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An owner or operator that is required to install a CEM under any federal requirement is also subject to all of the provisions of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>General Requirements for CEMs.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An owner or operator subject to this regulation shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Before installing a CEM, submit to the Department, for approval by the Department and EPA, a plan containing the CEM design specifications, proposed location, and a description of a proposed alternative measurement method; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Install and operate a CEM in accordance with the plan approved by the Department and EPA under the provisions of <cite path="26|11|01|.11|B.|(1)|(a)">§B(1)(a) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The owner or operator of fuel-burning equipment burning coal, with a heat input capacity of 100 million Btu per hour or greater, shall install CEMs to measure and record sulfur dioxide, nitrogen oxide, either oxygen or carbon dioxide, and flow.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The owner or operator of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A municipal waste combustor (MWC) shall install CEMs to measure and record SO<sub>x</sub>, NO<sub>x</sub>, carbon monoxide emissions and either CO<sub>2</sub> or oxygen;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A Kraft pulp mill shall install a CEM to measure and record SO<sub>2</sub> and flow; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A fluidized bed combustor of any size shall install CEMs to measure and record sulfur dioxide, nitrogen oxide and either oxygen or carbon dioxide.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Except as otherwise approved by the Department, if the owner or operator is unable to obtain emissions data from CEMs because of a malfunction of the CEM for more than 2 hours in duration, the owner or operator shall use the alternative measurement method approved by the Department and EPA.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Quality Assurance for CEMs. A CEM used to monitor a gas concentration shall meet the quality assurance criteria of 40 CFR Part 60, Appendix F, as amended, which is incorporated by reference, or, if applicable, the quality assurance criteria of 40 CFR Part 75, Appendix B, as amended.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Monitoring and Determining Compliance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>General. A CEM required by this regulation is the primary method used by the Department to determine compliance or non-compliance with the applicable emission standards established in any permit or approval, administrative or court order, Certificate of Public Convenience and Necessity, or regulation in this subtitle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Data Reduction. A CEM used to monitor a gas concentration shall record not less than four equally spaced data points per hour and automatically reduce data in terms of averaging times consistent with the applicable emission standard.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Record Keeping and Reporting Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>CEM System Downtime Reporting Requirements.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All CEM system downtime that lasts or is expected to last more than 24 hours shall be reported to the Department by telephone before 10 a.m. of the first regular business day following the breakdown.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The system breakdown report required by <cite path="26|11|01|.11|E.|(1)|(a)">§E(1)(a) of this regulation</cite> shall include the reason, if known, for the breakdown and the estimated period of time that the CEM will be down. The owner or operator of the CEM shall notify the Department by telephone when an out-of-service CEM is back in operation and producing data that has met performance specifications for accuracy, reliability, and durability of acceptable monitoring systems, as provided in <cite path="|26.11.31">COMAR 26.11.31</cite>, and is producing data.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>CEM Data Reporting Requirements.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All test results shall be reported in a format approved by the Department.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Certification testing shall be repeated when the Department determines that the CEM data may not meet performance specifications because of component replacement or other conditions that affect the quality of generated data.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A quarterly summary report shall be submitted to the Department not later than 30 days following each calendar quarter. The report shall be in a format approved by the Department, and shall include the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The cause, time periods, and magnitude of all emissions which exceed the applicable emission standards;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The source downtime including the time and date of the beginning and end of each downtime period and whether the source downtime was planned or unplanned;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The time periods and cause of all CEM downtime including records of any repairs, adjustments, or maintenance that may affect the ability of the CEM to meet performance specifications of emission data;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Quarterly totals of excess emissions, installation downtime, and CEM downtime during the calendar quarter;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Quarterly quality assurance activities;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Daily calibration activities that include reference values, actual values, absolute or percent of span differences, and drift status; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Other information required by the Department that is determined to be necessary to evaluate the data, to ensure that compliance is achieved, or to determine the applicability of this regulation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>All information required by this regulation to be reported to the Department shall be retained and made available for review by the Department for a minimum of 2 years from the time the report is submitted.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-07-18">Effective date: July 18, 1980 (7:12 Md. R. 1148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1981-10-10">Regulation .01A-1, F-1 adopted effective October 10, 1981 (8:18 Md. R. 1480)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1981-07-10">Regulation .01H amended effective July 10, 1981 (8:11 Md. R. 974)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-01-05">Regulation .01I amended effective June 8, 1981 (8:9 Md. R. 800); July 2, 1985 (12:11 Md. R. 1049); October 14, 1985 (12:18 Md. R. 1766); August 11, 1986 (13:13 Md. R. 1492); January 5, 1988 (14:24 Md. R. 2555)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-01-05">Regulation .01K amended effective June 8, 1981 (8:9 Md. R. 800); August 16, 1983 (10:14 Md. R. 1263); December 3, 1984 (11:22 Md. R. 1899); October 14, 1985 (12:18 Md. R. 1766); August 11, 1986 (13:13 Md. R. 1492); January 5, 1988 (14:24 Md. R. 2555)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1983-08-16">Regulation .01O-1, V-1, and Y adopted effective August 16, 1983 (10:14 Md. R. 1262)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-01-05">Regulation .01O-1 amended effective January 5, 1988 (14:24 Md. R. 2555)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-08-10">Regulation .01V-1 and Y amended, and X-1 adopted effective August 10, 1987 (14:14 Md. R. 1572)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1983-08-16">Regulation .01X amended effective July 10, 1981 (8:11 Md. R. 974); August 16, 1983 (10:14 Md. R. 1262)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1985-07-02">Regulation .04C amended effective February 10, 1984 (10:26 Md. R. 2341); July 2, 1985 (12:11 Md. R. 1049)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1984-02-10">Regulation .04D repealed and .05 amended effective February 10, 1984 (10:26 Md. R. 2341)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1984-12-03">Regulation .08 repealed effective December 3, 1984 (11:22 Md. R. 1899)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1987-03-24">Regulation .08 adopted effective March 24, 1987 (14:4 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1983-08-16">Figure 1 moved to <cite path="|10.18.01">COMAR 10.18.01</cite> from <cite path="|10.18.06">COMAR 10.18.06</cite> effective August 16, 1983 (10:14 Md. R. 1262); recodified as Regulation .09</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-07-18">On July 18, 1980, Subtitle 18 Air Quality was reorganized and recodified from 7 chapters to 22 chapters. Citation tables listing the codification changes appear at 7:5 Md. R. 501. The administrative histories of the original 7 chapters are given on the following pages.</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" discontinuity="true">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|10.18.01">COMAR 10.18.01</cite> to <cite path="|26.11.01">COMAR 26.11.01</cite></annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-12-07">Regulation .01 amended effective December 7, 1992 (19:24 Md. R. 2128)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Regulation .01A—Y recodified to Regulation .01A—DD</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-05-08">Regulation .01A and A-1 recodified to Regulation .01A-1 and A-2, respectively, and new Regulation .01A and A-3 adopted effective May 8, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 688)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-09-27">Regulation .01A-1 adopted effective September 27, 1988 (15:18 Md. R. 2148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-07-22">Regulation .01C-1 adopted effective July 22, 1991 (18:13 Md. R. 1484)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1989-06-20">Regulation .01E amended effective June 20, 1989 (16:9 Md. R. 995)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-07-22">Regulation .01E-1, F-1, and G-1 adopted effective July 22, 1991 (18:13 Md. R. 1484)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1993-04-26">Regulation .01J amended effective April 26, 1993 (20:8 Md. R. 724)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-17">Regulation .01K, M amended effective September 26, 1988 (15:17 Md. R. 2049); March 31, 1991 (18:4 Md. R. 450); February 17, 1992 (19:3 Md. R. 306)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1993-04-26">Regulation .01L amended effective March 21, 1989 (16:3 Md. R. 347); May 8, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 688); April 26, 1993 (20:8 Md. R. 724)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1993-04-26">Regulation .01M-1 adopted effective April 26, 1993 (20:8 Md. R. 724)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-07-22">Regulation .01O-1 adopted effective July 22, 1991 (18:13 Md. R. 1484)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1989-03-21">Regulation .01P-1, P-2, P-3 adopted effective March 21, 1989 (16:3 Md. R. 347)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-05-08">Regulation .01Q-1 and Q-2 adopted effective May 8, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 688)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-17">Regulation .01R amended effective March 21, 1989 (16:3 Md. R. 347); March 31, 1991 (18:4 Md. R. 450); February 17, 1992 (19:3 Md. R. 306)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-05-08">Regulation .01U amended effective May 8, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 688)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-07-22">Regulation .01U-1 adopted effective July 22, 1991 (18:13 Md. R. 1484)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-09-27">Regulation .01X-1 adopted effective September 27, 1988 (15:18 Md. R. 2148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-17">Regulation .01DD amended effective May 8, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 688); August 19, 1991 (18:16 Md. R. 1813); February 17, 1992 (19:3 Md. R. 306)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" discontinuity="true" effective="2010-09-20">Regulation .01B amended effective June 20, 1994 (21:12 Md. R. 1063 and 21:12 Md. R. 1064); May 8, 1995 (22:9 Md. R. 647); May 22, 1995 (22:10 Md. R. 708); June 30, 1997 (24:13 Md. R. 932); September 22, 1997 (24:19 Md. R. 1343); October 5, 1998 (25:20 Md. R. 1533); March 22, 1999 (26:6 Md. R. 487); October 16, 2000 (27:20 Md. R. 1842); December 10, 2001 (28:24 Md. R. 2130); November 24, 2003 (30:23 Md. R. 1653); September 12, 2005 (32:18 Md. R. 1521); October 8, 2007 (34:20 Md. R. 1741); June 16, 2008 (35:12 Md. R. 1121); July 16, 2009 (36:14 Md. R. 985); May 17, 2010 (37:10 Md. R. 724); July 26, 2010 (37:15 Md. R. 1000); September 20, 2010 (37:19 Md. R. 1285)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2011-05-16">Regulation .01B amended as an emergency provision effective January 2, 2011 (38:4 Md. R. 263); amended permanently effective May 16, 2011 (38:10 Md. R. 617)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2018-12-06">Regulation .01B amended effective March 5, 2012 (39:4 Md. R. 339 - two actions); July 8, 2013 (40:13 Md. R. 1076 - two actions); February 15, 2016 (43:3 Md. R. 273); May 9, 2016 (43:9 Md. R. 531); April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 422); December 6, 2018 (45:24 Md. R. 1163)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2007-10-08">Regulation .01C amended effective June 30, 1997 (24:13 Md. R. 932); October 16, 2000 (27:20 Md. R. 1842); December 10, 2001 (28:24 Md. R. 2130); October 8, 2007 (34:20 Md. R. 1741)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2007-10-08">Regulation .01D amended effective December 10, 2001 (28:24 Md. R. 2130); November 24, 2003 (30:23 Md. R. 1653); September 12, 2005 (32:18 Md. R. 1521); October 8, 2007 (34:20 Md. R. 1741)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2012-03-05">Regulation .04C amended effective July 16, 1990 (17:11 Md. R. 1344); August 19, 1991 (18:16 Md. R. 1813); February 17, 1992 (19:3 Md. R. 306); February 15, 1993 (20:3 Md. R. 260); November 2, 1998 (25:22 Md. R. 1653); June 19, 2006 (33:12 Md. R. 999); March 5, 2012 (39:4 Md. R. 339)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-12-10">Regulation .05 amended effective June 30, 1997 (24:13 Md. R. 932); December 10, 2001 (28:24 Md. R. 2130)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-17">Regulation .05C, D adopted effective May 17, 2010 (37:10 Md. R. 724)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-12-07">Regulation .05-1 adopted effective December 7, 1992 (19:24 Md. R. 2128)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-05-08">Regulation .07C amended effective May 8, 1995 (22:9 Md. R. 648)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1988-09-27">Regulation .08A, B amended effective September 27, 1988 (15:18 Md. R. 2148)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-07-22">Regulation .10 adopted effective July 22, 1991 (18:13 Md. R. 1484)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1997-09-22">Regulation .10 amended effective September 22, 1997 (24:19 Md. R. 1343)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-17">Regulation .10 repealed and new Regulation .10 adopted effective May 17, 2010 (37:10 Md. R. 724)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-02-15">Regulation .10A, B amended effective February 15, 2016 (43:3 Md. R. 273)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2011-08-22">Regulation .10A, C amended effective August 22, 2011 (38:17 Md. R. 1014)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2015-07-20">Regulation .10A, F amended effective July 20, 2015 (42:14 Md. R. 884)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2011-08-22">Regulation .10F amended effective August 22, 2011 (38:17 Md. R. 1014)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-02-15">Regulation .10F repealed effective February 15, 2016 (43:3 Md. R. 273)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-07-22">Regulation .11 adopted effective July 22, 1991 (18:13 Md. R. 1484)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1997-09-22">Regulation .11 amended effective April 27, 1992 (19:8 Md. R. 806); September 22, 1997 (24:19 Md. R. 1343)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-17">Regulation .11 repealed and new Regulation .11 adopted effective May 17, 2010 (37:10 Md. R. 724)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2011-08-22">Regulation .11A, B amended effective August 22, 2011 (38:17 Md. R. 1014)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2011-08-22">Regulation .11D amended effective August 22, 2011 (38:17 Md. R. 1014)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2011-08-22">Regulation .11E adopted effective August 22, 2011 (38:17 Md. R. 1014)</annotation>
  </annotations>
  <text>Administrative History of <cite path="|10.18.01">COMAR 10.18.01</cite> before June 13, 1980</text>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" discontinuity="true" effective="1968-05-28">Effective date: May 28, 1968</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1973-12-02">Amended effective January 28, 1969; September 29, 1970; January 4, 1971; January 17, 1972; May 12, 1973; December 2, 1973</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-12-16">Regulation .01AA adopted effective December 16, 1977 (4:26 Md. R. 2024)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-01-02">Regulation  .01Y, AA amended effective January 2, 1980 (6:23 Md. R. 1839)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-06-25">Regulation .01W, DD, SS adopted effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-03-30">Regulations .01P, WW, .03B amended effective March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-06-28">Regulation .01F, G, X, XX adopted effective June 28, 1977 (4:11 Md. R. 866)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1978-09-10">Regulation .01ZZ adopted effective September 10, 1978 (5:18 Md. R. 1387)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-01-02">Regulation .01AAA, BBB adopted effective January 2, 1980 (6:23 Md. R. 1839)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-12-10">Regulations .03B and .04 amended effective December 10, 1979 (6:21 Md. R. 1708)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-06-25">Regulation .04 adopted effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-01-02">Regulation .04A, G amended effective January 2, 1979 (5:23 Md. R. 1740)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1978-08-21">Regulation .04I amended effective August 21, 1978 (5:14 Md. R. 1137)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-03-30">Regulations .04F, .05E, .06A amended effective March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-01-02">Regulation .11 amended effective January 2, 1980 (6:23 Md. R. 1839)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-06-25">Regulation .11B, C, H, I amended effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-03-30">Regulation .11G, H, K amended effective March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-12-16">Regulation .11G, J, K amended effective December 16, 1977 (4:26 Md. R. 2024)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-01-02">Regulation .11H amended effective January 2, 1979 (5:23 Md. R. 1740)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1978-09-10">Regulation .11J amended effective September 10, 1978 (5:18 Md. R. 1387)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-01-02">Regulation .13 adopted effective September 10, 1978 (5:18 Md. R. 1387); repealed effective January 2, 1980 (6:23 Md. R. 1839)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-07-18">Chapter repealed effective July 18, 1980 (7:12 Md. R. 1148)</annotation>
  </annotations>
  <text>Administrative History of <cite path="|10.18.02">COMAR 10.18.02</cite>, <cite path="|10.18.03">10.18.03</cite>, <cite path="|10.18.06">10.18.06</cite>, and <cite path="|10.18.07">10.18.07</cite> before June 13, 1980</text>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1968-05-28">Effective date: May 28, 1968</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1973-12-02">Amended effective January 28, 1969; January 17, 1972; May 12, 1972; December 2, 1973</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-03-30">Regulation .01D amended effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015) and March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-06-25">Regulation .02A—D amended effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-06-25">Regulation .02E, F adopted effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-03-30">Regulation .02F amended effective March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-12-10">Regulations .02 and .03 amended effective December 10, 1979 (6:21 Md. R. 1708)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-03-30">Regulation .03A—E amended effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015) and March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-06-25">Regulation .04A—G amended effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-12-10">Regulation .04B, D, G, I amended effective December 10, 1979 (6:21 Md. R. 1708)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-06-25">Regulation .04I, J adopted effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-03-30">Regulation .04B, C, F, G, H, I amended effective March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-01-02">Regulation .05 adopted effective December 16, 1977 (4:26 Md. R. 2024); amended effective January 2, 1980 (6:23 Md. R. 1839)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-12-10">Regulation .06D amended effective December 10, 1979 (6:21 Md. R. 1708)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-06-25">Regulation .06D, E amended effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-03-30">Regulations .06D, .07A, B amended effective March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-01-02">Regulation .07 repealed and new Regulation .07 adopted effective September 10, 1978 (5:18 Md. R. 1387); amended effective January 2, 1980 (6:23 Md. R. 1839)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-07-18">Chapter repealed effective July 18, 1980 (7:12 Md. R. 1148)</annotation>
  </annotations>
  <text>Administrative History of <cite path="|10.18.04">COMAR 10.18.04</cite> before June 13, 1980</text>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1968-05-28">Effective date: May 28, 1968</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1974-02-12">Amended effective January 28, 1969; September 29, 1970; February 21, 1971; January 17, 1972; May 12, 1972; December 2, 1973; February 12, 1974</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-03-30">Regulation .01B, D amended effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015) and March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-01-02">Regulation .02B amended effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015) and January 2, 1979 (5:23 Md. R. 1740)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-06-25">Regulation .02C, D adopted effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-03-30">Regulation .02D amended effective March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-06-28">Regulation .02B, E amended effective June 28, 1977 (4:11 Md. R. 866)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-01-02">Regulation .03A amended effective January 2, 1979 (5:23 Md. R. 1740)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-06-25">Regulation .03A—D amended effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-03-30">Regulation .03A—C, E amended effective March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-06-28">Regulation .03B, E amended effective June 28, 1977 (4:11 Md. R. 866)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-06-28">Regulation .03G adopted effective June 28, 1977 (4:11 Md. R. 866)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-06-25">Regulation .04B—G, J amended effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-06-28">Regulation .04B amended effective June 28, 1977 (4:11 Md. R. 866)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-12-10">Regulation .04B, G amended effective December 10, 1979 (6:21 Md. R. 1708)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-03-30">Regulation .04C, F—J amended effective March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-03-31">Regulation .04D amended effective March 31, 1980 (7:4 Md. R. 347)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-01-02">Regulation .04I amended effective January 2, 1979 (5:23 Md. R. 1740)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-01-02">Regulation .04J amended effective January 2, 1980 (6:23 Md. R. 1839)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-06-25">Regulation .04K adopted effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-01-02">Regulation .05 adopted effective December 16, 1977 (4:26 Md. R. 2024); amended effective January 2, 1980 (6:23 Md. R. 1839)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-06-25">Regulation .06C, E, F, G amended effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-03-30">Regulation .06C, E, G amended effective March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-01-02">Regulation .06G, H amended effective January 2, 1980 (6:23 Md. R. 1839)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-01-02">Regulation .07 adopted effective September 10, 1978 (5:18 Md. R. 1387); amended effective January 2, 1980 (6:23 Md. R. 1839)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-07-18">Chapter repealed effective July 18, 1980 (7:12 Md. R. 1148)</annotation>
  </annotations>
  <text>Administrative History of <cite path="|10.18.05">COMAR 10.18.05</cite> before June 13, 1980</text>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1968-05-28">Effective date: May 28, 1968</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1974-02-12">Amended effective March 24, 1970; January 4, 1971; January 17, 1972; May 12, 1972; December 2, 1973; February 12, 1974</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-03-30">Regulation .01B, D amended effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015) and March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-01-02">Regulation .02B amended effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015); January 2, 1979 (5:23 Md. R. 1740)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-06-25">Regulation .02C, D adopted effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-03-30">Regulation .02D amended effective March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-06-28">Regulation .02E amended effective June 28, 1977 (4:11 Md. R. 866)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-01-02">Regulation .03A amended effective January 2, 1979 (5:23 Md. R. 1740)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-06-25">Regulation .03A—D amended effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-03-30">Regulation .03A—C, E amended effective March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-06-28">Regulation .03B, E amended effective June 28, 1977 (4:11 Md. R. 866)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-06-28">Regulation .03G adopted effective June 28, 1977 (4:11 Md. R. 866)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-06-25">Regulation .04B—G, J amended effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-06-28">Regulation .04B amended effective June 28, 1977 (4:11 Md. R. 816)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-12-10">Regulation .04B, G amended effective December 10, 1979 (6:21 Md. R. 1708)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-03-30">Regulation .04C, F—J amended effective March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-03-31">Regulation .04D amended effective March 31, 1980 (7:4 Md. R. 347)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1979-01-02">Regulation .04I amended effective January 2, 1979 (5:23 Md. R. 1740)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-01-02">Regulation .04J amended effective January 2, 1980 (6:23 Md. R. 1839)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-06-25">Regulation .04K adopted effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-01-02">Regulation .05 adopted effective December 16, 1977 (4:26 Md. R. 2024); amended effective January 2, 1980 (6:23 Md. R. 1839)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1975-06-25">Regulation .06C, E, F, G amended effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1977-03-30">Regulation .06C, E, G amended effective March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-01-02">Regulation .06G, H amended effective January 2, 1980 (6:23 Md. R. 1839)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-01-02">Regulation .07 adopted effective September 10, 1978 (5:18 Md. R. 1387); amended effective January 2, 1980 (6:23 Md. R. 1839)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1980-07-18">Chapter repealed effective July 18, 1980 (7:12 Md. R. 1148)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
