<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Type II School Vehicles — Construction Standards</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter is intended to provide minimum standards for the design, construction, and equipment of Type II school vehicles manufactured for sale in Maryland and is intended to enhance 49 CFR standards.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>When CFR standards conflict with Maryland standards, CFR standards shall be used to construct Maryland certified school vehicles.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Incorporation by Reference.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following documents are incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Documents Incorporated.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §393.65 All fuel systems, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §393.67 Liquid fuel tanks, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §393.77 Heaters, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.101 Controls and displays, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.102 Transmission shift position sequence, starter interlock, and transmission braking effect, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.103 Windshield defrosting and defogging systems, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.104 Windshield wiping and washing systems, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.105 Hydraulic and electric brake systems, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.108 Lamps, reflective devices, and associated equipment, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.111 Rearview mirrors, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.114 Theft protection and rollaway prevention, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.116 Motor vehicle brake fluids, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.119 New pneumatic tires for motor vehicles with a GVWR of more than 4,536 kilograms (10,000 pounds) and motorcycles, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.120 Tire selection and rims and motor home/recreation vehicle trailer load carrying capacity 49 CFR information for motor vehicles with a GVWR of more than 4,536 kilograms (10,000 pounds) , as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.131 School bus pedestrian safety devices, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.205 Glazing materials, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.208 Occupant crash protection, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.209 Seat belt assemblies, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.210 Seat belt assembly anchorages, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.217 Bus emergency exits and window retention and release, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.220 School bus rollover protection, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.221 School bus body joint strength, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.222 School bus passenger seating and crash protection, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.301 Fuel system integrity, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.302 Flammability of interior materials, as amended. Repeal effective January 1, 2014 pursuant to Chapter 453, Acts of 2011.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.303 Fuel system integrity of compressed natural gas vehicles, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>49 CFR §571.304 Compressed natural gas fuel container integrity, as amended.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Certification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A manufacturer, distributor, or dealer of Type II school vehicles that are to be sold or distributed in this State shall certify to the Administration that all vehicles they sell or distribute are in full compliance with the provisions of this chapter. The certification shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In a form prescribed by the Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Filed annually; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Filed before the introduction of a new model.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Supplemental certifications are required before new models are introduced during the current model year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Metal Certification Plate.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A stamped or embossed metal plate certifying that body construction is in compliance with the provisions of this chapter shall be posted by the body manufacturer in the area above the driver's seating position.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The metal certification plate shall be visible and, at a minimum, shall contain the body model number followed by "MD" and the manufacturer's name.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A tamper-proof, self-adhesive label with a clear surface that will not be damaged by moisture or cleaning solvents may be used in place of the metal plate. Upon return of the damaged or unreadable label, the manufacturer shall supply a new label to the owner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Bumpers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A front bumper shall be provided, and shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be painted black;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Extend to protect the outer edges of the fenders;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be of sufficient strength to permit pushing another vehicle of comparable weight without permanent deformation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Be located at a height of between 14 inches and 18 inches when measured from the bottom edge of the bumper to the level surface on which the unloaded bus stands.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A rear bumper shall be provided by the body manufacturer and it shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have at least a 7-inch face;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be at least 3/16 inch thick steel, or equivalent material;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be attached directly to the chassis frame with provisions for easy removal;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Be constructed so as to prevent hitching to or riding on it;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Be of sufficient strength to permit the vehicle to be pushed by another vehicle without permanent distortion;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Extend at least 1 inch beyond the rearmost part of the body surface measured at the floor line;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Be painted black; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Be located at a height of between 14 inches and 18 inches from the bottom edge to the level surface upon which the unloaded vehicle stands.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Brakes.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Braking systems may not allow the vehicle to be without operative brakes capable of stopping the vehicle when loaded to manufacturers gross vehicle weight at any legal road speed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Brake lines shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Protected from excessive heat and vibration by means of a heat shield, if necessary; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Installed to prevent chafing, cutting, or stretching.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Brake drums and rotors shall be permanently and plainly marked to clearly indicate, in legible cast or stamped legend, the maximum safe diameter of the drum or minimum safe thickness of the rotor beyond which it may not be used or machined, but shall be discarded.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Drive Train.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Axles.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The front axle and suspension shall be of sufficient capacity to support that portion of the load as would be imposed by the manufacturer's maximum gross vehicle weight rating.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The rear suspension assembly shall have a gross weight rating equal to that portion of the load as would be imposed by the manufacturer's maximum gross vehicle weight rating.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Drive Shaft. Each segment of the drive shaft shall be equipped with a suitable guard to prevent accident or injury in the event of its fracture or disconnection.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Electrical (Chassis Wiring).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Alternator. The alternator with rectifier shall have an operational rating capable of supplying sufficient electrical power to maintain a fully charged storage battery with all electrical equipment, except the horn, hydraulic lift, and engine starting motor, operating simultaneously while the vehicle is running normally.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Battery.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The battery shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be of sufficient capacity to supply all electrical requirements; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Have a minimum cold cranking capacity rating of 650 amperes measured at 0°F.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If equipped with a hydraulic lift, the manufacturer shall equip the vehicle with an appropriate heavy duty battery and alternator.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Exhaust System.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The exhaust system shall include the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Exhaust manifold and gaskets; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Piping leading from the flange of the exhaust manifold to and including the muffler or mufflers and exhaust pipes.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The exhaust system may not extend into the body and shall be attached to the chassis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Exhaust Pipes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall be of nonflexible 16-gauge steel. An Original Equipment Manufacture flexible pipe or its equivalent not longer than 24 inches in length may be used at the front of the system at or near the turbocharger;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall exit:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At the rear of the bus on either the left or right side of the emergency door, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Behind the rear wheel of the bus;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>May not exit under the fuel filler; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>May not exit through or be attached to the bumper.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The complete exhaust system shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Tight and free from leaks; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Properly insulated from electrical wiring or any combustible part of the bus.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The complete exhaust system may not pass within 12 inches of the gasoline fuel tank or its connections unless a suitable heat baffle is installed between the exhaust system and gasoline fuel tank. A shield is not required between a diesel tank and exhaust.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The exhaust system noise level may not exceed the levels in <cite path="11.14.07.08">COMAR 11.14.07.08</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The manufacturer shall provide the proper size exhaust pipes for the vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Replacement pipes shall be of the same diameter as the pipes provided by the manufacturer.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Frame.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The chassis frame, for a body on chassis type vehicles, shall extend to the rear edge of the rear body cross member.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The body shall be attached to the chassis frame in such a manner as to minimize shifting of the body from the chassis under severe impact.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Alterations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Alterations in the length of the frame may be made only behind the rear hangers of the rear springs or forward of the front hangers of the front springs, or both, and may not be for the purpose of extending the wheelbase.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Alterations may be made only if designed and guaranteed either by the original chassis manufacturer or by the company installing the school vehicle body.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Fuel System and Tank.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Fuel Tank. The fuel tank shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have a minimum capacity of 22 gallons;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be filled and vented entirely outside the body; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Have a fill opening located so that accidental fuel spillage will not drip or drain to any part of the exhaust system.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A fuel filter with replaceable element shall be installed between the fuel tank and the engine fuel system.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The fuel lines shall be mounted to obtain maximum possible protection from the chassis frame.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If mounted on the right-hand side, the fill opening shall be equipped with a door.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If a fuel other than gasoline or diesel is used, the fuel system shall meet all applicable federal standards.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Instruments.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A type II school vehicle shall be equipped with, at a minimum, the following nonglare illuminated instruments and gauges:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ammeter or voltmeter with charge or discharge indication;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fuel gauge;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Odometer capable of registering mileage in tenths of a mile;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Oil pressure gauge;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Speedometer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Upper beam headlamp indicator; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Water temperature gauge.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>These instruments and gauges shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Mounted so as to allow for easy maintenance and repair; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Positioned so as to be clearly visible to a seated driver.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Steering System.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Steering gear shall be approved by the chassis manufacturer and designed to ensure safe and accurate performance when a vehicle is operated with a maximum load at maximum speed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The steering adjustment mechanism shall be accessible to perform required external adjustments.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Only changes approved by the chassis manufacturer may be made in the steering apparatus.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The steering system design shall provide for lubrication of wear points, if necessary.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Suspension (Springs and Shocks).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Springs and Suspension Assemblies. Springs and suspension assemblies shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Of ample resiliency under all load conditions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Able to sustain the loaded vehicle without evidence of overload; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Designated to carry their proportional share of gross vehicle weight.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Rear Springs. Rear springs shall be of a progressive type.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Front Springs. If leaf-type front springs are used, the stationary eyes shall be protected by a full wrapped leaf in addition to the main leaf.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Shock Absorbers. Two front and two rear double acting shock absorbers compatible with the manufacturer's rated axle capacity shall be provided.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Tires and Rims.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Tires and rims of proper size and tires with load range commensurate with the chassis manufacturer's gross vehicle weight rating shall be provided.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the vehicle is equipped with a spare tire and rim, they shall be of the same size as those mounted on the vehicle, and shall be mounted outside the passenger compartment under the vehicle.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Alternating Flashing Lights.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Warning Lights. A bus shall be equipped with four red flashing warning lights and four amber flashing warning lights that conform to the same requirements except as to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Color; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Candlepower which shall be at least 2-1/2 times that specified for red flashing warning lights.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Installation. Both red and amber flashing warning lights shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be installed so that each amber flashing warning light shall be located near each red flashing warning light, at the same level, but closer to the vertical center line of the vehicle; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have shields over the warning lights, except those equipped by the manufacturer with Halogen or L.E.D (Light Emitting Diodes). Shields may be of a single type to cover both the red and amber lights and shall be painted black, with a minimum depth of 4 inches.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The system shall be wired so that the amber flashing warning lights are activated only by hand operation, and if activated, are automatically deactivated when the vehicle entrance door is opened.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The red and amber flashing warning lights shall draw an equal current load.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The flashing mechanism shall be capable of carrying the full current load of the signal system in continuous operation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>There shall be red and amber pilot lights which shall go on when the respective red or amber systems are actuated. The appropriate pilots shall either go out or flash at an obvious altered rate if any of the lights in the system are not functioning normally.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Warning Light System. The switches and red and amber pilot lights shall be mounted to the right of the seated driver within easy unobstructed reach in a panel or specific area in the dash and may not be incorporated with other switches.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Signal Lamp System.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Master Switch. The amber pilot light and amber flashing lights shall go on, with the master switch on and the entrance door closed, when the momentary switch is depressed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Open Entrance Door. The amber pilot light and amber flashing lights shall go off and the red pilot light and red flashing lights shall go on when the entrance door is opened, and the stop arm and crossing arm, if equipped, shall automatically extend.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Close Entrance Door. The red pilot and red flashing lights shall go off, and the stop arm and crossing arm, if equipped, shall retract immediately when the entrance door is closed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Open Entrance Door Without Depressing Momentary Switch. The red pilot light and red flashing lights shall go on, and stop arm and crossing gate, if equipped, shall automatically extend when the entrance door is opened without depressing the momentary switch.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>With the master switch off, depressing the momentary switch may not activate the amber flashing system. Opening the entrance door with the master switch off may not activate the red flashing signal and stop arm.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>An override switch shall be provided to permit activation of the red warning lights and red pilot light without opening the service door whether the master switch is in the on or off position.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Installation Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each flashing light shall be mounted with its axis substantially parallel to the longitudinal axis of the vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Front and rear alternately flashing lights shall be spaced as far apart laterally as practicable.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Alternately flashing lights shall be mounted at the front above the windshield and at the rear so that the lower edge of the lens is not lower than the top line of the side window.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Vertical and lateral vision of the front and rear alternately flashing warning lights may not be obstructed by any part of the body or lamphouse insofar as standard vehicle body construction permits.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The area around each lamp, extending approximately 1 inch outward, shall be painted black.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A separate fuse or circuit breaker, adequate to prevent damage to the system in the event of a dead short, shall be provided between the power source and the master switch.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Flashing White Strobe Light.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A school vehicle may be equipped with a flashing white strobe light on the roof of the vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The flashing white strobe light:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall be installed on the roof in a position not further than 1/3 of the body length forward from the rear edge of the roof;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall have a single clear lens emitting light 360 degrees around its vertical axis;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>May not extend above the roof more than the maximum legal vehicle height, as set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|24-104">Transportation Article, §24-104(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Shall be approved by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a flashing white strobe light is installed, a manual switch and pilot light shall be installed in the driver's compartment to indicate when the light is operating.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Body Construction.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The body shall be constructed of fire-resistant material and the materials used inside the passenger compartment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The body shall be reasonably dustproof, gasproof, weathertight, and fume proof, and openings between the chassis and passenger compartment, where applicable, shall be sealed to prevent fumes or gases from entering the vehicle body.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The body manufacturer shall indicate in a permanent and readily visible location on the body the month and year of final completion of the vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The floor in the passenger compartment shall be level, except in the wheel housing, toeboard, stepwell, fuel fill pipe, and driver's platform areas which shall be constructed of fire resistant material.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Rub Rails.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>One rub rail shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be located approximately at the floor line;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Cover the same longitudinal area as the upper rub rail, except at wheel housings; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Extend to the radii of the right and left rear corners of the vehicle.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>One rub rail shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be located on each side of the bus approximately at seat level; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Extend from the rear side of the entrance door completely around the bus body, except for the emergency door, to a point of curvature near the outside cowl on the left side.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Both rub rails shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least 4 inches in width;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Of 16-gauge steel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Corrugated or ribbed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Attached at each body post and all other upright structural members; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Applied outside the body or outside the body posts, pressed in or snap on rub rails not satisfying this requirement.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A snow rail, if required, shall be installed the full length of the body skirt.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Snow and floor line rails shall be screwed or huck bolted on and may not be an integral part of the body.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The inside body height shall be 65 inches or more, measured metal to metal, at any point on the longitudinal center line from the front vertical bow to the rear vertical bow.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The vehicle body shall be thermally insulated between the inner and outer panels, ceiling, roof, and walls with proper material to deaden sound and to reduce vibrations to a minimum.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Projections and Exposed Edges.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The interior of the vehicle, including the ceiling, shall be free of projections except those required for the installation of equipment approved by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An inner liner shall be provided on the ceiling and walls.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Rearward components shall be lapped over forward components to reduce the likelihood of injury from exposed edges. Exposed edges shall be beaded, hemmed, or flanged.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Storage Compartment. A fire resistant container of adequate strength and capacity for the storage of tire chains, or tow chains and tools for minor emergency repairs, may be provided. If inside, the compartment shall have a cover and be fastened to the floor of the vehicle. A seat cushion may serve as a storage compartment cover.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Ventilation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The body shall be equipped with a suitable controlled ventilating system of sufficient capacity to maintain a proper quantity of air under normal operating conditions, without opening windows except in extremely warm weather.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A static type exhaust roof ventilator is required, which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall be nonclosable; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May be incorporated into the roof vent or emergency exit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Book Racks.</heading>
    <text>Book racks may not be installed in Type II school vehicles.</text>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|19|03|.19">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Color and Identification (Lettering).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Color.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The school bus body, including the cowl, hood, and fenders shall be painted a uniform color, National School Bus Yellow. If the window pilasters are visible after the window is installed they also shall be painted National School Bus Yellow. A chrome or manufacturer's gray grill is acceptable and the roof may be painted white. The white painted area may not extend below the top of the marker lights on the sides of the vehicle. The front and rear caps may not be painted white.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Body trim, on the exterior of the body, including the bumpers, the emergency door arrow, lamp hoods, and the lettering on the front, rear, and both sides of the body, shall be black. Yellow numbers on the front bumper are acceptable.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Rub rails, seat line, and snow rails shall be painted glossy black.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Wheel rims shall be black, gray, or silver.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Required Lettering.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The lettering described in this section is required and shall be black, block type, and placed according to the appropriate diagrams in Figures 1 through 6.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"SCHOOL BUS".</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The body of the vehicle shall bear the words "SCHOOL BUS" in capital letters 8 inches by 1 inch, on both the front and rear of the body. This lettering:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Shall be placed as high as possible without impairment of its visibility; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>May be on a reflective area 12 inches by 49 inches.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The 12-inch by 49-inch background area may be reduced in size to conform to the contours of the vehicle.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The words "EMERGENCY DOOR" or "EMERGENCY EXIT" in capital letters shall be 2 inches high painted above the door and above the emergency push-out windows, both inside and outside the vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Operating of Emergency Door or Exit Latch" shall be indicated by a 6-inch high by 3/4-inch wide black arrow indicating direction or release of the door or exit, inside and outside.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The identification number shall be 6 inches high by 3/4 inch wide, shall be on all four sides of the vehicle and shall be visible directly from the front, rear, and each side. On the rear of the vehicle, the identification number shall be located above the rear bumper and below the window line. Temporary signage or numbers shall be placed in the second window on the lower glass on each side of the vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If applicable, the name of the local school system shall be on both sides of the vehicle, properly centered, in letters 6 inches high by 1 inch wide.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Contractors' and private owners' or operators' names shall be to the rear of the entrance door and at the same approximate location on the left side in letters 2-1/2-3 inches high by 1/4-1/2 inch wide in a 16 inch by 30 inch area.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The following lettering may be used, if required or desired:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Address and telephone number of owner, placed to the rear of entrance door and at the same approximate location on the left side, in letters 2-1/2-3 inches high by 1/4-1/2 inch wide;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"STOP ON SIGNAL", in letters 4 inches high below the rear window; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Body manufacturer's name or logo, in letters placed in an area 8 inches by 24 inches above the first passenger window on each side of the vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Only signs and lettering approved by State law or regulation and any numbers necessary for identification shall appear on the vehicle. Bumper stickers are not permitted. The fleet number may be on the front bumper.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A vehicle titled and registered after April 2002 shall comply with all lettering size and location requirements. If buses are repainted, they shall be relettered in compliance with this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Lettering shall be painted or applied using vinyl die cut self-adhering letters and numbers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>"Drug Free School Zone" Lettering.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If desired, "Drug Free School Zone" may be on the exterior of the vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The lettering shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Located under the first window on the service door side or at another approved location near the service door; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>2 inches high by 3/8 inch wide.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A decal for the "Drug Free School Zone" may be used provided the background is National School Bus Yellow and the decal is not larger than 8 inches by 18 inches.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Yellow Reflective Tape. Yellow reflective tape at least 1 inch wide and not wider than 6-1/2 inches may be used to form a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Single horizontal line on each side of the bus at the floor line; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Rectangular figure on the rear of the bus body, which shall have its:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Vertical lines as close to the sides of the bus as possible without extending over the sides of the bus, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Horizontal lines consisting of one straight line above and near the rear bumper and one at or near the roof line.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The reflective tape specified in <cite path="11|19|03|.19|H.">§H of this regulation</cite> may be applied in a discontinuous fashion so as not to cover any existing or required lettering.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Roof Identification Number. Identification numbers on the roof may be used. If used, they shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Located in the most forward section of the roof as possible;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Lettered from the left side to the right side of the bus; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>18 inches high by 10 inches wide with a 2-3/4 inch stroke.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|19|03|.20">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.20</num>
    <heading>Electrical — Lamps, Signals, Reflectors, and Fuses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Tail and Stop (Brake) Lamps. Two tail and stop lamps having an illuminated area of not less than 19 square inches shall be mounted on the rear of the vehicle at a height not less than 15 inches and not more than 72 inches above the surface on which the unloaded vehicle rests and shall be positioned as far apart as practicable.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Turn Signal Lamps.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Turn signal lamps may be independent units and shall be equipped with a four-way hazard warning signal switch to activate simultaneous flashing of the turn signal lamps when needed as a vehicular traffic hazard warning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Surface mounted, amber clearance lamps, with a minimum of 4 candlepower each, shall be mounted on the sides of the body at approximately seat level rub rail height just to the rear of the service door on the right side, and approximately the same location on the left side, and shall be connected to function with the regular turn signal lamps.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Back-Up Lights.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Two back-up lights shall be installed to be activated when the gear shift lever is placed in reverse.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The lights shall be not less than 4 inches in diameter with a minimum of 32 candlepower and mounted above the bumper and below the window line.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Clearance, Side-Marker, and Identification Lamps.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Two red clearance lamps on the rear and two amber clearance lamps on the front shall be mounted as high as practical on the permanent structure of the school bus to indicate extreme width.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Two side marker lamps, amber at the front and red at the rear, shall be mounted on each side of the bus.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Three red identification lamps shall be mounted on the same level not more than 8 inches apart in the center rear of the body as high as practical, and three amber identification lamps shall be likewise mounted in the center front of the body.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Interior lamps shall adequately illuminate the entire aisle, the emergency passageway, and the stepwell.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Circuits.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Wiring shall be arranged in at least ten regular circuits as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Head, tail, stop (brake), and instrument panel lamps;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Clearance and stepwell lamps;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Dome lamps;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Starter motor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Ignition and emergency door signal;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Turn signal lamps;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Alternately flashing red and amber warning signal lamps;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Horn and wipers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Heater and defrosters; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Hydraulic or electric lift, if equipped.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The combination circuits listed in <cite path="11|19|03|.20|F.|(1)">§F(1) of this regulation</cite> may be subdivided into independent circuits. Each body circuit shall be coded by number or letter at 4 inch intervals or by color. The code shall appear on a diagram of the circuits in a readily accessible location.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Wiring Protection.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Wires within the body shall be insulated and protected by a covering of fibrous loom, or its equivalent, which shall protect them from external damage and minimize dangers from short circuits.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whenever wires pass through the body or chassis members, additional protection in the form of a grommet or other appropriate type of insert shall be provided.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Exposed wires are not permitted.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Wires shall be fastened securely according to manufacturer requirements, and joints shall be soldered or joined by equally effective connectors.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Switches.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A solenoid switch or an electronic control system shall be connected to the ignition switch so that body accessories cannot be operated when the ignition switch is off.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The alternating flashing warning lights, wheelchair lift, and electric powered service door, if equipped, may operate independently of the ignition switch.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A noise reduction off and on switch shall be installed to permit the driver to shut off the body heater and fan motors. This requirement applies to school vehicles constructed as of the effective date of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.21</num>
    <heading>Ignition Lock.</heading>
    <text>A lock key or other device to prevent the vehicle from being set in motion or its engine started by an unauthorized individual, or otherwise contrary to the will of the owner or individual in charge of the vehicle, shall be provided.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.22</num>
    <heading>Horns.</heading>
    <text>A suitable horn or horns providing an audible warning to other highway users at a distance of 300 feet shall be conveniently controlled from the driver's seated position.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.23</num>
    <heading>Back-Up Warning Alarm.</heading>
    <text>An automatic non-variable audible alarm activated when the vehicle is in reverse shall be installed behind the rear axle and be at least 97 decibels.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.24</num>
    <heading>Emergency Equipment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Fire Extinguisher. The vehicle shall be equipped with at least one 5-pound capacity, pressurized, dry chemical fire extinguisher complete with hose. The extinguisher shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be mounted in a bracket located below the window line in the driver's compartment and shall be readily accessible;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be equipped with a pressure gauge mounted on the extinguisher so as to be easily read without moving the extinguisher from its mounted position;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be of a type with a total rating of 2A 10 ABC or greater; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Have an operating mechanism sealed with a type of seal which does not interfere with the use of the fire extinguisher.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>First Aid Kit. Type II school vehicles shall carry a weatherproof first aid kit, removable and readily identifiable, mounted in an accessible, nonenclosed location in the driver's compartment. The kit shall contain at a minimum, the contents suggested by the National Standards for School Transportation Specifications and Procedures.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Reflectors and Flares.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The vehicle shall be equipped with three red triangular emergency reflectors in a suitable holder located in the driver's area.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The vehicle shall be equipped with three 30-minute stand-up lean-to flares stored in a red canister in the driver's area.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A locking device on the storage door for emergency equipment is prohibited.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Body Fluid Clean-Up Kit. Each bus shall have a removable and moisture-proof body fluid clean-up kit. The kit shall be properly mounted in the driver's compartment and identified as a body fluid clean-up kit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The safety equipment may be stored in a non-locking compartment that is permanently labeled "Safety Equipment Inside".</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.25</num>
    <heading>Flooring and Floor Covering.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Underseat Areas. The floor in underseat areas, including the top and side of the wheelhousing, driver's compartment, and toe board, shall be covered with fire-resistant rubber or equivalent floor covering having a minimum overall thickness of 0.125 inch. A molded floor cover over wheel housings is acceptable.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Aisle and Step Areas.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Floor covering in the aisle and steps shall be one continuous piece of fire resistant, nonskid, wear resistant, rubber, with a minimum overall thickness of 0.1875 inch.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>There shall be a heavy-duty, white-nosed, rubber wear plate where the floor covering meets the steps.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Bonding and Seals.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Floor covering shall be permanently bonded to the floor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Bonding material or seam sealers shall match the manufacturer's specification to ensure waterproofing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All seams, including those in the front and rear of or over wheel housings, shall be covered with aluminum strips or joined by bonding or welding.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Aisle seams shall be located on the aisle side of seat legs and shall be covered with strips made of aluminum or other material as approved by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Cove or cove molding made of metal or other material as approved by the Administration shall be installed over joints around the sides and rear body wall.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.26</num>
    <heading>Interior Heaters.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Heaters shall be of a hot water type.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The heating system shall be capable of maintaining a temperature of not less than 50°F throughout the vehicle at the average minimum January temperature established by the National Weather Service, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, for the area in which the vehicle is to be operated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Heaters shall bear a name plate attached by the manufacturer which shall indicate the heater rating and which shall constitute certification that the heater performance is as shown on the plate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Heater hoses shall be adequately supported to guard against excessive wear due to vibration, and may not dangle or rub against the chassis or sharp edges and may not interfere with or restrict the operation of any engine function.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Heater lines inside the passenger compartment shall be shielded to prevent accidental contact or scalding of the driver or passengers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Dual Heater Installation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each dual heater installation, if so equipped, shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Include a shut-off valve on each heater hose located in the engine compartment or under the body to the rear of the right front wheel on each heater hose;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be secured to the underside of the chassis to prevent abrasion or damage; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Be of a type to withstand weathering and abrasion of this exposed location.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>One heater shall be located at the front of the vehicle as original equipment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If an auxiliary heater is used, it shall be located as far to the rear of the passenger compartment as possible.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Combustion Heaters.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Combustion heaters are permitted and shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Have a switch or one-way valve installed at the fuel tank when the fuel line is pressurized to shut off the fuel to the heater in case of a broken line;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Have an indicator light in the driver's compartment to alert the driver of a malfunction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Be mounted on the left side of the vehicle in an individual compartment opening from the outside; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Have the exhaust come out the left side of the vehicle under the skirt as close to the rear wheels as possible.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Only combustion heaters approved by the Administration may be installed on school vehicles.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Portable heaters may not be used.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.27</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|19|03|.28">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.28</num>
    <heading>Mirrors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An interior clear view mirror shall be at least 5 by 15 inches to afford a good view of the passengers and the roadway to the rear. If it is not metal backed and framed, the mirror shall be made of laminated safety glass. It shall have rounded corners and protected edges.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Two adjustable exterior, clear view mirrors, framed with black housing, shall be installed on each side of the vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Fender-Mounted Mirrors.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>One fender-mounted tripod or solid piece mirror bracket shall be mounted on each front fender.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An exterior convex mirror shall be mounted on each front fender to provide a close infield of the vision to eliminate blind spots.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A single mirror of a type approved by the Administration in conjunction with the State Department of Education may be used in place of the mirrors in <cite path="11|19|03|.28|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.29</num>
    <heading>Seats, Crash Barriers, and Interior.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Passenger Seats.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The minimum clearance of all aisles, including the aisle or passageway between seats leading to the emergency door, shall be 12 inches.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The forward-most seat on the right side of the vehicle shall be located so as not to interfere with the operator's vision and may not be farther forward than the rear of the operator's seat when adjusted to its rearmost position.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The backs of seats of similar size shall be of the same width at the top, of the same height from the floor, and shall slant at the same angle with the floor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Seats shall be forward facing and shall be securely fastened with bolts and nuts to supporting parts of the vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Each seat leg shall be fastened with a minimum of two bolts and nuts.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Portable seats may not be used.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Aisle supports of seat backs shall be slanted away from the aisle sufficiently to give an aisle clearance of 15 inches at the tops of the seat backs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>As of January 1, 2014, all vehicles procured for use in this State shall be constructed with materials that enable it to meet all the criteria of the school bus seat upholstery fire block test established by the National School Transportation Specifications and Procedures adopted at the most recent National Congress on School Transportation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Seat cushions shall be fastened to the seat structure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Seat covering shall be of minimum 42-ounce or approved equal material.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Operator's Seat.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The minimum distance between the steering wheel and the backrest of the operator's seat is 11 inches.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The operator's seat shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be rigidly positioned;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Have fore and aft adjustment of not less than 4 inches, without the use of tools or other devices; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Be fastened to the floor with bolts, nuts, and washers or flanged-head nuts.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Crash Barriers.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Crash barriers shall be located on both sides of the aisle in front of the most forward facing seat.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>On vehicles with the engine inside the front of the body, the minimum distance between the barrier at the rear of the entrance stepwell and the engine cover shall be 14 inches at floor level.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>As of January 1, 2014, all vehicles procured for use in this State shall be constructed with materials that enable it to meet all the criteria of the school bus seat upholstery fire block test established by the National School Transportation Specifications and Procedures adopted at the most recent National Congress on School Transportation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Sun Visor. An interior adjustable sun visor supported by two brackets not less than 5 inches wide and 15 inches long shall be installed so that it can be turned up to prevent being a hazard when not in use.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Steering Wheel. The steering wheel circumference shall have at least 2 inches of clearance at all points.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Speakers. Ceiling or side mounted speakers shall be flush mounted.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.30</num>
    <heading>Service Door.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The service door shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be located on the right side near the front in a location which shall provide the seated driver an unobstructed view of the entrance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have a minimum horizontal opening of 24 inches and a minimum vertical opening of 50 inches;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Have a head pad, minimum of 1 inch by 4 inches of foam rubber, on the interior of the vehicle to extend the width of the door opening;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Be of the jackknife, accordion, or split type;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Be manually or power operated by the seated drive; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Be designed to afford easy release and prevent accidental opening.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The parts of a service door hand lever may not come together so as to shear or crush fingers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Split-type doors may open outward, but if one section of a folding door opens inward and the other opens outward, the forward section shall open outward.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Vertical closing edges shall be equipped with padding to prevent injury.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The bottom of the lower glass panel may not be more than 10 inches from the top surface of the bottom step.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The top of the upper glass panel may not be more than 3 inches below the interior control cover or head pad.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Manually operated service doors shall be reinforced to support the door control operating mechanism.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Power operated doors shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Equipped so as to regulate control and to permit manual operation in case of power failure; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Labeled on the inside in letters at least 1/2 inch high with instructions for emergency opening.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Step Well.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Step risers shall be approximately equal in height, with the upper riser not more than 12 inches high.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The steps shall be surfaced with a non-skid material with a minimum of 1-1/2 inch white nosing on the steps and where the floor meets the steps as an integral piece.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The step well shall be illuminated by at least one lamp providing a white light actuated automatically when the service door is open.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The lower step may not be less than 10 inches and not more than 14 inches above the level on which the unloaded vehicle rests.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The entrance may be equipped with a running board-type step which does not extend beyond the width of the vehicle body.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A step well shall have a grab handle of stainless steel not less than 10 inches in length and be properly secured on the left in an unobstructed location inside the doorway.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.31</num>
    <heading>Emergency Door.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Emergency exits shall be in accordance with the requirements of 49 CFR §571.217, with the following additions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The rearmost seats shall be spaced to provide an unobstructed exit; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The words "Emergency Door" shall be 2 inches high by 3/8 inch wide black lettering and shall be applied above the door and emergency push-out windows on the inside and outside of the vehicle. If the outside areas above the door or the upper door window are not large enough for the words, the words may be placed on the door under the upper window.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>There shall be a head bumper pad sufficient to reduce the likelihood of injury upon impact installed on the inside of the vehicle at the top of the emergency door. The pad shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be 4 inches wide; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Extend across the entire top of the door opening.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Passage to the emergency door shall be kept clear of obstructions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Slide Bar Latch.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The emergency door or doors shall be equipped with a slide bar-type latch which shall extend into or overlap the door frame by not less than 1 inch.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a vertical slide bar latch system is used, it shall simultaneously engage latch plates in both the floor and overhead structure not more than 4-1/2 inches from the opening side of the door or doors.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The outside handle of the slide bar latch shall be installed so as to minimize hitching and shall be a nondetachable device.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An automatically operated, distinctive audible signal shall clearly indicate to the seated driver, when the engine is running, the unlatching of the emergency door or doors. A cut-off switch except through the ignition switch may not be installed in the circuit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The upper and lower portion of a central rear emergency door shall be equipped with approved safety glass, the exposed area of which shall be not less than 400 square inches in the upper portion and not less than 300 square inches in the lower portion.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Prohibitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>There may not be steps leading to the emergency door; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The engine starting system of a bus may not operate if any emergency exit is locked from either inside or outside the bus.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.32</num>
    <heading>Emergency Exit Windows.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An automatically operated distinctive audible signal shall clearly indicate to the seated driver, when the engine is running, that an emergency window has been unlatched. A cut-off switch except through the ignition switch may not be installed in the circuit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Operating Instructions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Concise operating instructions describing the motions necessary to unlatch and open the emergency window shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Of a color that contrasts with the letters' background; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Located within 6 inches of the release mechanism on the inside surface of the vehicle.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A decal containing the instructions may be placed on the window. The decal shall be transparent except for the lettering.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The emergency window, if provided, shall be labeled "Emergency Exit" in letters 2 inches high located at the top of or directly above the emergency window on both the inside and outside surfaces of the vehicle.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.33</num>
    <heading>Roof Vent/Emergency Exit.</heading>
    <text>At least one roof vent/emergency exit shall be installed and be:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Adjustable;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Equipped with a release handle inside and outside to permit the ventilator cover to hinge open for emergency exit;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Labeled "Emergency Exit" followed by precise operating instructions; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Equipped with a distinctive audible alarm, if a roof vent.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.34</num>
    <heading>Stop Signal Arm.</heading>
    <text>A second stop signal arm may be installed on the left outside of the body and shall be installed as close as practicable to the rear of the bus.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.35</num>
    <heading>Crossing Arm.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A crossing arm may be installed on the far right of the front bumper. The crossing arm:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall be securely bolt-mounted;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall be easily removable for towing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Shall be activated simultaneously with the stop arm;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>May not open more than 90 degrees;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Shall extend a minimum of 66 inches from the front of the bumper when activated;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>May not have sharp edges or projections which may cause injury to students; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Shall be air, vacuum, or electrically operated and may not have lights.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Interrupt Switch.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A crossing arm interrupt switch may be installed on the dash near the control box for the alternating flashing lights.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pressing the switch shall stop the arm from opening for a full cycle and the arm shall recycle after the alternating flashing lights have been deactivated.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.36</num>
    <heading>Undercoating.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The entire underside of the vehicle body and front fenders, including floor members and side panels below floor level, shall be coated with a fire resistant asphalt based or rubber based undercoating material applied by spray method at least 1/8 inch thick in order to seal, deaden sound, insulate, and prevent oxidation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Fiberglass construction is exempt from undercoating requirements.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.37</num>
    <heading>Wheel Housing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The wheel housing opening shall allow for easy tire removal and service.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The wheel housing shall be attached to the floor sheets in such a manner as to prevent dust, water, or fumes from entering the body.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The inside height of the wheel housing above the floor line may not exceed 10 inches.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The wheel housing shall provide clearance for the installation and use of tire chains on single and dual, if so equipped, power driving wheels.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>No part of a raised wheel housing may extend into the emergency door opening.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.38</num>
    <heading>Windshields, Windows, Wipers, and Washers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Safety Glass. Glass shall be installed so that the identification mark is legible.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Windshields. The windshield shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be large enough to permit the operator to see the highway clearly;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be slanted to reduce glare; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be installed between front corner posts that are so designed and located as to afford a minimum of obstruction to the operator's view of the highway.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Stirrup Steps. There may be at least one folding stirrup step or recessed foothold and suitably located handles on each side of the front of the body for easy accessibility for cleaning the windshield and lamps.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Windows.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Glass in passenger compartment side windows, doors, and rear windows shall be AS-2 or AS-3 laminated safety glass.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Passenger compartment windows shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Operate freely;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Open 9-10-1/2 inches from the top only and provide an emergency exit of at least 9 inches by 22 inches;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Have all exposed edges of glass banded;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Be free of window guards or bars either on the inside or outside; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Be aluminum-framed split sash.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Windshield Wipers.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Automatic, variable, two speed or intermittent windshield wipers with nonglare arms and blades shall be installed so as to clean the maximum possible area of the windshield.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The windshield wiper blades and arms shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be heavy-duty; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be at least 14 inches long.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.39</num>
    <heading>Video Cameras.</heading>
    <text>A video camera system may be installed if the system is:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Approved by the Administration;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Installed securely in an area of the vehicle with no sharp edges;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Located in an area not likely to cause student injury; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Outside the federal head impact zone, as defined in 49 CFR §571.222.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.40</num>
    <heading>Safety Detection Systems.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A safety detection system approved by the Federal Communications Commission may be installed to warn bus drivers of moving objects such as children within areas around a school vehicle considered to be most dangerous, if the system:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is designed to monitor and warn school bus drivers of moving objects during loading and unloading;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Operates automatically;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is activated by extending the stop arm; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Has audible and visual alarms.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The audible alarm volume shall compensate for background noises.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The visual alarm shall be easily visible both at night and in bright sunshine.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The system shall be located in the driver's compartment and be visible to the driver in a seated position.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A delay feature shall be incorporated in the system which shall operate the detection unit for a brief period of time after the bus resumes motion.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.41</num>
    <heading>Air Conditioning Systems.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Air conditioning systems may be installed in school vehicles if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The systems are approved by the Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The agency and personnel installing the systems have been certified by the air conditioning manufacturer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>There are no sharp edges or protrusions that could injure students;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The total vehicle battery capacity is of sufficient amperes to supply all electrical requirements;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The vehicle alternator rating is at least 130 amperes; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The system does not contain refrigerant that is toxic to individuals or is flammable.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>System operating controls, including the on-off and blower switch or switches and the thermostat control or controls, shall be accessible to the driver in a seated position.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Wiring, hoses, and lines shall be grommeted, routed, and supported so as to reduce wear resulting from heat, chafing, vibration, or other factors.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Evaporator cases, lines and ducting shall be designed so that condensation is effectively drained to the exterior of the vehicle below floor level and under all conditions of vehicle movement without leakage on any interior portion of the vehicle. Evaporator cases, lines, and ducting shall be inaccessible to passengers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>System components shall be readily available for servicing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An air conditioning grill on the exterior shall be the same color as the predominant area in which it is installed.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.42</num>
    <heading>Air Cleaners.</heading>
    <text>The engine intake air cleaner shall be furnished and properly installed by the chassis manufacturer to meet engine specifications.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.43</num>
    <heading>Child Reminder System.</heading>
    <text>A child reminder system approved by the Administration may be installed. The deactivating switch shall be located on the inside rear-most portion of the bus.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|7-808">Education Article, §7-808</cite>; Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-174">11-174</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b), and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|25-110">25-110</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1981-04-17">Effective date: April 17, 1981 (8:8 Md. R. 722)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1981-10-26">Regulation .01 amended as an emergency provision effective July 24, 1981 (8:15 Md. R. 1300); adopted permanently effective October 26, 1981 (8:21 Md. R. 1709)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1985-06-03">Regulations .01—.02, .04, .06—.11, .13, .15—.18, .20—.24, .26, .29—.33, .35, .36, .40, .42—.46, .49—.52, .54, .55, and .58 amended effective June 3, 1985 (12:11 Md. R. 1050)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" discontinuity="true" effective="1999-04-19">Regulations .01—.58 repealed and new Regulations .01—.42 adopted effective April 19, 1999 (26:8 Md. R. 616)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-04-02">Regulations .03C .09C, .17C, .19A, .24, .25C and .34 amended effective April 2, 2001 (28:6 Md. R. 621)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2005-06-20">Regulation .15B amended effective June 20, 2005 (32:12 Md. R. 1047)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2005-06-20">Regulation .19A amended effective June 20, 2005 (32:12 Md. R. 1047)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2005-06-20">Regulation .19K adopted effective June 20, 2005 (32:12 Md. R. 1047)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2005-06-20">Regulation .20M amended effective June 20, 2005 (32:12 Md. R. 1047)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2005-06-20">Regulation .26F amended effective June 20, 2005 (32:12 Md. R. 1047)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2005-06-20">Regulation .41F adopted effective June 20, 2005 (32:12 Md. R. 1047)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2001-04-02">Regulation .43 adopted effective April 2, 2001 (28:6 Md. R. 621)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" discontinuity="true" effective="2010-07-12">Chapter revised effective July 12, 2010 (37:14 Md. R. 939)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-01-21">Regulation .02B amended effective January 21, 2013 (40:1 Md. R. 20)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-01-21">Regulation .08A, C amended effective January 21, 2013 (40:1 Md. R. 20)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-01-21">Regulation .19 amended effective January 21, 2013 (40:1 Md. R. 20)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-01-21">Regulation .23 amended effective January 21, 2013 (40:1 Md. R. 20)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-01-21">Regulation .24E amended effective January 21, 2013 (40:1 Md. R. 20)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-01-21">Regulation .25B amended effective January 21, 2013 (40:1 Md. R. 20)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-01-21">Regulation .26 amended effective January 21, 2013 (40:1 Md. R. 20)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-01-21">Regulation .28 amended effective January 21, 2013 (40:1 Md. R. 20)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-01-21">Regulation .29A, C amended effective January 21, 2013 (40:1 Md. R. 20)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-03-28">Regulation .30A amended effective January 21, 2013 (40:1 Md. R. 20); March 28, 2016 (43:6 Md. R. 410)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-03-28">Regulation .31G amended effective March 28, 2016 (43:6 Md. R. 410)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-01-21">Regulation .32B, C amended effective January 21, 2013 (40:1 Md. R. 20)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-01-21">Regulation .33 amended effective January 21, 2013 (40:1 Md. R. 20)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2013-01-21">Regulation .38A, E amended effective January 21, 2013 (40:1 Md. R. 20)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
