<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Formula for Determining the Agricultural Value of Land</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>These regulations provide the formula for determining the agricultural value of land under the Maryland Agricultural Land Preservation Program.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Agricultural land preservation easement" or "easement" means a negative servitude in land which restricts a landowner's right to use the land for any commercial, industrial, or residential purpose except as otherwise permitted under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-513">Agriculture Article, §2-513, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Agricultural value" means the value of the land determined by a formula adopted by the Department that measures the farm productivity of the land.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Cultivatable land" means the portion of the applicant's land that consists of the following soil groups as classified under the USDA Soil Conservation Service's Soil Capability System: Class I, II, III, IV, V, and VI soils.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Maryland Department of Agriculture.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Fair market value" means the value of land as of the valuation date for the highest and best use of the land which a vendor, willing but not obligated to sell, would accept for the property, and which a purchaser, willing but not obligated to buy, would pay for the property if the property was not subject to any easement restriction.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Purchase of Easement.</heading>
    <text>If land has development potential for commercial, industrial, or residential use, the Department may purchase, subject to requirements of COMAR 15. <cite path="|15.01">15.01</cite>, an agricultural land preservation easement from a landowner. The maximum value that the Department may pay for an easement is the asking price or the difference between the fair market value of the land and the agricultural value of the land, whichever is lower. The Foundation may not purchase an easement from a landowner whose land is already restricted to agricultural use.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Fair Market Value.</heading>
    <text>The fair market value of the land on which the landowner has applied to sell an easement shall be determined by the Department of General Services based upon one or more appraisals by State appraisers and any appraisals, if any, of the landowner.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Explanation of Formula for Determining Agricultural Value.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Formula's Underlying Premise. The agricultural value of the land on which the landowner has applied to sell an easement shall be determined by the formula provided under Regulation .06. This formula, which measures the farm productivity of the applicant's land, provides a method for ascertaining the capitalized value of the sum necessary to rent the applicant's farm. (The formula's premise is that the capitalized value of cash rents paid for land is a reliable indicator of the land's agricultural value.) The formula numerically explains how certain factors such as a farm's location and its soil types affect rent.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Factors Affecting Rent.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Soil Types. A survey of Maryland farmers who rented land revealed a strong relationship between rent and soil types, that is, the greater a land's natural productivity, the greater the rent paid for that land (and per the formula's premise, the greater the agricultural value of the land). As explained in Regulation .07, a land's natural productivity is measured in terms of a soil productivity index. This index is based on the natural characteristics of each soil class and how these characteristics relate to crop production.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Location. A survey of Maryland farmers also revealed a relationship between rent and a farm's location, that is, the greater a farm's average distance from Baltimore and Washington, up to 100 miles, the greater the rent paid for that land (and per the formula's premise, the greater the agricultural value of the land). Beyond 100 miles, the relationship between rent and a farm's location was not significant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Quantifying How Soil Types and Location Affect Rent. From the results of this survey, a mathematical equation was developed which effectively estimates how a farm's soil types and location would affect its rent. Being able to effectively estimate how these factors would affect a farm's rent (and consequently, per the formula's premise, how they would affect a farm's agricultural value), this equation forms a major step in the Department's formula for determining agricultural value. The mathematical equation is as follows: Rent = -53 + (160 X productivity index) + (0.11 X average distance from Baltimore and Washington, up to 100 miles). The equation, however, is only effective for estimating rental values greater than $25 per acre. For this reason, under the Department's formula for determining agricultural value, $25 per acre constitutes the minimum per acre rental value for a parcel of land.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Explanation of Mathematical Equation.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Relationship Between Rent and Soil Types. The chart indicated in Regulation .08 is useful to understand the relationship between rent and soil types. A visual inspection reveals that rents tend to be greater for higher soil productivity indexes. Mathematical methods are used to generalize this relationship into a statistically "best fit" formula shown by the formula line on the graph. The -53 in the equation represents the point where the formula line crosses the rent axis on the graph. It has no practical meaning except to fit the formula line to the data. The 160 in the equation represents the formula line's slope. It means that for each increase of 0.10 in the soil productivity index of a parcel of land, rental values increase $16.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Relationship Between Rent and Location. The relationship between rent and location of this equation can be similarly explained. The 0.11 in the equation means that for every mile increase in average distance that the applicant's land is from Baltimore and Washington, up to 100 miles, rental rates increase by 11 cents.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Range of Equation's Effectiveness. The $25 minimum rent value line indicates that the equation is only effective for estimating rents within the range of the data. In those few cases when, under the equation, a land's rental value is estimated to be less than $25 per acre, use $25 per acre to complete the formula for determining the land's agricultural value.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Formula for Determining Agricultural Value.</heading>
    <text>To determine the agricultural value of the land on which the landowner has applied to sell an easement, complete the following five steps:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Step 1. Using the following method, determine the soil productivity index of the parcel of land on which the applicant has applied to sell an easement. First, note how many acres of cultivatable land (Class I through VI soils) are contained in this parcel. Second, determine how many of these acres consist of Class I soils. Third, using the table found in Regulation .07 of this chapter, multiply the number of acres of Class I soils by the soil productivity index for Class I soils. Having completed the calculation process for Class I soils, follow the same process for Class II through Class VI soils. Next, add each of these calculations together. Finally, divide this sum by the total number of acres of cultivatable land contained in the entire parcel. This figure equals the soil productivity index of the applicant's parcel. (For example, if the applicant's parcel consists of 60 acres of Class II soils and 40 acres of Class III soils, the following calculations must be made: 60 acres X 0.72 = <cite path="|43.20">43.20</cite>; 40 acres X 0.50 = 20; <cite path="|43.20">43.20</cite> + 20 = <cite path="|63.20">63.20</cite>; <cite path="|63.20">63.20</cite> divided by 100 acres = 0.632. The soil productivity index of the applicant's parcel in this example equals 0.632.) Use this calculation to complete Step 3.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Step 2. Determine the average distance the applicant's land is from Baltimore and Washington. First, note the distance this land is from Baltimore. Second, note the land's distance from Washington, D.C. To obtain the land's average distance from Baltimore and Washington, add these two distances together and divide by 2. (For example, if the applicant's land is 50 miles from Washington and 20 miles from Baltimore, its average distance from these areas is 35 miles. (50 + 20) divided by 2 = 35.) Use this calculation to complete Step 3.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Step 3. Using the mathematical equation discussed in Regulation .05 of this chapter, determine the per acre rental value of the applicant's land. That equation is as follows: Rent = -53 + (160 X productivity index) + (0.11 x average distance from Baltimore and Washington, up to 100 miles). Insert the figures derived from completing Steps 1 and 2 to complete the equation. The productivity index number is the figure derived from completing Step 1. The average distance is the figure derived from completing Step 2. If the average distance is 100 miles or more, insert 100 into the equation. (Using the figures from the examples noted in Steps 1 and 2, the equation is completed as follows: Rent = -53 + (160 X 0.632) + (0.11 X 35) or, to answer the equation, $51.97 per acre.) Use this calculation or the most recent 5-year average cash rent of the county where the property is located, whichever is lower, to complete Step 4. If the rental value calculated in Step 3 or if the running 5-year average cash rent of the county is less than $25 per acre, use $25 per acre to complete Step 4.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Step 4. To determine the per acre agricultural value of the applicant's land, divide the figure derived from completing Step 3 (the per acre rental value of the applicant's land) by a capitalization rate of 6 percent (the Department has estimated 6 percent to be the capitalization rate). (Using the figure from the example noted in Step 3, or $51.97 per acre, the per acre agricultural value is $742.43 ($51.97 divided by 0.06).) Use this figure to complete the final step.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Step 5. To determine the agricultural value of the applicant's land, multiply the figure derived from completing Step 4 (the per acre value) by the total number of acres of cultivatable land comprising the applicant's land.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Soil Productivity Index*.</heading>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Soil Class</td>
            <td data-vertical-align="middle">Soil Productivity Index</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Class I</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1.00</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Class II</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">.72</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Class III</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">.50</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Class IV</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">.50</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Class V</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">.18</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">VI</td>
            <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">.18</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>*The figures in this table numerically express the soil productivity for each class of soil. Compiled by the Maryland Agricultural Statistics Services, USDA, and the Agricultural Resource Economics Department, University of Maryland, they are based on the capability each class has of producing crops under average management. Class I soils have a high productivity rating. Class II soils have a medium productivity rating which is 28 percent less than Class I. Class III and IV soils have a low productivity rating which is 50 percent less than Class I. Class V and VI soils have the lowest rating which is 82 percent less than Class I.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Relationship Between Rent and Soil Productivity Index.</heading>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">
      <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-511">Agriculture Article, §2-511, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>
    </annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-03-04">Regulations .01—.08 adopted as an emergency provision effective March 4, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 681); emergency status extended at 18:16 Md. R. 1810 (August</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container">9, 1991)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-10-28">Regulations .01—.08 adopted effective October 28, 1991 (18:21 Md. R. 2310)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1997-09-08">Regulation .06C amended effective September 8, 1997 (24:18 Md. R. 1297)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
