<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This subtitle is applicable to electric companies and subscriber organizations in service territories where customers have the ability to subscribe to a community solar energy generation system under a pilot program approved by the Commission.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Agent.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Agent" means a person who conducts marketing or sales activities, or both, on behalf of a subscriber organization or subscription coordinator. Agent includes an employee, a representative, an independent contractor and a vendor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Agent" includes subcontractors, employees, vendors and representatives not directly under contract with the subscriber organization or subscription coordinator that conducts marketing or sales activities on behalf or for the benefit of the subscriber organization or subscription coordinator.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Agent" does not include a member of a neighborhood association, church, nonprofit organization, or other community organization that is a subscriber organization when the member is conducting marketing or sales activities on behalf of the subscriber organization to fellow members and is not receiving any compensation for those marketing or sales activities.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Baseline annual usage" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-306">Public Utilities Article, §7-306</cite>.2, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Brownfield" means one of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A former industrial or commercial site identified by federal or State laws or regulations as contaminated or polluted;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A closed municipal or rubble landfill regulated under a refuse disposal permit by the Maryland Department of the Environment; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Mined lands" as defined in <cite path="26.21.01.01|B.">COMAR 26.21.01.01B</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Clean fill site" means a closed filling operation exempt from regulation by the Maryland Department of the Environment under <cite path="26.04.07.04|C.|(5)">COMAR 26.04.07.04C(5)</cite> for which a subscriber organization has provided documentation from a local authority having jurisdiction that the filling operation meets the exemption criteria under <cite path="26.04.07.04|C.|(5)">COMAR 26.04.07.04C(5)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Commission" means the Public Service Commission of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Community solar energy generating system" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-306">Public Utilities Article, §7-306</cite>.2, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Consent" means an agreement with an action communicated by the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A written document with customer signature; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An electronic document with electronic signature.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Consumer" or "customer" means a retail electric customer account holder of a regulated electric company.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Contract summary" means a summary of the material terms and conditions of a community solar pilot program subscriber contract on a form provided by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"CSEGS" means a community solar energy generating system.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Electric company" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|1-101">Public Utilities Article, §1-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Electronic transaction" means a standardized data protocol or electronic transmission medium that has been accepted by the Commission for use in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Low income" means a subscriber whose gross annual household income is at or below 175 percent of the federal poverty level for the year of subscription or who is certified as eligible for any federal, state, or local assistance program that limits participation to households whose income is at or below 175 percent of the federal poverty limit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Moderate income" means a subscriber whose gross annual household income is at or below 80 percent of the median income for Maryland for the year of subscription.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"Personally identifiable information" means information that can be used to distinguish or trace an individual's identity, either alone or when combined with other personal or identifying information that is linked or capable of being linked to a specific individual.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"Program" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-306">Public Utilities Article, §7-306</cite>.2, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>"Public event" means an event open to the public where subscriptions to a community solar energy generation system are marketed or sold.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>"Security deposit" means any payment of money given to a subscriber organization by a subscriber in order to protect the subscriber organization against nonpayment of future subscription fees, but does not include escrowed prepaid subscription fees.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>"Subscriber" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-306">Public Utilities Article, §7-306</cite>.2, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>"Subscriber organization" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-306">Public Utilities Article, §7-306</cite>.2, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>"Subscription" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-306">Public Utilities Article, §7-306</cite>.2, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>"Subscription coordinator" means a person that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Markets CSEGS projects or otherwise provides CSEGS-related services under its own brand name;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Performs any administrative actions to connect or enroll customers with CSEGS projects or allocates subscriptions; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Manages interactions between a subscriber organization and an electric company relating to subscribers.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>"Unsubscribed energy" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-306">Public Utilities Article, §7-306</cite>.2, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>"Utility" means an electric company as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|1-101">Public Utilities Article, §1-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>"Virtual net energy metering" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-306">Public Utilities Article, §7-306</cite>.2, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Electric Company Compliance Plan.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An electric company shall file a plan and relevant tariffs for compliance with this subtitle within 45 days after this regulation becomes effective.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A municipal electric company or electric cooperative electing to participate in the pilot program shall file a plan and related tariffs for compliance with this subtitle within 45 days after notifying the Commission of that election.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Waiver.</heading>
    <text>The Commission may waive a regulation in this subtitle for good cause shown.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-113">2-113</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-306">7-306</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-306">7-306</cite>.1, and 7-306.2, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-07-18">Effective date: July 18, 2016 (43:14 Md. R. 781)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-03-21">Regulation .02B amended effective March 21, 2022 (49:6 Md. R. 406)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
