<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Pilot Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Pilot Program Structure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each electric company shall establish a program to accept and administer community solar energy generating system projects for a period of 7 years from the earlier of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The first date of application of a subscriber organization to operate a community solar energy generating system after the effective date of this subtitle; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>6 months from the effective date of this subtitle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Community solar energy generating system programs may not end prior to December 31, 2024.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Program Annual Start Date.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An electric company participating in the Pilot Program shall post a start date for each program year on the electric company's website.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An electric company shall make best efforts to begin each program year within 12 months of the start date for the previous year, with the exception of Program Year 6.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An electric company may include a schedule of program years in its tariff.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An electric company shall make best efforts to begin Program Year 6 within 18 months after the beginning of Program Year 4.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An electric company shall apply bill credits and excess generation to a subscriber's bill in accordance with applicable tariffs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An electric company shall pay subscriber organizations for unsubscribed energy in accordance with applicable tariffs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An electric company shall maintain program data and records as directed by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|62|02|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Program Generation Capacity.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Capacity Limit.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Statewide Capacity.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Subject to <cite path="20|62|02|.02|A.|(1)|(b)">§A(1)(b) of this regulation</cite>, an electric company may not accept pilot program project applications after the Statewide capacity of pilot projects has exceeded 4.55 percent of the 2015 Maryland peak demand in MW as measured by the sum of the nameplate capacity of each project's inverter.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An electric company shall accept an additional 0.15 percent of 2015 capacity for projects serving the LMI category or projects serving the Small category under <cite path="20|62|02|.02|A.|(3)|(a)|(iv)">§A(3)(a)(iv) of this regulation</cite> if an electric utility has reached full capacity available to projects in the LMI category.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An electric company shall accept an additional 0.05 percent of 2015 capacity for projects of 50kW or less during the fourth through seventh year of the program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Annual Cap. The following percentages of 2015 Maryland peak demand will set annual program capacity:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>First year — 0.6 percent.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Second year — 0.6 percent.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Third year — 0.3 percent.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Fourth year — 0.35 percent.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Fifth year — 0.8 percent.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Sixth year — 0.9 percent.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Seventh year — 0.95 percent.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Program Categories. An electric company shall accept pilot projects in each of the following categories up to the annual and program capacity limits according to the percentages shown in each of the following paragraphs:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Small, Brownfield and Other Category (Small) — 30 percent.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Projects up to and including 500 kW.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Projects installed on rooftops, parking lots, roadways or parking structures.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Projects installed on brownfield locations.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Projects serving more than 51 percent of kWh output to Low or Moderate income customers.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Projects installed on clean fill sites.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Open Category (Open) — 40 percent — Projects of any size up to 2 MW.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Low and Moderate Income Category (LMI) — 30 percent — Projects serving more than 30 percent of kWh output to Low or Moderate income subscribers of which Low Income subscribers receive a minimum of 10 percent of kWh output.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Projects which qualify for the Small or LMI category may use capacity from the Open category after the electric company has accepted projects up to the limit of its respective categories.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>An electric company may accept an LMI project using either LMI capacity or LMI projects serving the Small category under <cite path="20|62|02|.02|A.|(3)|(a)|(iv)">§A(3)(a)(iv) of this regulation</cite> as described in <cite path="20|62|02|.02|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite> from subsequent program years if the capacity in the current year has been fully allocated.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Electric Company Program Capacity Limits.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Subject to the annual and category limits established in this regulation, an electric company shall accept pilot program applications up to 4.55 percent of its 2015 Maryland peak demand.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An electric company may accept project applications after it has accepted 4.55 percent of its 2015 peak demand in MW as measured by the sum of the nameplate capacity of each project's inverter.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An electric company may cease accepting project applications according to the annual percentages listed in <cite path="20|62|02|.02|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite> as applied to that company's 2015 peak demand.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>An electric company shall allocate annual capacity according to the program category percentages listed in <cite path="20|62|02|.02|A.|(3)">§A(3) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>An electric company shall notify the Commission if it intends to accept project applications beyond the level described in <cite path="20|62|02|.02|A.|(4)|(a)">§A(4)(a) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>An electric company shall combine the capacity of the Small and Open categories if the capacity allocated to the "Open" category is 500 kW or less.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Waitlist.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>If a subscriber organization applies to add a project to a category after an electric company has awarded all available capacity in that category, the electric company shall place the project application on a waitlist for the category in the order in which the application was received.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>In years 4 through 7 of the Program, an electric company shall first award project applications in each category from the waitlist for that category before awarding capacity to new project applications.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A subscriber organization may not change the category of a project on the waitlist.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>An electric company shall remove a project from a category waitlist upon request of the subscriber organization for which the Commission has authorized the project.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>A subscriber organization may re-apply to a different category after the electric company has removed a project from a category waitlist.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Unused Annual Capacity.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Electric company capacity in each year which remains unused by projects shall be added to the capacity of the following year such that the total Statewide capacity does not exceed the limit in <cite path="20|62|02|.02|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If a category listed in <cite path="20|62|02|.02|A.|(3)">§A(3) of this regulation</cite> has unused capacity at the end of any year of the program, the unused capacity shall be carried forward in the same category to the following year.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Capacity that has remained unused following the sixth year shall be reallocated by the Commission upon good cause shown.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each electric company shall maintain a list of accepted projects and total pilot program capacity in its service territory.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Project Lists.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each electric company shall provide the list in <cite path="20|62|02|.02|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> to the Commission on the first business day after June 30 and December 31 of each year until the pilot is closed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An electric company that posts on its website the information in <cite path="20|62|02|.02|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> shall be considered to have met the requirements of this section.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Commission may direct electric companies to close the program to new applications if the total Statewide net-metered generation exceeds the limit described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-306">Public Utilities Article, §7-306(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Number of Accounts per Project.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A subscriber organization may subscribe as many accounts as needed to match each CSEGS's capacity.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An electric company may require a subscriber organization to maintain a minimum average subscription size of 2 kW per customer for an individual CSEGS during the pilot program.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|62|02|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Subscription Credits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Subscriber List.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>List Composition.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A subscriber organization shall provide the electric company with electronic data indicating the proportion of a community solar energy generating system's output that shall be applied to each subscriber's bill.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An electric company may develop an alternative format for processing subscriber lists.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Update Frequency.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A subscriber organization may at any time provide an updated subscriber list to an electric company.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A subscriber organization shall provide an updated subscriber list via the designated electronic portal maintained by the electric company under <cite path="20|62|02|.04|H.">§H of this regulation</cite> or any other format accepted by the electric company.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An electric company shall use the most recent subscriber list provided by a subscriber organization, subject to submission deadlines incorporated by tariff and accepted by the Commission.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An electric company shall apply credits using the most recently updated subscriber list provided by the subscriber organization.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An electric company shall determine the amount of kilowatt hours to be credited to each subscriber by multiplying the subscriber's most recent generation proportion from <cite path="20|62|02|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> by the metered output of the community solar energy generating system.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Application of Subscription Credits.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Unless otherwise directed by the Commission, an electric company may choose to apply the appropriate kilowatt-hour credit from <cite path="20|62|02|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> to each subscriber's bill as either a reduction in metered kilowatt-hour use or a dollar credit to the subscriber's billed amount.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An electric company shall choose the same method for all subscribers in a project.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the electric company chooses to apply the credit from <cite path="20|62|02|.04|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> as a dollar amount, the electric company shall apply a credit no less than the value to the subscriber of the credit had it been applied to the subscriber's bill as a reduction in metered kilowatt hours.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An electric company shall retain a record of a pilot project's kilowatt hours applied to each subscriber's account for a period of 7 years.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Subscription credits shall carry over to the next month's bill until the earlier date on which:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The subscriber's account is closed; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The subscriber's last meter reading prior to the month of April.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Subscriber credits that are not carried over under <cite path="20|62|02|.04|F.">§F of this regulation</cite> shall be handled as excess generation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Electronic Portal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An electric company shall establish and maintain an electronic portal that allows a subscriber organization to provide subscriber lists to the electric company for crediting as required by this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An electric company that has established an electronic portal prior to the effective date of this regulation shall maintain an electronic portal with the capability that is specified in <cite path="20|62|02|.04|H.|(3)">§H(3) of this regulation</cite> for the period of time specified in <cite path="20.62.02.10|B.">COMAR 20.62.02.10B</cite> for each CSEGS in the program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An electric company shall allow a subscriber organization to input data electronically in batches of up to 1,000 subscriber accounts per CSEGS, including the ability to add new subscribers, remove subscribers, and edit the allocations of existing subscribers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Electric companies that do not currently have the capabilities in <cite path="20|62|02|.04|H.|(3)">§H(3) of this regulation</cite> as of the effective date of this regulation shall implement these requirements no later than 12 months from the effective date of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Electric Company Credit Allocation Reporting.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An electric company shall provide a subscriber organization with a report detailing each subscriber's credit allocation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An electric company shall provide the report described in <cite path="20|62|02|.04|I.|(1)">§I(1) of this regulation</cite> no later than the last day of each calendar month following the month of the CSEGS meter reading by the electric company.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|62|02|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Subscription Limitations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A subscriber may not subscribe for an amount of energy that exceeds 200 percent of the value of the subscriber's baseline annual usage including all subscriptions and any net metered generation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Multiple Subscriptions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A customer may purchase multiple subscriptions from one or more CSEGS.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A subscriber's total subscribed credits shall comply with <cite path="20|62|02|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A subscriber may participate in net metering as described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-306">Public Utilities Article, §7-306, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, such that the total of all net-metered generation and subscribed energy does not exceed 200 percent of the value of the subscriber's baseline annual usage.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Credit Payments.</heading>
    <text>An electric company may not refund generation credits to customers except as electric bill credits or as payment for excess generation.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Excess Generation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An electric company shall pay a subscriber a dollar amount of excess generation as reasonably adjusted to exclude the distribution, transmission, and noncommodity portion of the customer's bill unless the electric company records subscriber credits as kilowatt hours.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An electric company that serves electric retail choice customers shall pay the subscriber for kilowatt hours of excess generation at the lesser of the subscriber's retail supply rate or the Standard Offer Service rate in effect at the time of payment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An electric company that does not provide Standard Offer Service shall pay a subscriber for kilowatt hours of excess generation at the electric company's avoided cost of generation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An electric company may pay a subscriber an amount of excess generation as a bill credit if the amount of payment is less than $25.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An electric company shall make a determination to apply §A, B, or C of this regulation in accordance with the type of subscription credits used for the subscriber according to Regulation .04 of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Unsubscribed Energy.</heading>
    <text>An electric company shall file tariffs to pay a subscriber organization for unsubscribed energy in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-306">Public Utilities Article, §7-306</cite>.2(d)(7), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Utility Cost Recovery.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An electric company shall receive full and timely cost recovery of program credit costs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An electric company may not establish a separate surcharge, fee, or rate for recovery of any program costs, including credit and administrative costs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An electric company may include program credit costs in existing rate adjustments for distribution rates or as a revenue or cost component for transmission or commodity rates as accepted by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Program Sunset.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Electric company tariffs requiring payments or credits from an electric company to subscribers in effect during the program shall remain in effect for subscribers for the earlier of 25 years from the date of the end of the program or until the subscriber's contract with its subscriber organization has ended.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An electric company shall continue to facilitate the operation of a subscriber organization that was established during the program for a period of 25 years after the program has ended.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A subscriber organization may continue to operate a community solar energy generating system that was established during the program for a period of 25 years after the program has ended.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A subscriber organization may create, exchange, and trade subscriptions up to the full project capacity for a community solar energy generating system that was established during the program for a period of 25 years after the program has ended</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Billing Accuracy.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission may establish standards for billing accuracy to apply to subscriber credits and billing revenue.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission may direct an electric company to develop additional automated billing and crediting features in order to improve billing accuracy for the program.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-113">2-113</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-306">7-306</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-306">7-306</cite>.1, and 7-306.2, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2016-07-18">Effective date: July 18, 2016 (43:14 Md. R. 781)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-03-21">Regulation .01 amended effective June 15, 2020 (47:12 Md. R. 597); March 21, 2022 (49:6 Md. R. 406)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-03-21">Regulation .02A amended effective June 15, 2020 (47:12 Md. R. 597); March 21, 2022 (49:6 Md. R. 406)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-03-21">Regulation .02C amended effective March 21, 2022 (49:6 Md. R. 406)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-06-15">Regulation .03 amended effective June 15, 2020 (47:12 Md. R. 597)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2022-03-21">Regulation .04 amended effective March 21, 2022 (49:6 Md. R. 406)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="2020-06-15">Regulation .04E amended effective June 15, 2020 (47:12 Md. R. 597)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
