<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Fees Charged to Test Standards and Other Equipment Used by Technicians</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>These regulations set forth the fees that the Department will charge to test the standards of weights and measures and other appropriate equipment possessed and used by any technician and any agency engaged in the maintenance and repair of weighing and measuring devices.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Cast Iron and Steel Weights—Class F Tolerances.</heading>
    <text>The Department shall charge the following fees to test cast iron and steel weights (Class F tolerances):</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the weight is less than or equal to 30 kilograms (66 pounds), the fee is $9 a unit;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the weight is greater than 30 kilograms (66 pounds) but less than or equal to 600 kilograms (1,300 pounds), the fee is $28 a unit;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the weight is greater than 600 kilograms (1,300 pounds) but less than or equal to 1,100 kilograms (2,500 pounds), the fee is $50 a unit;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the weight is greater than 1,100 kilograms (2,500 pounds) but less than or equal to 2,200 kilograms (5,000 pounds), the fee is $69 a unit;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the weight is greater than 2,200 kilograms (5,000 pounds), but less than or equal to 4,500 kilograms (10,000 pounds), the fee is $115 a unit; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If data is included with the certificate of conformance, the fee is $2 a unit.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Class F Tolerances—Test Weight Sets.</heading>
    <text>The Department shall charge the following fees to test a Class F tolerances test weight set provided, however, that the set does not have a total capacity that is greater than 35 kilograms (77 pounds):</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the number of weights in the set is less than or equal to 18, the fee is $57 a set;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the number of weights in the set is greater than 18 but less than or equal to 36, the fee is $80 a set;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the number of weights in the set is greater than 36 the fee is $3 a unit; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If data is included with the certificate of conformance, the fee is $2 a unit.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Other Weighing Services.</heading>
    <text>The Department may provide other weighing services not otherwise noted in this chapter at a rate of $50 an hour.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Equipment Refurbishing.</heading>
    <text>If equipment needs refurbishing before it can be tested and if the Department agrees to refurbish the equipment, the Department shall do this work at the rate of $52 an hour plus an additional $10 for shop materials.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Weight-Moving Equipment for Vehicle Scales.</heading>
    <text>The Department shall charge $140 a unit to test weight-moving equipment for vehicle scales.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Mass Laboratory Standards.</heading>
    <text>The Department shall charge the following fees to test mass laboratory standards:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the standard is less than or equal to 5 kilograms, the fee is $25 a unit;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the standard is greater than 5 kilograms but less than or equal to 30 kilograms, the fee is $60 a unit; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the standard is greater than 30 kilograms but less than or equal to 600 kilograms, the fee is $125 a unit.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Other Services Related to Laboratory Standards of Mass.</heading>
    <text>The Department shall provide other services related to laboratory standards of mass at a rate of $75 an hour.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Volumetric Field Standards.</heading>
    <text>The Department shall charge the following fees to test volumetric field standards:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the standard is less than or equal to 5 gallons (20 liters), the fee is $30 a unit;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the standard is greater than 5 gallons (20 liters) but less than or equal to 26 gallons (100 liters), the fee is $50 a unit;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the standard is greater than 26 gallons (100 liters) but less than or equal to 264 gallons (1,000 liters), the fee is $110 a unit;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the standard is greater than 264 gallons (1,000 liters) but less than or equal to 1,321 gallons (5,000 liters), the fee is $200 a unit;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the standard is greater than 1,321 gallons (5,000 liters), the fee is $250 a unit; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If the standard is for measuring liquefied petroleum gas between 20 gallons and 125 gallons, the fee is $250.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Other Volumetric Calibrations.</heading>
    <text>The Department shall perform other volumetric calibrations not otherwise noted in this chapter at a rate of $50 an hour.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Volumetric Laboratory Standards.</heading>
    <text>The Department shall charge the following fees to test volumetric laboratory standards:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the standard is less than or equal to 4 liters (1 gallon), the fee is $38 each;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the standard is greater than 4 liters (1 gallon) but less than or equal to 40 liters (11 gallons), the fee is $112 each; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the standard is greater than 40 liters (11 gallons) but less than or equal to 400 liters (110 gallons), the fee is $250.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Other Volumetric Calibrations.</heading>
    <text>The Department shall perform other volumetric calibrations not otherwise noted in this chapter at a rate of $45 an hour.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Thermometry and Calibration Services.</heading>
    <text>The Department shall perform thermometry and calibration services at a rate of $65 an hour.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Environmental Chamber Services.</heading>
    <text>For performing environmental chamber services, the Department shall charge as follows:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>$250 per device for use of the chamber; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>$45 per hour for each technician required for testing the device.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Linear Measures and Surveyor Tapes Testing.</heading>
    <text>The Department shall test linear measures at the following rates:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The fees for testing shall be $15 a unit (each interval);</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The fee for testing tapes shall be $15 a unit (each interval); and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The fee for testing other linear devices shall be $50 an hour.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">
      <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|11-205">Agriculture Article, §11-205, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>
    </annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1991-05-13">Effective date: May 13, 1991 (18:9 Md. R. 1011)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-03-02">Regulation .02C and D amended effective March 2, 1992 (19:4 Md. R. 474)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1992-03-02">Regulation .03 amended effective March 2, 1992 (19:4 Md. R. 474)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-02-13">Regulation .07 amended effective February 13, 1995 (22:3 Md. R. 155)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-02-13">Regulation .08 amended effective March 2, 1992 (19:4 Md. R. 474); February 13, 1995 (22:3 Md. R. 155)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" effective="1995-02-13">Regulation .14 amended effective February 13, 1995 (22:3 Md. R. 155)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" discontinuity="true" effective="2000-10-02">Chapter revised effective October 2, 2000 (27:19 Md. R. 1728)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" dest="container" discontinuity="true" effective="2007-12-17">Chapter revised effective December 17, 2007 (34:25 Md. R. 2214)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
